<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Gammer Gvrtons nedle</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>possible author</resp>
               <name>Still, John, 1543?-1608</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>possible author</resp>
               <name>Bridges, John, d. 1618</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>possible author</resp>
               <name>Stevenson, William, d. 1575</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp>
               <name>Lancashire, Ian</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>deposited by <name type="person">Lancashire, Ian</name>
               <name type="institution">University of Toronto</name>
               <name type="place">Toronto</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Canada</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date/>
            </authority>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/3008</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106000072</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106000071</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
      </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Revised version of  <relatedItem type="older" target="http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/1788"/>
            </bibl>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gammer Gvrtons nedle / by Mr S., Mr of Art ; edited by H. F. B. Brett-Smith</title>
                  <editor role="editor">Brett-Smith, H. F. B. (Herbert Francis Brett)</editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xv, 79 p. ; 20 cm.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                  <date>1920</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <seriesStmt>
                  <p>The Percy reprints ; no. 2</p>
               </seriesStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note anchored="true">With facsimile t.-p. of the original ed. published in 1575 under title: A ryght pithy, pleasaunt and  merie comedie: intytuled Gammer Gurton's nedle</note>
                  <note anchored="true">Formerly ascribed to John Still, Bishop of Bath and Wells, or to John Bridges, Bishop of Oxford; later attributed to William Stevenson, of Christ's College, Cambridge, 1551-1561</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notAfter="1575"/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <term type="genre">Comedies -- England -- 16th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Plays -- England -- 16th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-08-31">Header normalised</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="cover">
         <graphic url="http://www.ota.ox.ac.uk/Pages/3008-tp.jpg"/>
      </surface>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage facs="#cover">
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">
                  <title type="main">Gammer Gvrtons Nedle</title>
               </titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <docAuthor>anonymous</docAuthor>
            </byline>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Prologue">
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <l>As Gammer Gurton, with manye a wyde styche </l>
            <l>Sat pesynge &amp; patching of Hodg her mans briche </l>
            <l>By chance or misfortune as shee her geare tost </l>
            <l>In Hodge lether bryches her needle shee lost, </l>
            <l>When Diccon the bedlem had hard by report </l>
            <l>That good Gammer Gurton was robde in thyssorte, </l>
            <l>He quyetly perswaded with her in that stound </l>
            <l>Dame Chather deare gossyp this needle had found, </l>
            <l>Yet knew shee no more of this matter (alas) </l>
            <l>Then knoeth Tom our clarke whatthe Priest saith at masse </l>
            <l>Here of there ensued so fearfull a fraye, </l>
            <l>Mas Doctor was sent for these gossyps to staye, </l>
            <l>Because he was Curate and estemed full wyse </l>
            <l>Who found that he sought not by Diccons deuice, </l>
            <l>When all thinges were tombled and cleane out of fassion </l>
            <l>Whether it were by fortune or some other constellacion </l>
            <l>Sodenlye the neele Hodge found by the prickynge </l>
            <l>And drew it out of his bottocke where he felt it stickynge </l>
            <l>Theyr hartes then atrest with perfect securytie. </l>
            <l>With a pot of good nale they stroake vp theyr plauditie. <pb n="1"/>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div n="A1" type="act">
            <head>The fyrst Acte.</head>
            <div n="S11" type="scene">
               <head>The fyrst Acte. The fyrst Sceane</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Diccon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Many a myle haue I walked, diuers and sundry waies </l>
                  <l>And many a good mans house haue I bin at in my daies </l>
                  <l>Many a gossips cup in my tyme haue I tasted </l>
                  <l>And many a broche and spyt, haue I both turned and basted </l>
                  <l>Many a peece of bacon haue I had out of thir balkes </l>
                  <l>In ronnyng ouer the countrey, with long and were walkes, </l>
                  <l>Yet came my foote neuer, within those doore cheekes, </l>
                  <l>To seeke flesh orfysh Garlyke Onyons or Leekes, </l>
                  <l>That euer I saw a sorte, in such a plyght </l>
                  <l>As here within this house appereth to my syght, </l>
                  <l>There is howlynge and scowlyng, all cast in a dumpe, </l>
                  <l>With whewling and pewling, as though they had lost a trump </l>
                  <l>Syghing and sobbing they weepe and they wayle </l>
                  <l>I maruell in my mynd, whatthe deuill they wayle </l>
                  <l>The olde Trotsyts groning,with alas and alas, </l>
                  <l>And Tib wringes her hands,and takes on in worse case </l>
                  <l>With poore Cocke theyr boye they be dryuen in such fyts </l>
                  <l>I feare mee the folkes be not well in theyr wyts </l>
                  <l>Aske them what they ayle, or who brought them in this staye? </l>
                  <l>They auuswer not at all,but alacke and welaway <pb n="2"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whan I saw it booted not out at doores I hyed mee </l>
                  <l>And caught a slyp of Bacon, when I saw that none spyed mee, </l>
                  <l>Which I intend not far hence vnles my purpose fayle </l>
                  <l>Shall serue for a shoinghorne to draw on two pots of ale. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S12" type="scene">
               <head>The fyrst Acte. The second Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>See so cham arayed with dablynge in the durt </l>
                  <l>She that set me to ditchinge, ich wold she had the squrt </l>
                  <l>Was neuer poore soule that such a life had ? </l>
                  <l>Gogs bones thys vylthy glaye hase drest mee to bad </l>
                  <l>Gods soule, see how this stuffe teares </l>
                  <l>Iche were better to bee a Bearward and set to keepe Beares </l>
                  <l>By the Masse here is a gasshe, a sharnefull hole in deade </l>
                  <l>And one stytch teare furder, a man may thruste in his heade </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>By my fathers soule Hodge, if I shulde now be sworne </l>
                  <l>I can not chuse but say thy breech is foule be-torne </l>
                  <l>But the next remedye in such acaseand hap </l>
                  <l>Is to plaunche on a piece, as brode as thy cap. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs soule man, tis not yet two dayes fully ended </l>
                  <l>Synce my dame Gurton (chem sure) these breches amended, <pb n="3"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>But cham made such a drudge to trudge at euery neede </l>
                  <l>Chwold rend it though it were stitched wyth sturdy pacthreede, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Hoge, let thy breeches go, and speake and tell mee soone </l>
                  <l>What deuill ayleth gammer gurton, &amp; Tib her mayd to frowne, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Tush man thart deceyued tys theyr dayly looke, </l>
                  <l>They coure so ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coles, theyr eyes be bleard with smooke, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Nay by the masse, I perfectly perceiued as </l>
                  <l>I came hether </l>
                  <l>That eyther Tib &amp; her dame hath ben by the eares together </l>
                  <l>Or els as great a matter as thou shalt shortly see. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Now iche beseeche our Lord they neuer better agree. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>By gogs soule there they syt as still as stones in the streite </l>
                  <l>As though they had ben taken with fairies or els w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> some il sprite </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs hart, I durst haue layd my cap to a crowne </l>
                  <l>Chwould lerne of some prancome as sone as ich came to town. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Why Hodge art thou inspyred? or dedst thou therof here? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Nay but ich saw such a wonder as ich saw nat ths vii. yere </l>
                  <l>Tome Tannkards Cow (be gogs bones) she set me vp her saile </l>
                  <l>And flynging about his halfe aker fysking with her taile, </l>
                  <l>As thoughthere had ben in her ars a swarme of Bees, </l>
                  <l>And chad not cryed tphrowh hoore shead lept out of his Lees. <pb n="4"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Why Hodg lies the connyng in Tom tankards cowes taile? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Well ich chaue hard some say such tokens do not fayle, </l>
                  <l>But canst y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not tell in faith Diccon, why she frownes or wher at </l>
                  <l>Hath no man stolne her Ducks or Henes, or gelded gyb her Cat </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>What deuyll can I tell man, I cold not haue one word </l>
                  <l>They gaue no more hede to my talk then thou woldst to a lorde </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Iche can not styll but muse what meruaylous thinge it is </l>
                  <l>Chyll in and know my selfe what matters are arnys. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Then farewell hodge a while, synce thou doest inward hast, </l>
                  <l>For I will into the good wyfe Chats, to feele how the ale dooth taste. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S13" type="scene">
               <head>The fyrst Acte. The thyrd Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Hodge. Tyb.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>CHam agast by the masse, ich wot not what to do </l>
                  <l>Chad nede blesse me well before ich go them to </l>
                  <l>Perchaunce sonie felon sprit may haunt our house indeed, </l>
                  <l>And then chwere but a noddy to venter where cha no neede </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib</speaker>
                  <l>Cham worse then mad by the masse to be at this staye <pb n="5"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cham chyd cham blamd, and beaton all thoures on the daye, </l>
                  <l>Lamed and hunger storued, prycked vp all in Jagges </l>
                  <l>Hauyng no patch to hyde my backe, saue a few rotten ragges. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>I say Tyb, if thou be Tyb, as I trow sure thou bee, </l>
                  <l>What deuyll make a doe is this betweene our dame and thee. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Gogsbreade Hodg thou had a good turne thou warte not here this while. </l>
                  <l>It had ben better for some of vs to haue ben hence a myle </l>
                  <l>My Gammer is so out of course, and frantyke all at ones </l>
                  <l>That Cocke our boy, &amp; I poore wench haue felt it on our bones. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>What is the matter, say on Tib wherat she taketh so on. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>She is vndone she sayth (alas,) her ioye and life is gone </l>
                  <l>If shee here not of some comfort, she is sayth but dead </l>
                  <l>Shall neuer come within her lyps, one inch of meate ne bread. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Bur Ladie cham not very glad, to see her in this dumpe </l>
                  <l>Cholde a noble her stole hath fallen, &amp; shee hath broke her rumpe </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Nay and that were the worst, we wold not greatly care </l>
                  <l>For bursting of her huckle bone, or breakyng of her Chaire </l>
                  <l>But greatter greater is her grief, as hodge we shall all feele. <pb n="6"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs woundes Tyb, my gammer has neuer lost her Neele? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ryb</speaker>
                  <l>Her Neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Her Neele? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>rib</speaker>
                  <l>Her neele by him that made me, it is true Hodge </l>
                  <l>I tell thee. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs sacrament, I would she had lost tharte out of her bellie </l>
                  <l>The Deuill or els his dame, they ought her sure a shame </l>
                  <l>How a murryon came this chaunce. (say Tib) vnto our dame? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>My gammer sat her downe on her pes, &amp; bad me reach thy breeches </l>
                  <l>And by &amp; by, a vengeance in it or she had take two stitches </l>
                  <l>To clap a clout vpon thine ars, by chaunce a syde she leares </l>
                  <l>And gyb our cat in the milke pan, she spied ouer head and eares </l>
                  <l>Ah hore out thefe she cryed aloud, &amp; swapt the breches downe </l>
                  <l>Up went her staffe, and out leapt gyb, at doors into the towne </l>
                  <l>And synce that time was neuer wyght, cold set their eies vpon it </l>
                  <l>Gogs malison chaue Cocke and I, byd twenty times light on it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>And is not then my breches sewid vp, to morow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I shuld were </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>No in faith hodge thy breeches lie, for al this neuer the nere. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Now a vengeance light on al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> sort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> better shold haue kept it, </l>
                  <l>The cat the house, and tib our maid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> better shold haue swept it <pb n="7"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Se where she commeth crawling come on in twenty deuils way </l>
                  <l>Ye haue made a fayre daies worke haue you not? pray you say. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S14" type="scene">
               <head>The fyrste Acte. The.iiii. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Gammer. Hodge. Tyb. Cocke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>ALas hoge, alas I may well cursse and ban </l>
                  <l>This daie that euer I saw it, with gyb and the inylke pan </l>
                  <l>For these and ill lucke to gather, as knoweth </l>
                  <l>Cocke my boye </l>
                  <l>Haue stacke away my deare neele, and robd me of my boye </l>
                  <l>My fayre longe strayght neele that was myne one y treasure </l>
                  <l>The fyrst day of my sorow is, and last end of my pleasure. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Might ha kept it when ye had it, but fooles will be fooles styll. </l>
                  <l>Lose that is vast in your handes, ye meede not but ye will. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Go hie thee tib, and run thou hoore, to thend here of the towne </l>
                  <l>Didst cary out dust in thy lap, seeke wher thou porest it downe </l>
                  <l>And as thou sawest me roking, in the asshes where I morned. </l>
                  <l>So see in all the heape of dust, thou leaue no straw vnturned. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>That chal gammer swythe and tyte, and sone be here agayne. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Tib stoope &amp; loke downe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground to it, &amp; take some paine. <pb n="8"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Here is a prety matter, to see this gere how it goes </l>
                  <l>By gogs soule I thenk you wold loes your ars, and it were loose </l>
                  <l>Your neele lost, it is pitie you shold lack care and endlesse sorow </l>
                  <l>Gogs deth how shall my breches be sewid, shall I go thus to morow </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Ah hodg, hodg, if that ich cold find my neele by the reed </l>
                  <l>Chould sow thy breches ich promise y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> full good double threed </l>
                  <l>And set a patch on either knee, shuld last this monethes twaine </l>
                  <l>Now god &amp; good Saint Sithe I praye, to send it home againe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Wherto serued your hands &amp; eies, but this your neele to kepe </l>
                  <l>What deuill had you els to do, ye kept ich wot no sheepe </l>
                  <l>Cham faine a brode to dyg and delue, in water, myre and claye </l>
                  <l>Sossing and possing in the durte, styll from day to daye </l>
                  <l>A hundred thinges that be abrode, cham set to see them weele </l>
                  <l>And foure of you syt idle at home, and can not keepe a neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>My neele alas ich lost it hodge, what time ich me vp hasted </l>
                  <l>To saue the milke set vp for the, which gib our cat hath wasted </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>The Deuill he burst both gib, and Tib, with all the rest </l>
                  <l>Cham alwayes sure of the worst end, who euer haue the best <pb n="9"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where ha you ben fidging abrode, since you your neele lost </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Withm the house and at the dore, sittmg by this same post </l>
                  <l>Wher I was loking a long howre, before these folks came here, </l>
                  <l>But welaway, all was in vayne, my neele is neuer the nere. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Set me a candle, let me seeke and grope where euer it bee </l>
                  <l>Gogs hart ye be so folish (ich thinke) you knowe it not when you it see </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Come hether Cocke what Cocke I say. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>Howe Gammer. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>r</speaker>
                  <l>Goe hye thee soone and grope behynd the old brasse pan, </l>
                  <l>Whych thing when thou hast done </l>
                  <l>Ther shalt thou fynd an old shooe, wher in if thou looke well </l>
                  <l>Thou shalt fynd lyeng an inche of a whyte tallow candell, </l>
                  <l>Lyght it, and brynge it tite awaye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>That shalbe done anone. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Nay tary hodg til thou hast light, and then weele seke ech one. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Cum away ye horson boy, are ye a slepe; ye must haue a crier. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>Ich cannot get the candel light here is almost no fler. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chil hold the a peny chil make ye come if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ich may catch thine eares </l>
                  <l>Art deffe thou horson boy ? cocke I say, why canst not heares. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Beate hym not Hodge but help the boy and come you two togethe. <pb n="10"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S15" type="scene">
               <head>The.i.Acte The.v.Sceane</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Gammer. Tyb. Cocke. Hodge</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>How now Tyb quycke lets here,what newes thou hast brought hether </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Chaue tost and tumbled yender heap our &amp; ouer againe </l>
                  <l>And winowed it through my fingers as men wold winow grain </l>
                  <l>No so much as a hens turd but in pieces I tare it </l>
                  <l>Or what so euer clod or clay I found, I did not spare it </l>
                  <l>Lokyng within and eke without, to fynd your neele (alas) </l>
                  <l>But all in vaine and without help, your neele is where it was. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Alas my neele we shall neuer meete, adue, adue for aye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Not so gammer, we niyght it fynd f we knew where it laye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs crosse Gammer if ye will laugh looke in but at the doore </l>
                  <l>And see how Hodg lieth tomblynge and tossmg amids the floure </l>
                  <l>Rakyng there some fyre to find amonge the asshes dead </l>
                  <l>Where there is not one sparke, so byg as a pyns head, </l>
                  <l>At last in a darke corner two sparkes he thought he sees </l>
                  <l>Which were mdede nought els but Gyb our cats two eyes <pb n="11"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Puffe quod hodg thinking therby to haue fyre without doubt </l>
                  <l>With that Gyb shut her two eyes, &amp; so the fyre was out </l>
                  <l>And by and by them opened, euen as they were before, </l>
                  <l>With that the sparkes appered euen as they had done of yore, </l>
                  <l>And euen as hodge blew the fire as he did thincke </l>
                  <l>Gyb as she felt the blast strayght way began to wyncke, </l>
                  <l>Tyll Hodge fell of swering as came best to his turne, </l>
                  <l>The fier was sure bewicht and therfore wold not burne: </l>
                  <l>At last Gyb vp the stayers, among the old postes and pinnes, </l>
                  <l>And Hodge he hied him after till broke were both his shinnes: </l>
                  <l>Cursynge and swermg othes, were neuer of his makyng, </l>
                  <l>That Gyb wold fyre the house, if that shee were not taken. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>See here is all the thought that the foolysh Urchyn taketh, </l>
                  <l>And Tyb me thinke at his elbowe almost as mery maketh </l>
                  <l>This is all the wyt ye haue when others make their mone, </l>
                  <l>Come downe Hodge, where art thou and let the Cat alone. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs harte, help and come vp, Gyb in her tayle hath fyre, </l>
                  <l>And is like to burne all if shee get a lytle hier: </l>
                  <l>Cum downe (quoth you,) nay then you might count me a patch, <pb n="12"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>The house commeth downe on your heads if it take ons y thatch. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>It is the cats eyes foole that shineth in the darke. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Hath the Cat do you thinke in euery eye a sparke. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cammer</speaker>
                  <l>No, but they shyne as lyke fyre as euer man see. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse and she burne all, yoush beare the blame for mee </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Cum downe &amp; help to seeke here our neele that it were found </l>
                  <l>Downe Tyb on the knees I say,downe Cocke to the ground. </l>
                  <l>To God I make a vowe, and so to good Saint Anne </l>
                  <l>A candell shall they haue a peece, get it where I can, </l>
                  <l>If I may my neele find in one place or in other. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Now a vengeaunce on gib light, on gyb and gybs mother </l>
                  <l>And all the generacyon of Cats both far and nere </l>
                  <l>Looke on the ground horson thinks thou the neele is here. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>By my trouth gammer me thought your neele here I saw </l>
                  <l>But when my fyngers toucht it, I felt it was a straw. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>SeeHodgewhats thys mayitiiotbe within it, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Breake it foole with thy hand and see and thou canst fynde it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Nay breake it you Hodge accordyng to your word. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs sydes fye it styncks; it is a Cats tourd, </l>
                  <l>It were well done to make thee eate it by the masse. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>This matter amendeth not my neele is still where it wasse <pb n="13"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our candle is at an ende let vs all in quight </l>
                  <l>And come another tyme, when we haue more lyght </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="A2" type="act">
            <head>The.ii. Acte.</head>
            <div type="Song">
               <head>The.ii. Acte. Fyrste a Songe.</head>
               <sp>
                  <l>Backe and syde go bare, go bare, booth foote and hande go colde: </l>
                  <l>But Bellye god sende thee good ale ynoughe, whether it be newe or olde. </l>
                  <l>I Can not eate but lytle meate, my stomacke is not good: </l>
                  <l>But sure I thmke that I can drynke with him that weares a hood. </l>
                  <l>Thoughe I go bare take ye no care, I am nothinge a colde: </l>
                  <l>I stuffe my skyn so full within, of ioly good Ale and olde. </l>
                  <l>Backe and syde go bare go bare, booth foote and hand go colde: </l>
                  <l>But belly god send the good ale inoughe whether it be new or olde. </l>
                  <l>I loue no rost but a nut browne toste and a Crab layde in the fyre, </l>
                  <l>A lytle bread shall do me stead much breade I not desyre: </l>
                  <l>No froste nor snow, no winde I trowe can hurte mee if I wolde, </l>
                  <l>I am so wrapt, and throwly lapt of ioly good ale and olde. </l>
                  <l>Backe and syde go bare &amp;c. <pb n="14"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Tyb my wyfe that as her lyfe loueth well good ale to seeke, </l>
                  <l>Full ofte drynkes shee tyll ye may see the teares run downe her cheekes: </l>
                  <l>Then dooth she trowle to mee the bowle euen as a mault worme shuld, </l>
                  <l>And sayth sweete hart I tooke my part of this ioly good ale and olde. </l>
                  <l>Backe and syde go bare &amp;c. </l>
                  <l>Now let them drynke tyll they nod and winke, euen as good felowes shoulde doe </l>
                  <l>They shall not mysse to haue the blisse, good ale doth bringe men to: </l>
                  <l>And all poore soules that haue scowred boules or haue them lustely trolde, </l>
                  <l>God saue the lyues of them and theyr wyues whether they be yonge or olde. </l>
                  <l>Backe and syde go bare &amp;c. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S21" type="scene">
               <head>The fyrst Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Diccon. Hodge.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Well done be Gogs malt well songe and well sayde, </l>
                  <l>Come on mother Chat as thou art true mayde. </l>
                  <l>One fresh pot of ale lets see to make an ende </l>
                  <l>Agaynst this colde wether, my maked armes to defende, </l>
                  <l>This gere it warms the soule, now wind blow on the worst, </l>
                  <l>And let us drink and swill, till that our bellies burste </l>
                  <l>Now were he a wyse man, by cunnynge colde defyne </l>
                  <l>Which way my Iourney lyeth or where Dyccon will dyne <pb n="15"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>But one good turne I haue be it by nyght or daye </l>
                  <l>South East North or west I am neuer out of my waye </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chym goodly rewarded, cham I not, do you thyncke? </l>
                  <l>Chad a goodly dynner for all my seate and swyncke, </l>
                  <l>Neyther butter cheese, mylke onyons fleshe nor fyshe </l>
                  <l>Saue thys poor pece of barly bread, tis a pleas costly dishe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Haile fellow Hodge &amp; well to fare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy meat, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue any? </l>
                  <l>But by thy words as I then smelled thy damtrels be not manye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Daintrels diccon (gogs soule man) saue this pece of dry horsbred, </l>
                  <l>Cha byt no byt this lyue longe daie no crome come in my hed </l>
                  <l>My gutts they yawle crawle and all my be rumbleth </l>
                  <l>The puddynges can not lye still ech one ouer other tumbleth </l>
                  <l>By gogs harte cham so vente and in my belly pende </l>
                  <l>Chould one peece were at the spittlehouse another at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> castels ende. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Why hodge was there none at home thy dinner for to set: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Godgs bread Diccon ich came to late, was nothing ther to get </l>
                  <l>Gib (a fowle feind might on her hght) lick y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> milke pan so clene </l>
                  <l>See Diccon, twas not so wellwasht this .vii. yere as ich wene <pb n="16"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>A pestilence lyght on all ill lucke, chad thought yet for all thys </l>
                  <l>Of a morsell of bacon behynde the dore at worst shuld not misse, </l>
                  <l>But when ich sought a slyp to cut, as ich was wont to do </l>
                  <l>Gogs soule Diccon, gyb our Cat had eate the bacon to. </l>
               </sp>
               <note anchored="true">Which bacon Diccon stole, as is declared before.</note>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Ill luck quod he mary swere it hodg, this day ye trueth to tel </l>
                  <l>Thou rose not on thy right syde, or els blest thee not wel, </l>
                  <l>Thy mylk slopt vp thy bacon filtched, that was to bad luck hodg. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Nay nay ther was a fowler fault, my gammer ga me ye dodge </l>
                  <l>Seest not how cham rent &amp; torn, my heels, my knees &amp; my breech </l>
                  <l>Chad thought as ich sat by the fire, help here &amp; there a stitch, </l>
                  <l>But there ich was powpte indeede. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Why Hodge? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Bootes not man to tell, </l>
                  <l>Cham so drest amonst a sorte of fooles, chad better be in hell, </l>
                  <l>My gammer (cham ashamed to say) by god serued me not weele </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>How so Hodge? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Bootes not man to tell, </l>
                  <l>Cham so drest amonst a sorte of fooles, chad better be in hell, </l>
                  <l>My gammer (chain ashamed to say)by god serued me not weele </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>How so Hodge? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Hase she not gone trowest now and lost her neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Her Eele Hodge who fysht of late? that was a damty dysh. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Tush tush, her neele, her neele, her neele man. Tys neyther flesh nor fysh. <pb n="17"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>A lytle thing with an hole in the end, as bright as any syller, </l>
                  <l>Small, longe, sharpe at the poynt, &amp; straight as any pyller. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I know not what a deuil y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> menest, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> brigst me more in doubt </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Knowest not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what tom tailers man, sits broching throughe a clout </l>
                  <l>A neele, neele, a neele, my gammers neele is gone. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Her neele Hodge, now I smel thee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was a chaunce alone, </l>
                  <l>By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> masse y<hi rend="sup">n</hi> hadst a shamefull losse &amp; it wer but for thy breches </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs soule man chould giue a crown chad it but iii stitches. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>How sayest y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> Hodg, what shuld he haue, again thy neele got </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Bem vathers soule, and chad it chould giue him a new grot. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Canst thou keepe counsaile in this case. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Els chwold my tonge were out. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Do thou but then by my aduise, &amp; I will fetch it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubt, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chyll runne chyll ryde, chyll dygge, chyl delue, chill toyle, chill trudge shalt see: </l>
                  <l>Chill hold chil drawe, chil pull, chill pynche chill kneele on my bare knee. </l>
                  <l>Chill scrape chill scratche, chill skte, chyll seeke, chill bowe, chill bende, chill sweate, </l>
                  <l>Chil stoop, chil stur, chil cap chil knele, chil crepe on hands &amp; feete, </l>
                  <l>Chil be thy bondman Diccon, ich sweare by sunne and moone </l>
                  <l>And channot sum what to stop this gap, chaiu vtterly vndone </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">Pointing behind to his torne breeches</stage>
               <pb n="18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Why, is ther any special cause, thou takest hereat such sorow </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Kirstian Clack Tom simsons maid, bi the masse coms hether to morow </l>
                  <l>Chamnot able to say, betweene vs what may hap, </l>
                  <l>She smyled on me the last sonday when ich put of my cap, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Well Hodge this is a matter of weight, &amp; must be kept close, </l>
                  <l>It might els turne to both our costes as the world now gose, </l>
                  <l>Shalt sware to be no blab Hodge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chyll Diccon. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Then go to, </l>
                  <l>Lay thine haud here say after me as thou shalt here me do </l>
                  <l>Haste no booke? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Cha no booke I. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Then needes must force vs both, </l>
                  <l>Upon my breech to lay thme hand, and there to take thme othe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>I Hodge breechele, </l>
                  <l>Sweare to Diccon rechelesse </l>
                  <l>By the crosse that I shall kysse, </l>
                  <l>To kepe his counsaile close </l>
                  <l>And alwayes me to dispose </l>
                  <l>To worke that his pleasure is. </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">Here he kysseth Diccons breeche.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Now Hodge see thou take heede </l>
                  <l>And do as I thee byd </l>
                  <l>For so I iudge it meete, </l>
                  <l>This nedle againe to win </l>
                  <l>Thgere is no shift therin </l>
                  <l>But coniure vp a spreet. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>What the great deuill Diccon I saye? <pb n="19"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Yea in good faith, that is the waye, </l>
                  <l>Fet with some prety charme. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodgc</speaker>
                  <l>Softe Diccon be not to hasty yet, </l>
                  <l>By the masse for ich begyn to sweat </l>
                  <l>Cham afrayde of some harme. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Come hether then and sturre the nat </l>
                  <l>One mche out of this Cyrcle plat </l>
                  <l>But stande as I thee teache. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>And shall ich be here safe from theyr clawes: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>The mayster deuill with his longe pawes </l>
                  <l>Here to thee can not reache: </l>
                  <l>Now will I settle me to this geare. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>I saye Diccon heare me heare: </l>
                  <l>Go softely to thys matter. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>What deuyll man art afraide of nought </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Canst not tarrye a lytle thought </l>
                  <l>Tyll ich make a curtesie of water. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Stand still to it why shuldest thou fearehym? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs sydes Diccon me thinke ich heare him </l>
                  <l>And tarrye chal mare all. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>The matter is no worse then I tolde it, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse cham able no longer to holde it, </l>
                  <l>To bad iche must beraye the hall. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Stand to it Hodge sture not you horson, </l>
                  <l>What Deuyll be thine ars strynges brusten? </l>
                  <l>Thy selfe a while but staye, </l>
                  <l>The deuill I smell hym wyll be here anone. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Hold him fast Diccon, cham gone, cham gone </l>
                  <l>Chyll not be at that fraye. <pb n="20"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S22" type="scene">
               <head>The .ii. Acte. The ii. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Diccon. Chat.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Fy shytten knaue, and out vpon thee </l>
                  <l>Aboue all other loutes fye on thee, </l>
                  <l>Is not here a clenly prancke? </l>
                  <l>But thy matter was no better </l>
                  <l>Nor thy presence here no sweter, </l>
                  <l>To flye I can the thanke: </l>
                  <l>Here is a matter worthy glosynge </l>
                  <l>Of Gammer Gurtons nedle losynge </l>
                  <l>And a foule peece of warke, </l>
                  <l>A man I thyncke myght make a playe </l>
                  <l>And nede no worde to this they saye </l>
                  <l>Being but halfe a Clarke. </l>
                  <l>Softe let me alone I will take the charge </l>
                  <l>This matter further to enlarge </l>
                  <l>Withm a tyme shorte, </l>
                  <l>If ye will marke my toyes and note </l>
                  <l>I will geue ye leaue to cut my throte </l>
                  <l>If I make not good sporte, </l>
                  <l>Dame Chat I say where be ye within? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Who haue we there maketh such a din: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Here is a good fellow maketh no great daunger, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>What diccon? come nere ye be no straunger, </l>
                  <l>We be fast set at trumpe man hard by the fyre, </l>
                  <l>Thou shalt set on the king if thou come a litle nyer. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nay, there is no tarying: I must be gone againe </l>
                  <l>But first for you in councel I haue a word or twaine. <pb n="21"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Come hether Dol, Dol, sit downe and play this game, </l>
                  <l>And as thou sawest me do, see thou do euen the same </l>
                  <l>Thereis 5. trumps beside the Queene, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hindmost y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> shalt finde her </l>
                  <l>Take hede of Sim glouers wife, she hath an eie behind her, </l>
                  <l>Now Diccon say your will. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Nay softe a litle yet, </l>
                  <l>I wold not tel it my sister, the inatter is so great, </l>
                  <l>There I wil haue you sweare by our dere Lady of Bullaine, </l>
                  <l>S Dunstoue, and S. Donnyke, with the three Kinges of Kullaine, </l>
                  <l>That ye shal keepe it secret. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs bread that will I doo, </l>
                  <l>As secret as mine owne thought, by god aud the deuil two. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Here is gammer gurton your neighbour, a sad heuy wight </l>
                  <l>Her goodly faire red Cock, at home, was stole this last night. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs soule her Cock with the yelow legs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nightly crowed so iust? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>That cocke is stollen. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>What was he fet out of the heus ruste? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I cau not tel where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil he was kept, vnder key or locke, </l>
                  <l>But Tib hath tykled in Gaminers eare, that you shoulde steale the cocke </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Haue I strouge hoore? by bread aud salte. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>What softe I say be styl. </l>
                  <l>Say hot one word for all this geare. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>By the inasse that I wyl, <pb n="22"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>I wil haue the yong hore by the head, &amp; the old trot by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throte </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Not one word dame Chat I say, not one word for my cote. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Shall such a begars brawle as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thinkest y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> make me a theefe </l>
                  <l>The pocks light on her hores sydes, a pestlence &amp; a mischeefe </l>
                  <l>Come out thou hungry nedy bytche, o that my nails be short. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs bred woman hold your peace this gere wil els passe sport </l>
                  <l>I wold not for an hundred pound this matter shuld be knowen, </l>
                  <l>That I am auctour of this tale or haue abrode it blowen </l>
                  <l>Did ye not sweare ye wold be ruled before the tale I tolde </l>
                  <l>I said ye must all secret keepe and ye said sure ye wolde. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Wolde you suffer your selfe diccon such a sort, to reuile you </l>
                  <l>With slaunderous words to blot your name, &amp; so to defile you? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>No goodwife chat I wold be loth such drabs shulde blot my name </l>
                  <l>But yet ye must so order all, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Diccon beare no blame. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Go to then, what is your rede? say on your minde, ye shall mee rule herein. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Godamercye to dame chat, in faith thou must the gere begin </l>
                  <l>It is twenty pound to a goose turd, my gammer will not tary </l>
                  <l>But hetherward she comes as fast as her legs can her cary, <pb n="23"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>To brawle with you about her cocke, for well I hard Tib say </l>
                  <l>The Cocke was rosted in your house, to breafast yesterday, </l>
                  <l>And when ye had the carcas eaten, the fethers ye out flunge </l>
                  <l>And Doll your maid the legs she hid a foote depe in the dunge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>0h gracyous god my harte it burstes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Well rule your selfe a space </l>
                  <l>And gammer gurton when she commeth anon into thys place </l>
                  <l>Then to the Queane lets see tell her your inynd &amp; spare not </l>
                  <l>So shall Diccon blamelesse bee, and then go to I care not. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Then hoore beware her throte, I can abide no longer </l>
                  <l>In faith old witch it shalbe seene, which of vs two be stronger </l>
                  <l>And Diccon but at your request, I wold not stay one howre. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Well keepe it in till she be here, and then out let it powre, </l>
                  <l>In the meane while get you in, and make no wordes of this </l>
                  <l>More of this matter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this howre to here you shall not misse </l>
                  <l>Because I know you are iny freind, hide it I cold not doubtles </l>
                  <l>Ye know your harm, see ye be wise about your owne busines </l>
                  <l>So fare ye well. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Nay soft Diccon and drynke, what Doll I say </l>
                  <l>Bringe here a cup of the best ale, lets see, come quicly awaye. <pb n="24"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S23" type="scene">
               <head>The ii. Actt. The iii.Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Ye see masters y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one end tapt of this my short deuise </l>
                  <l>Now must we broche thoter to, before the smoke arise </l>
                  <l>And by the time they haue a while run, I trust ye need not craue it, </l>
                  <l>But loke what heth in both their harts ye ar hke sure to haue it </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodgc</speaker>
                  <l>Yea gogs soule, art aliue yet? what Diccon dare ich come? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>A man is wel hied to trust to thee, I will say nothing but inum </l>
                  <l>But and ye come any nearer I pray you see all be sweete. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Tush man is gammers neele found, that chould gladly weete </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>She may thanke thee it is not found, for if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> had kept thy standing </l>
                  <l>The deuil he wold haue fet it out, euen hodg at thy commaunding </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs hart, &amp; cold he tel nothing wher the neele might be found </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Ye folysh dolt, ye were to seek ear we had got our ground, </l>
                  <l>Therfore his tale so doubtfull was, that I cold not perceiue it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Then ich se wel something was said, chope one day yet to haue it, </l>
                  <l>But diccon, diccon, did not the deuill cry ho, ho, ho, <pb n="25"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hadst taryed where thou stoodst, thou woldest haue said so </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Durst swere of a boke, chard him rore, streight after ich was gon </l>
                  <l>But tel me diccon what said y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knaue: let me here it anon. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>The horson talked to mee. I know not well of what </l>
                  <l>One whyle his tonge it ran and paltered of a Cat, </l>
                  <l>Another whyle he stamered styll vppon a Rat, </l>
                  <l>Last of all there was nothing but euery word </l>
                  <l>Chat, Chat, </l>
                  <l>But this I well perceyued before I wolde him rid, </l>
                  <l>Betweene Chat and the Rat and the Cat, the nedle is hyd, </l>
                  <l>Now wether Gyb our cat haue eate it in her mawe, </l>
                  <l>Or Doctor Rat our curat haue found it in the straw, </l>
                  <l>Or this dame chat your neighbour haue stollen it, god hee knoweth </l>
                  <l>But by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morow at this time, we shal learn how the inatter goeth </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Canst not learn to night man, seest not what is here, </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">Pointyng behind to his torne breeches.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Tys not possyble to make it sooner appere, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Alas Diccon then chaue no shyft but least ich tary to longe </l>
                  <l>Hye me to Sym glouers shop, theare to seeke for a Thonge, </l>
                  <l>Ther with this breech to tatche and tye as ich may. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>To inorow hodg if we chaunce to meete, shalt see what I will say. <pb n="26"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S24" type="scene">
               <head>The ii. Acte. The iiii. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Diccon. Gammer.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Now this gere must torward goe, for here my gammer commeth, </l>
                  <l>Be still a while &amp; say nothing, make here a litle romth. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Good lord, shall neuer be my lucke my neele agayne to spye? </l>
                  <l>Alas the whyle tys past my helpe, where tis still it must lye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Now Iesus gammer gurton, what driueth you to this sadnes: </l>
                  <l>I feare me by my conscience you will sure fall to madnes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Who is that, what Diccon chaue lost man fye fye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Mary fy on them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be worthy, but what shuld be your troble, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Alas the more ich thinke on it, my sorow it waxeth doble </l>
                  <l>My goodly tossing sporyars neele, chaue lost ich wot not where. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Your neele whan? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>My neele (alas ich myght full ill it spare, </l>
                  <l>As god him selfe he knoweth nere one besyde chaue. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>If th s be all good gammer, I warrant you all is saue. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Why know you any tydings which way my neele is gone? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Yea that I do doubtlesse, as ye shall here anone, <pb n="27"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>A see a thing this inatter toucheth within these .xx. howres, </l>
                  <l>Euen at this gate, before my face, by a neyghbour of yours, </l>
                  <l>She stooped ine downe, and vp she toke a nedle or a pyn: </l>
                  <l>I durst be sworne it was euen yours, by all my mothers kyn. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>It was iny neele diccon ich wot, for here euen by this poste </l>
                  <l>Ich sat, what time as ich vp starte, and so my neele it loste: </l>
                  <l>Who was it leiue son? speke ich pray the, &amp; quickly tell me that? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>A suttle queane as any in thys Towne your neyghboure here dame Chat. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Dame chat diccon let me be gone, chil thyther in post haste. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Take my councell yet or ye go, for feare ye walke in wast, </l>
                  <l>It is a inurrion crafty drab and froward to be pleased, </l>
                  <l>And ye take not the better way our nedle yet ye lose it: </l>
                  <l>For when she tooke it vp euen here before your doores </l>
                  <l>What soft dame chat (quoth I) that same is none of yours </l>
                  <l>Auant (quoth she) syr knaue, what pratest thou of that I fynd: </l>
                  <l>I wold y hadst kist me I wot whear: (she inent I know behind) </l>
                  <l>And home she went as brag, as it had ben a bodelouce, </l>
                  <l>And I after as bold, as it had ben, the goodinan of the house: </l>
                  <l>But there and ye had hard her, how she began to scolde </l>
                  <l>The tonge it went on patins, by hym that judas solde, </l>
                  <l>Ech other worde I was a knaue, and you a hore of hores, </l>
                  <l>Because I spake in your behalfe, and sayde the neele was yours. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs bread, and thinks y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> callet thus to kepe my neele me fro? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Let her alone, and she minds non other but euen to dresse you so </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse chil rather spend the cote that is on my backe </l>
                  <l>Thinks the false quean by such a slyght, that chill my neele lacke </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Slepe not your gere I counsell you, but of this take good hede </l>
                  <l>Let not be knowen I told you of it, how well soeuer ye spede. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Chil in Diccon a cleene aperne to take, and set before me, </l>
                  <l>And ich may my neele once see, chil sure remember the </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S25" type="scene">
               <head>The ii. Acte. The v. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Diccon.</stage>
               <pb n="28"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>HEre will the sporte begin, if these two once may meete. </l>
                  <l>Their chere durst lay money will proue scarsly sweete </l>
                  <l>My gammer sure entends, to be vppon her bones, </l>
                  <l>With staues, or with clubs, or els with coble stones. <pb n="29"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dame Chat on the other syde, it she be far behynde </l>
                  <l>I am right far deceiued she is geuen to it of </l>
                  <l>He that may tarry by it a whyle, and that but shorte </l>
                  <l>I warrant hym trust to it, he shall see all the sporte </l>
                  <l>Into the towne will I, my frendes to vysit there </l>
                  <l>And hether straight againe to see thend of this gere </l>
                  <l>In the meane time felowes, pype vpp your fiddles, </l>
                  <l>I saie take them </l>
                  <l>And let your freyndes here such mirth as ye can make them. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="A3" type="act">
            <head>The.iii. Acte.</head>
            <div n="S31" type="scene">
               <head>The iii. Acte. The i. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Hodge.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>SYm glouer yet gramercy, chain meetlye well sped now, </l>
                  <l>Thart euen as good a felow as euer kyste a cowe, </l>
                  <l>Here is a thonge in dede, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> masse though ich speake it </l>
                  <l>Tom tankards great bald curtal, I thinke could not breake it </l>
                  <l>And when he spyed my neede to lie so straight and hard, </l>
                  <l>Hays lent me here his naull, to set the gyb for-ward, </l>
                  <l>As for my Gammers neele, the flyenge feynd go weete, </l>
                  <l>Chill not now go to the doore againe with it to meete: <pb n="30"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Chould make shyfe good inough and chad a candels ende, </l>
                  <l>The cheefe hole in my breeche, with these two chil amende. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S32" type="scene">
               <head>The iii. Acte. The i.i.. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Gammer. Hodge.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>HOw Hodge, mayst nowe be glade, cha newes to tell thee </l>
                  <l>Ich knowe who hais my neele, ich trust soone shalt it see </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>The deuyll thou does, hast hard gammer in deede, or doest but iest </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Tys as true as steele Hodge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Why, knowest well where dydst leese it? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Ich know who found it, and tooke it vp shalt see or it be longe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gods mother dere, if that be true, farwel both naule an thong </l>
                  <l>But who hais it gammer say on: chould faine here it disclosed. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>That false fixen, that same dame Chat, that counts her selfe so honest. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Who tolde you so: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>That same did Diccon the bedlam, which saw it done. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Diccon: it is a vengeable knaue gammer, tis a bonable horson, </l>
                  <l>Can do mo things then that els cham deceyued euill:. </l>
                  <l>By the masse ich saw him of late cal vp a great blacke deuill, <pb n="31"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>O the knaue cryed ho, ho he roared and he thundred, </l>
                  <l>And yead bene here, cham sure yould murrenly ha wondred. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Was not thou afraide Hodge to see him in this place : </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>No, and chad come to me, chould haue laid him on the face, </l>
                  <l>Chould haue promised him </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>But Hodge, had he no hornes to pushe: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>As long as your two armes, saw ye neuer Fryer </l>
                  <l>Rushe </l>
                  <l>Painted on a cloth, with a side long cowes tayle </l>
                  <l>And crooked clouen feete, and many a hoked nayle? </l>
                  <l>For al the world (if I shuld iudg) chould recken him his brother </l>
                  <l>Loke euen what face Frier Rush had, the deuil had such another </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Now Iesus mercy hodg, did diccon in him bring: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Nay gammer (heare me speke) chil tel you a greater thing, </l>
                  <l>The deuil (when diccon had him, ich hard him wondrous weel) </l>
                  <l>Sayd plainly (here before vs), that dame chat had your neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Then let vs go, and aske her wherfore she minds to kepe it, </l>
                  <l>Seing we know so much, tware a madnes now to slepe it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Go to her gammer, see ye not where she stands in her doores </l>
                  <l>Byd her geue you the neele, tys none of hers but yours. <pb n="32"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S33" type="scene">
               <head>The iii. Acte. The iii. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Gammer. Chat Hodge. </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Dame Chat cholde praye the fair, let me haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is mine </l>
                  <l>Chil not this twenty yeres take one fart that is thyne </l>
                  <l>Therfore giue me mine owne &amp; let me liue besyde the </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Why art thou crept from home hether, to mine own doores to chide me. </l>
                  <l>Hence doting drab, auaunt, or I shall set the further. </l>
                  <l>Intends thou and that knaue, mee in my house to murther: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Tush gape not so on me woman, shalt not yet eate mee, </l>
                  <l>Nor all the frends thou hast, in this shall not intreate mee [mdash ] </l>
                  <l>Mine owne goods I will haue, and aske the no beleue, </l>
                  <l>What woman: pore folks must haue right, thongh the thing you agreue. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Giue thee thy right, and hang thee vp, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thy baggers broode </l>
                  <l>What wilt thou make me a theefe, and say I stole thy good: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Chil say nothing (ich warrant thee), but that ich can proue it well </l>
                  <l>Thou fet my good euen from my doore, cham able this to tel, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Dyd I (olde witche) steale oft was thine: how should that thing be knowen: <pb n="33"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Ich can not tel, but vp thou tokest it as though it had ben thine owne, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Mary fy on thee, thou old gyb, with al my very hart. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Nay fy on thee y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> rampe, thou ryg, with al that take thy parte. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>A vengeaunce on those lips y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laieth such things to my charge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>A vengeance on those callats hips, whose con-science is so large </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Come out Hogge </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Come out hogge, and let me haue right. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Thou arrant Witche. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Thou bawdie bitche, chil make thee cursse this night. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>A bag and a wallet. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>A carte for a callet. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Why wenest thou thus to preuaile, </l>
                  <l>I hold thee a grote, </l>
                  <l>I shall patche thy coate, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Thou warte as good kysse my tayle: </l>
                  <l>Thou slut, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> kut, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> rakes, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> iakes. will not shame make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hide the </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Thou skald, thou bald, thou rotten, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> glotton, </l>
                  <l>I will no longer chyd the </l>
                  <l>But I will teache the to kepe home. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Wylt thou drunken beaste. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Sticke to her gammer, take her by the head, chil warrant you thys feast. </l>
                  <l>Smyte I saye gammer, </l>
                  <l>Byte I say gammer, </l>
                  <l>I trow ye wyll be keene:. </l>
                  <l>Where be your nayls ? claw her by the iawes, pull me out bothe her eyen, </l>
                  <l>Gogs bones gammer, holde vp your head, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>I trow drab I shall dresse thee. <pb n="34"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tary y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knaue I hold the a grote, I shall make these hands blesse thee </l>
                  <l>Take y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> this old hore for amends, &amp; lerne thy tonge well to tame </l>
                  <l>And say thou met at this bickering, not thy fellow but thy dame. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Where is the strong stued hore, chil geare a hores marke, </l>
                  <l>Stand out ones way, that ich kyll none in the darke </l>
                  <l>Up gammer and ye be alyue, chil feyght now for us bothe, </l>
                  <l>Come no nere me thou scalde callet, to kyll the ich wer loth. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Art here agayne thou hoddy peke, what doll bryng me out my spitte. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chill broche thee wyth this, bim father soule, chyll coniure that foule sprete: </l>
                  <l>Let dore stand Cock, why coms in deede? kepe dore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> horson boy. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Stand to it y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dastard for thine eares, ise teche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a sluttish toye. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs woundes hore, chil make the auaunte, take heede Cocke, pull in the latche, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>I faith sir loose breche had ye taried, ye shold haue found your match. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Now ware thy throte losell, thouse pay for al </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Well said gammer by my soule, </l>
                  <l>Hoyse her, souse her, bounce her, trounce her, pull out her throte boule </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Comst behynd me thou withered witch, &amp; I get once on foote </l>
                  <l>Thouse pay for all, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> old tarlether, ile teach the what longs to it </l>
                  <l>Take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this to make vp thy mouth, til time thou come by more <pb n="35"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Up gammer stand on your feete, where is the olde hore? </l>
                  <l>Haith woulde chad her by the face choulde racke her callet crowne </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>A hodg, hodg, where was thy help, when fixen had me downe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse Gammer, but for my staffe Chat had gone nye to spyl you </l>
                  <l>Ich think the harlot had not cared, and chad not com to kill you but shall we loose our neele thus ? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>No Hodge chwarde lothe doo soo. </l>
                  <l>Thinkest thou chill take that at her hand, no hodg ich tell the no </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chold yet this fray wer wel take vp, &amp; our own neele at home </l>
                  <l>Twill be my chaunce els some to kil, wher euer it be or whome </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>We haue a parson, (hodge thou knoes) a man estemed wise </l>
                  <l>Mast doctor Rat, chil for hym send, and let me here his aduise, </l>
                  <l>He will her shriue for all this gere, &amp; geue her penaunce strait </l>
                  <l>Wese haue our neele, els dame chat comes nere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in heauen gate </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Ye mary gammer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ich thmk best: wyll you now for him send </l>
                  <l>The sooner Doctor Rat be here, the soner wese ha an ende, </l>
                  <l>And here gaminer Dyccons deuill, (as iche re-member well) </l>
                  <l>Of Cat, and Chat, and Doctor Rat a felloneu tale dyd tell, </l>
                  <l>Chold you forty pound, that is the way your neele to get againe. <pb n="36"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Chil ha him strait call out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boy wese make him take the payn </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>What coke I saye, coine out what deuill canst not here. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>How now hodg ? how does gammer, is yet the wether cleare? </l>
                  <l>What wold chaue me to doo? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Come hether Cocke anon [mdash ] </l>
                  <l>Hence swythe to Doctor Rat, hye the that thou were gone, </l>
                  <l>And pray hym come speke with me, cham not well at ease, </l>
                  <l>Shalt haue him at his chamber, or els at mother Bees, </l>
                  <l>Els seeke him at Hob fylchers shop, for as charde it reported </l>
                  <l>There is the best ale in al the towne, and now is most resorted. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>And shal ich brynge hyin with me gainmer? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Yea, by and by good Cocke. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>Shalt see that shalbe here anone, els let me haue one the docke </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Now gammer shal we two go in, and tary for hys commynge </l>
                  <l>What deuill woman plucke vp your hart, &amp; leue of al this glomming </l>
                  <l>So </l>
                  <l>Though she were stronger at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> first, as ich thinke ye did find her </l>
                  <l>Yet there ye drest the dronken sow, what time ye cam behind her </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nay, cham sure she lost not all, for set thend to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning </l>
                  <l>And ich doubt not, but she will make small bost of her winning. <pb n="37"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S34" type="scene">
               <head>The iii:. Acte. The iiii. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Tyb. Hodge Gammer. Cocke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Se gammer, gammer, gib our cat, cham afraid what she ayleth </l>
                  <l>She standes me gasping behind the doore, as though her winde her faileth: </l>
                  <l>Now let ich doubt what gib shuld mean, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now she doth so dote </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Hold hether, ichould twenty pound, your neele is in her throte </l>
                  <l>Grope her ich say, me thmkes ich feele it, does not pricke your hand? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Ich can feele nothing </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>No, ich know thars not within this land </l>
                  <l>A muryner Cat then Gyb is, betwixt the tems and Tyne, </l>
                  <l>Shase as much wyt in her head almost as chaue in mine. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
                  <l>Faith shase eaten some thing, that wil not easely downe </l>
                  <l>Whether she gat it at home, or abrode in the towne </l>
                  <l>Iche can not tell </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Alas ich feare it be some croked pyn, </l>
                  <l>And then farewell gyb, she is vndone, and lost al saue the skyn. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Tys your neele woman, I say gogs soule geue me a knyfe </l>
                  <l>And chil haue it out of her mawe, or els chal lose my lyfe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>What nay hodg, fy kil not our cat, tis al the cats we ha now. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse dame Chat hays me so moued. iche care not what I kyll, ma god a vowe. <pb n="38"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Go to then Tyb to this geare, holde vp her tayle and take her, </l>
                  <l>Chil see what deuil is in her guts chil take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pain es to rake her </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Rake a Cat Hodge, what woldst thou do ? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>What thinckst that cham not able? </l>
                  <l>Did not Tom Tankard rake his Curtal toore day standing in the stable. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Soft be content, lets here what newes Cocke bringeth from maist Rat </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>Gammer chaue ben ther as you bad, you wot wel about what </l>
                  <l>Twill not be long before he come, ich durst sweare of a booke </l>
                  <l>He byds you see ye be at home, and there for him to looke. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Where didst thou find him boy was he not wher </l>
                  <l>I told thee? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cocke</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes euen at hob filchers house, by him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bought and solde me </l>
                  <l>A cup of ale had in his hand, and a crab lay in the fyer, </l>
                  <l>Chad much a do to go and coine, al was so ful of myer. </l>
                  <l>And Gammer one thing I can tel, Hob filchers naule was loste </l>
                  <l>And Doctor Rat found it againe, hard beside the doore poste, </l>
                  <l>I chould a penny can say something, your neele againe to fet </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Cham glad to heare so much Cocke, then trust he wil not let, </l>
                  <l>To helpe vs herein best he can therfore tyl time he come </l>
                  <l>Let vs go in, if there be ought to get thou shalt haue some. <pb n="39"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="A4" type="act">
            <head>The.iiii. Acte.</head>
            <div n="S41" type="scene">
               <head>The iiii. Acte. The i. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Doctor Rat. Gammer Gurton.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>A Man were better twenty times be a bandog &amp; barke, </l>
                  <l>Then here among such a sort, be parish priest </l>
                  <l>Where he shal neuer be at rest, one pissing while a day </l>
                  <l>But he must trudge about the towne, this way, and that way, </l>
                  <l>Here to a drab, there to a theefe, his shoes to teare and rent </l>
                  <l>And that which is worst of al, at euery knaues commauindement </l>
                  <l>I had not sit the space, to drmke two pots of ale </l>
                  <l>But Gammer gurtons sory boy, was straite way at my taile, </l>
                  <l>And she was sicke, and I must come, to do I wot not what, </l>
                  <l>If once her fingers end but ake, trudge, call for Doctor Rat </l>
                  <l>And when I come not at their call, I only therby loose, </l>
                  <l>For I am sure to lacke therfore, a tythe pyg or a goose </l>
                  <l>I warrant you when truth is knowen, &amp; told they haue their tale </l>
                  <l>The inatter where about I come, is not worth a half peny worth of ale, </l>
                  <l>Yet must I talke so sage and smothe, as though I were a glosier </l>
                  <l>Els or the yere come at an end, I shalbe sure the loser. <pb n="40"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>What worke ye gammer gurton? hoow here is your frend M. Rat. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>A Sood M. Doctor cha trobled, cha trobled you, chwot wel that </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>How do ye woman: be ye lustie, or be ye not wel at ease: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>By gys inaster cham not sick, but yet chaue a disease. </l>
                  <l>Chad a foule turne now of late, chill tell it you by gigs. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Hath your browne cow cast hir calfe, or your sandy sowe her pigs </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>No, but chad ben as good they had, as this ich wot weel. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>What is the matter ? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Alas alas, cha lost my good neele, </l>
                  <l>My neele I say, and wot ye what: a drab came by and spied it </l>
                  <l>And when I asked hir for the same, the filth flatly denied it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>What was she that: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>A dame ich warrant you: she began to scold and brawle </l>
                  <l>Alas, alas, come hether Hodge: this wretche can tell you all. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S42" type="scene">
               <head>The iiii. Acte. The ii. Sceane.</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Hodge. Doctor Rat. Gammer. Diccon. Chat.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>God morow gaffer Vicar </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat 2 Come on fellow let vs heare.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy dame hath sayd to me, thou knowest of all this geare, </l>
                  <l>Lets see what thou canst saie. <pb n="41"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Bym fay sir that ye shall, </l>
                  <l>What matter so euer here was done, ich can tell your maship all </l>
                  <l>My Gammer gurton heare see now, sat her downe at this doore, see now: </l>
                  <l>And as she began to stirre her, see now, her neele fell in the floore, see now. </l>
                  <l>And while her staffe she tooke, see now, at Gyb her Cat to flynge, see now, </l>
                  <l>Her neele was lost in the floore, see now is not this a wondrous thing, see now? </l>
                  <l>Then came the queane Dame Chat, see now to aske for hir blacke cup, see now:. </l>
                  <l>And euen here at this gate, see now: she tooke that neele vp, see now. </l>
                  <l>My Gammer then she yeede, see now hir neele againe to bring, see now </l>
                  <l>And was caught by the head see now is not this a wondrous thing, see now </l>
                  <l>She tare my Gammers cote see now and scratched hir by the face, see now </l>
                  <l>Chad thought shad stopt hir throte, see now is not this a wondrous case, see now ? </l>
                  <l>When ich saw this, ich was wrothe see now and start betwene them twaine, see now </l>
                  <l>Els ich durst take a booke othe, see now my Gammer had bene slaine, see now. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>This is euen the whole matter, as Hodge has plainly tolde </l>
                  <l>And chould faine be quiet for my part, that chould </l>
                  <l>But helpe vs good master, beseech ye that ye doo </l>
                  <l>Els shal we both be beaten and lose our neele too </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>What wold ye haue me to doo? tel me that I were gone </l>
                  <l>I will do the best that I can, to set you both at one <pb n="42"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>But be ye sure dame Chat hath this your neele founde [mdash ] </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes the man that see hir take it vp of the ground, </l>
                  <l>Aske him your selfe master Rat if ye beleue not me </l>
                  <l>And helpe me to my neele, for gods sake and samt charitie. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Come nere diccon and let vs heare, what thou can expresse. </l>
                  <l>Wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be swome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> seest dame chat. this womans neele haue? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Nay by S. Benit wil I not, then might ye thmke me raue. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Why didst not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> tel me so euen here canst y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> for shame deny it </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I mary gammer. but I said I wold not abide by it, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Will you say a thmg, and not sticke to it to trieit? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Stick to it quoth you master rat, mary sir I defyit, </l>
                  <l>Nay there is many an honest main, when he suche blastes hath blowne </l>
                  <l>In his freindes eares, he woulde be loth the same by him were knowne </l>
                  <l>If such a toy be vsed oft among the honestie </l>
                  <l>It may beseme a simple man, of your and my degree </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Then we be neuer the nearer, for all that you can tell, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Yes mary sir, if ye will do by mine aduise and counsaile, </l>
                  <l>If mother chat se al vs here, she knoweth how the matter goes </l>
                  <l>Therefore I red you three go hence, and within keepe close, <pb n="43"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>And I will into dame chats house, and so the matter vse, </l>
                  <l>That or you cold go twise to church, I warant you here news, </l>
                  <l>She shal looke wel about hir, but I durst lay a pledge, </l>
                  <l>Ye shal of gammers neele, haue shortly better knowledge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Now gentle Diccon do so, and good sir let vs trudge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse I may not tarry so long to be your iudge. <pb n="44"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Tys but a litle while man, what take so much paine, </l>
                  <l>If I here no newes of it I will come sooner againe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Tary so much, good master Doctor of your gentlenes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Then let vs hie vs inward, and Diccon speede thy busines. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dicon</speaker>
                  <l>Now sirs do you no more, but kepe my counsaile iuste, </l>
                  <l>And Doctor Rat shall thus catch, some good I trust, </l>
                  <l>But mother Chat my gossop, talke first with all I must: </l>
                  <l>For she must be chiefe captaine to lay the Rat in the dust. </l>
                  <l>God deuen dame Chat in faith, and wel met in this place. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>God deuen my friend Diccon, whether walke ye this pace? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>By my truth euen to you, to learne how the world goeth, </l>
                  <l>Hard ye no more of the other matter, say me now by your troth <pb n="45"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>O yes diccon, here the olde hoore, &amp; hodge that great knaue </l>
                  <l>But in faith I would thou hadst sene, o lord I drest them braue </l>
                  <l>She bare me two or three souses behind in the nape of the necke </l>
                  <l>Till I made hir olde wesen, to answere againe kecke </l>
                  <l>And Hodge that dirty dastard, that at hir elbow standes, </l>
                  <l>If one paire of legs had not bene worth two paire of hands </l>
                  <l>He had had his bearde shauen, if my nayles wold haue serued </l>
                  <l>And not without a cause, for the knaue it well deserued. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>By the masse I can the thank wench, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> didst so wel acquite the </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>And thadst seene him Diccon, it wold haue made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beshite the </l>
                  <l>For laughter. The horsen dolt at last caught vp a club, </l>
                  <l>As though he would haue slaine the master deuil Belsabub, </l>
                  <l>But I set him soone inwarde. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>iccon</speaker>
                  <l>O Lorde there is the thing </l>
                  <l>That Hodge is so offended, that makes him starte and flyng </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Why? makes the knaue any moyling, as ye haue sene or hard </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>iccon</speaker>
                  <l>Euen now I sawe him last, like a mad man he farde, </l>
                  <l>And sware by heauen and hell, he would a wreake his sorowe </l>
                  <l>And leue you neuer a hen on hue, by viii. of the clock to morow, <pb n="46"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therfore marke what I say, and my wordes see that ye trust </l>
                  <l>Your hens be as good as dead, if ye leaue them on the ruste. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>The knaue dare as wel go hang himself, as go vpon my ground </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Wel yet take hede I say, I must tel you my tale round, </l>
                  <l>Haue you not about your house, behind your fumace or leade. </l>
                  <l>A hole where a crafty knaue, may crepe in for neade? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Yes by the masse, a hole broke down, euen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in these ii. dayes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Hodge, he intendes this same night, to slip in there awayes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>O christ that I were sure of it, in faith he shuld haue his mede. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Watch wel, for the knaue wil be there as sure as is your crede </l>
                  <l>I wold spend my selfe a shilling: to haue him well. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>I am as glad as a woman can be, of this thing to here tell </l>
                  <l>By gogs bones when he commeth, now that I know the matter </l>
                  <l>He shal sure at the first skip, to leape in scalding water: </l>
                  <l>With a worse turne besides, when he will, let him come. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I tell you as my sister, you know what meaneth mum, </l>
                  <l>Now lacke I but my doctor, to play his part againe. </l>
                  <l>And lo where he commeth towards, Peraduenture to his paine. <pb n="47"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>What good newes Diccon? fellow, is mother chat at home, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>She is syr, and she is not, but it please her to whome: </l>
                  <l>Yet did I take her tardy, as subtle as she was. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>The thing that thou wentst for, hast thou brought it to passe? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I haue done that I haue done, be it worse, be it better. </l>
                  <l>And dame Chat at her wyts ende, I haue almost set her. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Why hast thou spied the neele quickly I pray thee tell </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I haue spyed it in faith sir, I handled my selfe so well, </l>
                  <l>And yet the crafty queane, had almost take my trumpe. </l>
                  <l>But or all came to an ende, I set her in a dumpe: </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>How so I pray thee Diccon? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Mary syr will ye heare? </l>
                  <l>She was clapt downe on the backside, by cocks mother dere </l>
                  <l>And there she sat sewing a halter, or a bande, </l>
                  <l>With no other thing saue gammers nedle in her hande, </l>
                  <l>As soone as any knocke, if the filth be in doubte, </l>
                  <l>She needes but once puffe, and her candle is out:. </l>
                  <l>Now I sir knowing of euery doore the pin, </l>
                  <l>Came nycely, and said no worde, till time I was within, </l>
                  <l>And there I sawe the neele, euen with these two eyes, </l>
                  <l>Who euer say the contrary, I will sweare he lyes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>O Diccon that I was not there, then in thy steade. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Well, if ye will be ordred, and do by my reade, <pb n="48"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will bring you to a place, as the house standes. </l>
                  <l>Where ye shall take the drab, with the neele in her handes </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>For Gods sake do so Diccon, and I will gage my gowne </l>
                  <l>To geue thee a full pot, of the best ale in the towne, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Follow me but a litle, and marke what I will say. </l>
                  <l>Lay downe your gown beside you, go to, come on your way. </l>
                  <l>Se ye not what is here? a hole wherin ye inay creepe </l>
                  <l>Into the house, and sodenly vnwares among them leape, </l>
                  <l>There shal ye finde the Bitchfox, and the neele together </l>
                  <l>Do as I bid you man, come on your wayes hether. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou sure diccon, the swil tub standes not here aboute. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>I was within my selfe man euen now, ther is no doubt, </l>
                  <l>Go softly, mike no noyse giue me your foote sir John, </l>
                  <l>Here will I waite wpon you tyl you come out anone. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Helpe Diccon, out alas, I shal be slaine among them </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>If they giue you not the nedle, tel them that ye will hang them </l>
                  <l>Ware that, hoow my wenches, haue ye caught the Fuxe, </l>
                  <l>That vsed to make reuel, among your hennes and </l>
                  <l>Cocks:. </l>
                  <l>Saue his life yet for his order. though he susteine some paine </l>
                  <l>Gogs bread, I am afraide, they wil beate out his braine <pb n="49"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Wo worth the houre that I came heare. </l>
                  <l>And wo worth him that wrought this geare, </l>
                  <l>A sort of drabs and queanes haue me blest, </l>
                  <l>Was euer creature halfe so euill drest? </l>
                  <l>Who euer it wrought, and first did inuent it, </l>
                  <l>He shall I warrant him, erre long repent it, </l>
                  <l>I will spend all I haue without my skinne </l>
                  <l>But he shall be brought to the plight I am in, </l>
                  <l>Master Bayly I trow and he be worth his eares, </l>
                  <l>Will snaffle these murderers and all that them beares, </l>
                  <l>I will surely neither byte nor suppe </l>
                  <l>Till I fetch him hether this matter to take vp </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="A5" type="act">
            <head>The.v. Acte.</head>
            <div n="S51" type="scene">
               <head>The v. Acte. The i. Sceane,</head>
               <stage type="entrance">Master Bayly. Doctor Rat.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bailie</speaker>
                  <l>I Can perceiue none other, I speke it from my hart </l>
                  <l>But either ye ar in al the fault or els in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greatest part </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>If it be counted his fault, besides all his greeues </l>
                  <l>When a poore man is spoyled: and beaten among theeues? </l>
                  <l>Then I confesse my fault herein, at this season, </l>
                  <l>But I hope you wil not iudge so much against reason. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>And me thinkes by your owne tale, of all that ye name, </l>
                  <l>If any plaid the theefe you were the very same. </l>
                  <l>The women they did nothing, as your words make probation </l>
                  <l>But stoutly withstood your forcible inuasion, <pb n="50"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>If that a theefe at your window, to enter should begin, </l>
                  <l>Wold you hold forth your hand, and helpe to pull him in:. </l>
                  <l>Or you wold kepe him out: I pray you answere me. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Mary kepe him out, and a good cause why:. </l>
                  <l>But I am no theefe sir but an honest learned </l>
                  <l>Clarke, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Yea, but who knoweth that, when he meets you in the darke </l>
                  <l>I am sure your learning shines not out at your nose, </l>
                  <l>Was it any maruaile, though the poore woman arose </l>
                  <l>And start vp, being afraide of that was in hir purse </l>
                  <l>Me thinke you may be glad that your lucke was no worse. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this euill ynough, I pray you as you thinke, </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">Showing his broken head.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Yea but a man in the darke, if chaunces do wincke, </l>
                  <l>As soone he smites his father, as any other man, </l>
                  <l>Because for lacke of hght, disceme him he ne can, </l>
                  <l>Might it not haue ben your lucke, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a spit to haue ben slaine. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>I thinke I am litle better, my scalpe is clouen to the braine, </l>
                  <l>If there be all the remedy, I know who beares the knockes </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>By my troth and well worthy, besides to kisse the stockes </l>
                  <l>To come in on the backe side, when ye might go about, <pb n="51"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>I know non such, vnles they long to haue their braines knockt out </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Well, wil you be so good sir, as talke with danie Chat ? </l>
                  <l>And know what she intended. I aske no more but that. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Let her be called fellow because of master doctor, </l>
                  <l>I warrant in this case, she wil be hir owne Froctor, </l>
                  <l>She will tel hir owne tale in metter or in prose, </l>
                  <l>And byd you seeke your remedy, and so go wype your nose. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="S52" type="scene">
               <head>The v. Acte. The ii Sceane,</head>
               <stage type="entrance">M. Bayly. Chat. D Rat. Gammer. Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>DAme Chat, master doctor vpon you hcre complained </l>
                  <l>That you &amp; your maides shuld him much mis-order. </l>
                  <l>And taketh many an oth, that no word he fained, </l>
                  <l>Laying to your charge, how you thought him to murder: </l>
                  <l>And on his part againe, that same inan saith furder </l>
                  <l>He neuer offended you in word nor intent, </l>
                  <l>To heare you answer hereto, we haue now for you sent. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>That I wold haue murdered him, fye on him wretch, </l>
                  <l>And euil mought he thee for it, our Lord I besech, </l>
                  <l>I will swere on al the bookes that opens and shuttes </l>
                  <l>He faineth this tale out of his owne guttes, <pb n="52"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>For this seuen weeks with me, I am sure he sat not downe, </l>
                  <l>Nay ye haue other minions, in the other end of the towne, </l>
                  <l>Where ye were liker to catch such a blow, </l>
                  <l>Then any where els, as farre as I know. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Belike then master Doctor, yon stripe there ye got not? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Thinke you I am so mad, that where I was bet, </l>
                  <l>I wot not? </l>
                  <l>Will ye beleue this queane, before she hath tryd it? </l>
                  <l>It is not the first dede she hath done and after-ward denide it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>What man, will you say I broke your head? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>How canst thou proue the contrary? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, how prouest thou that I did the deade </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>To plainly, by S. Hary. </l>
                  <l>This profe I trow may serue, though I no word spoke. </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">Showing his broken head.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Bicause thy head is broken, was it I that it broke? </l>
                  <l>I saw thee Rat I tel thee, not once within this fortnight, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>No mary, thou sawest me not, for why thou hadst no light, </l>
                  <l>But I felt thee for al the darke, beshrew thy smothe cheekes, </l>
                  <l>And thou groped me, this wil declare, any day this six weekes </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="act">Showing his heade.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Answere me to this M. Rat, when caught you this harme of yours? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>A while a go sir, god he knoweth, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in les then these ii. houres. <pb n="53"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Dame Chat was there none with you: (confesse I faith) about that season. </l>
                  <l>What wonian, let it be what it wil, tis neither felony nor treason </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Yes by my faith master Bayly, there was a knaue not farre </l>
                  <l>Who caught one good Philup on the brow, with a dore barre </l>
                  <l>And well was he worthy, as it semed to mee, </l>
                  <l>But what is that to this inan, since this was not hee </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Who was it then? lets here. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Alas sir, aske you that? </l>
                  <l>Is it not made plain inough (by the owne mouth of daine chat) </l>
                  <l>The time agreeth, my head is broken, her tong can not lye, </l>
                  <l>Onely vpon a bare, nay she saith it was not I. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>No mary was it not indeede ye shal here by this one thing, </l>
                  <l>This after noone a frend of mine, for good wil gaue me warning </l>
                  <l>And bad me wel loke to my ruste, and al niy Capons pennes, </l>
                  <l>For if I toke not better heede, a knaue wold haue my hennes, </l>
                  <l>Then I to saue my goods, toke so much pains as him to watch </l>
                  <l>And as good fortune serued me, it was my chaunce him for to catch </l>
                  <l>What strokes he bare away, or other what was his gaines </l>
                  <l>I wot not, but sure I am, he had something for his paines </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Yet telles thou not who it was. <pb n="54"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Who it was a false theefe, </l>
                  <l>That came like a false Foke, my pullaine to kil and mischeefe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>But knowest thou not his name? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>I know it but what than, </l>
                  <l>It was that crafty cullyon Hodge my gammer gurtons man. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bailie</speaker>
                  <l>Cal me the knaue hether, he shal sure kysse the stockes. </l>
                  <l>I shall teach him a lesson, for filching hens or cocks </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>I maruaile master bayly, so bleared be your eyes. </l>
                  <l>An egge is not so ful of meate, as she is ful of lyes:. </l>
                  <l>When she hath playd this pranke, to excuse al this geare, </l>
                  <l>She layeth the fault in such a one, as I know was not there. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Was he not thear loke on his pate, that shalbe his witnes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>I wold my head were half so hole, I wold seeke no redresse. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>God bless you gammer Gurton. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>God dylde you master mine. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in thy house, hodge, a ser-uant of thine. </l>
                  <l>They tel me that busy knaue, is such a filching one, </l>
                  <l>That Hen, Fig, goose or capon, thy neighbour can haue none, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>By god cham much ameued, to heare any such reporte: </l>
                  <l>Hodge was not wont ich trow, to baue him in that sort. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>A theeuisher knaue is not on liue, more filching. nor more false <pb n="55"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Many a truer man then he, hase hanged vp by the halse </l>
                  <l>And thou his dame of al his theft, thou art the sole receauer </l>
                  <l>For hodge to catch, and thou to kepe, I neuer knew none better </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Sir reuerence of your masterdome, and you were out adoore, </l>
                  <l>Chold be so bolde for al hir brags, to cal hir arrant whoore, </l>
                  <l>And ich knew Hodge so bad as tow, ich wish me endlesse sorow </l>
                  <l>And chould not take the pains, to hang him vp before to morow? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>What haue I stolne from the or thine: thou ilfauored olde trot. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>A great deale more (by Gods blest,) then cheuer by the got, </l>
                  <l>That thou knowest wel I neade not say it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Stoppe there I say, </l>
                  <l>And tel me here I pray you, this matter by the way:. </l>
                  <l>How chaunce hodge is not here him wold I faine haue had. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Alas sir, heel be here anon, ha be hapdled to bad. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Master bayly, sir ye be not such a foole wel I know, </l>
                  <l>But ye perceiue by this lingring, there is a pad in the straw. </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">Thinking that Hodg, his head was broke, and that gammer
Wold not let him come before them</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Chil shew you his face, ich warrant the, now where he is. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bailie</speaker>
                  <l>Come on fellow it is tolde me thou art a shrew iwysse. <pb n="56"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy neighbours hens y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> takest, and playes the two legged foxe </l>
                  <l>Their chikens &amp; their capons to, &amp; now and then their Cocks. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Ich defy them al that dare it say, cham as true as the best </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Wart not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> taken within this houre, in dame chats hens nest? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Taken there? no master chold not dot, for a house ful of gold. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Thou or the deuil in thy cote, sweare this I dare be bold </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Sweare me no swearing quean, the deuill he geue the sorow, </l>
                  <l>Is not worth a gnat, thou canst sweare till to morow, </l>
                  <l>Where is the harme he hath? shew it by gods bread, </l>
                  <l>Ye beat him with a witnes, but the stripes light on my head. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Bet me? gogs blessed body, chold first ich trow haue burst the </l>
                  <l>Ich thinke and chad my hands loose callet chould haue crust the. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Thou shitten knaue I trow y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knowest y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful weight of my fist </l>
                  <l>I am fowly deceiued, onles thy head &amp; my doore bar kyste. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Hold thy chat whore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> criest so loude, can no man els be hard </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Well knaue, &amp; I had the alone, I wold surely rap thy costard. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Sir answer me to this, is thy head whole or broken? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Yea master Bayly, blest be euery good token. <pb n="57"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Is my head whole? ich warrant you, tis neither scuruy nor scald </l>
                  <l>What you foule beast, does think tis cither pild or bald. </l>
                  <l>Nay ich thanke god: chil not for al that thou maist spend </l>
                  <l>That chad one scab on my narse, as brode as thy fingers end </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Come nearer heare. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Yes That ich dare </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>By our Lady here is no harme, </l>
                  <l>Hodges head is hole ynough, for al dame Chats charme. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>By gogs blest, how euer the thing he clockes or smolders, </l>
                  <l>I know the blowes he bare away, either w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> head or shoulders, </l>
                  <l>Camest y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not knaue within this houre, crepmg mto my pens </l>
                  <l>And there was caught within my hous, gropig among my hens. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>A plage both on thy hens &amp; the, a carte whore, a carte, </l>
                  <l>Chould I were hanged as hie as a tree, &amp; chware as false as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art </l>
                  <l>Geue my gammer again her washical, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> stole away in thy lap. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Yea maister baily there is a thmg, you know not on may hap </l>
                  <l>This drab she kepes away my good, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil he might her snare </l>
                  <l>Ich pray you that ich might haue, a right action on her. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Haue I thy good old filth, or any such old sowes? </l>
                  <l>I am as true, I wold thou knew, as skin betwene thy browes <pb n="58"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Many a truer hath ben hanged, though you escape the daunger </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Thou shalt answer by gods pity, for this thy foule slaunder </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what can ye charge hir withal? to say so, ye do not well. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Mary a vengeance to hir hart, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whore hase stoln my neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Thy nedle old witch, how so? it were almes thy scul to knock </l>
                  <l>So didst thou say, the other day, that I had stolne thy Cock </l>
                  <l>And rosted him to my breakfast, which shal not be forgotten, </l>
                  <l>The deuil pul out thy lying tong, and teeth that be so rotten </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Geue me my neele, as for my cocke, chould be very loth </l>
                  <l>That chuld here tel he shuld hang, on thy fals faith and troth. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Your talke is such, I can scarse learne who shuld be most in fault bred &amp; salt </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Kepe ye content a while, se that your tonges ye holde, </l>
                  <l>Me thinkes you shuld remembre, this is no place to scolde, </l>
                  <l>Nedle had? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>To name you sir the party, chould not be very glad. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Yea but we must nedes heare it, &amp; therfore say it boldly. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Such one as told the tale, full soberly and coldly, <pb n="59"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>What time this drunken gossip, my faire long neele vp tooke </l>
                  <l>Diccon (master) the Bedlam, cham very sure ye know him. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bailie</speaker>
                  <l>A false knaue by Gods pitie, ye were but a foole to trow him, </l>
                  <l>I durst auenture wel the price of my best cap, </l>
                  <l>That when the end is knowen, all wil turue to a iape, </l>
                  <l>Tolde he not you that besides she stole your </l>
                  <l>Cocke that tyde? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>No master no indede, for then he shuld haue lyed, </l>
                  <l>My cocke is I thanke Christ, safe and wel a fine </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Yea but that ragged colt, that whore that tyb of thine </l>
                  <l>Said plainly thy cocke was stolne, &amp; in my house was eaten, </l>
                  <l>That lying cut is lost, that she is not swinged and beaten, </l>
                  <l>And yet for al my good name, it were a small amendes </l>
                  <l>I picke not this geare (hearst thou) out of my fingers endes </l>
                  <l>But he that hard it told me, who thou of late didst naine </l>
                  <l>Diccon whom al men knowes, it was the very same. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>This is the case, you lost your nedle about the dores </l>
                  <l>And she answeres againe, she hase no cocke of yours, </l>
                  <l>Thus in your talke and Action, from that you do intend, </l>
                  <l>She is whole fiue inile wide, froin that she doth defend. </l>
                  <l>Will you saie she hath your Cocke? <pb n="60"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>No mery sir that chil not, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Will you confesse hir neele? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Will I? no sir I will not </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Then there lieth all the matter. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Soft master by the way, </l>
                  <l>Ye know she could do litle, and she cold not say nay. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Yea but he that made one he about your Cock stealing, </l>
                  <l>Wil not sticke to make another, what time lies be in dealing </l>
                  <l>Tweene, the ende wil proue, this brawle did first arise, </l>
                  <l>Upon no other ground, but only Diccons lyes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Though some be lyes as you belike haue espyed them, </l>
                  <l>Yet other some be true, by proof I haue wel tryed them. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>What other thing beside this dame Chat. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Mary syr euen this, </l>
                  <l>The tale I tolde before, the selfe same tale it was his, </l>
                  <l>He gaue me like a frende, warning against my losse, </l>
                  <l>Els had my hens be stolne, eche one, by Gods crosse: </l>
                  <l>He tolde me Hodge wold come, and in he came </l>
                  <l>But as the matter chaunsed, with greater hast then speede, </l>
                  <l>This truth was said, and true was found, as truly </l>
                  <l>I report. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>If Doctor Rat be not deceiued, it was of another sort. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>By Gods mother thou and he, be a cople of suttle foxes, <pb n="61"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Betweene you and Hodge, I beare away the boxes, </l>
                  <l>Did not diccon apoynt the place, wher y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> shuldst stand to mete him </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Yes by the masse, &amp; if he came, bad me not sticke to speet hym. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Gods sacrament the villain knaue hath drest vs round about, </l>
                  <l>He is the cause of all this brawle, that dyrty shitten loute:. </l>
                  <l>When gammer gurton here coinplained, &amp; made a ruful mone </l>
                  <l>I heard him sweare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you had gotten, hir nedle that was gone, </l>
                  <l>And this to try he furder said, he was ful loth how be it </l>
                  <l>He was content with small adoe, to bring me where to see it. </l>
                  <l>And where ye sat, he said ful certain, if I wold folow his read </l>
                  <l>Into your house a priuy way, he wold me guide and leade, </l>
                  <l>And where ye had it in your hands, sewing about a clowte, </l>
                  <l>And set me in the backe hole, therby to finde you out </l>
                  <l>And whiles I sought a quietnes, creping vpon my knees, </l>
                  <l>I found the weight of your dore bar, for my reward and fees, </l>
                  <l>Such is the lucke that some men gets, while they begin to mel </l>
                  <l>In setting at one such as were out, minding to make al wel. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Was not wel blest gammer, to scape y scoure. &amp; chad ben there <pb n="62"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then chad ben drest be like, as ill by the masse, as gaffar vicar </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Mary sir, here is a sport alone, I loked for such an end </l>
                  <l>If diccon had not playd the knaue, this had ben sone amend </l>
                  <l>My gammer here he made a foole, and drest hir as she was </l>
                  <l>And goodwife Chat he set to scole, till both partes cried alas, </l>
                  <l>And D. Rat was not behind, whiles Chat his crown did pare, </l>
                  <l>I wold the knaue had ben starke blind, if hodg had not his share. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Cham meetly wel sped alredy amongs, cham drest like a coult </l>
                  <l>And chad not had the better wit, chad bene made a doult </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Sir knaue make hast diccon were here, fetch him where euer he bee </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Fie on the villaine, fie, fie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> makes vs thus agree, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Fie on him knaue, with al my hart, now fie, and fie againe. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Now fie on him may I best say, whom he hath almost slaine. </l>
                  <l>Lo where he commeth at hand, belike hewas not fare </l>
                  <l>Diccon heare be two or three, thy company can not spare. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>God blesse you, and you may be blest so many al at once </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Come knaue, it were a good deed to geld the by cockes bones </l>
                  <l>Seest not thy handiwarke? sir Rat can ye for-bearn him? <pb n="63"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>A vengeance on those hands lite, for my hands cam not nere hym </l>
                  <l>The horsen priest hath lift the pot, in some of these ale wyves chayres </l>
                  <l>That his head wolde not serue him, belyke to come downe the stayres. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Baily</speaker>
                  <l>Nay soft, thou maist not play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knaue, &amp; haue this language to </l>
                  <l>If thou thy tong bridle a while, the better maist </l>
                  <l>Confesse the truth as I shall aske, and cease a while to fable. </l>
                  <l>And for thy fault I promise the, thy handlmg shalbe reasonable </l>
                  <l>Hast thou not made a lie or two, to set these two by the eares? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>What if I haue? fiue hundred such haue I seene within these seuen yeares: </l>
                  <l>I am sory for nothing else but that I see not the sport </l>
                  <l>Which was betwene them when they met, as they then selues report </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>The greatest thing master rat, ye se how he is drest. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>What deuil nede he be groping so depe, in good-wife Chats hes nest </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Yea but it was thy drift to bring him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> briars. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Gods bread, hath not such an old foole, wit to saue his eares? </l>
                  <l>He showeth himselfe herein ye see, so very a coke, </l>
                  <l>The Cat was not so madly alured by the Foxe, </l>
                  <l>To run into the snares, was set for him doubtlesse, </l>
                  <l>For he leapt in for myce, and this sir Iohn for madnes. <pb n="64"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Well and ye shift no better, ye losel, lyther, and lasye, </l>
                  <l>I will go neare for this, to make ye leape at a Dasye </l>
                  <l>In the kings name master Bayly, I charge you set him fast. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>What fast at cardes, or fast on slepe? it is the thing I did last. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Nay fast in fetters false varlet, according to thy deedes. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Master doctor ther is no remedy, I must intreat you needes </l>
                  <l>Some other kinde of punishment </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Nay by all Halowes, </l>
                  <l>His punishment if I may iudg, shalbe naught els but the gallous </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>That were to sore, a spiritual man to be so extreame. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>Is he worthy any better, sir how do ye iudge and deame? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>I graunt him worthie punishment, but in no wise so great </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>It is a shame ich tel you plaine, for such false knaues intreat </l>
                  <l>He has almost vndone vs al, that is as true as steele: </l>
                  <l>And yet for al this great ado'cham neuer the nere iny neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Canst y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not say any thing to that diccon, with least or most? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Yea mary sir, thus much I can say wel, the nedle is lost, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Nay canst not thou tel which way, that nedle may be found </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>No by my fay sir, though I might haue an hundred pound. <pb n="65"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Thou her lickdish didst not say the neele wold be gitten ? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>No hodge by the same token, you where that time beshitten? </l>
                  <l>For f eare of Hobgobling, you wot wel what I meane, </l>
                  <l>As long as it is sence, I feare me yet ye be scarce cleane </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Wel master rat, you must both learne, &amp; teach vs to forgeue </l>
                  <l>Since Diccon hath confession made, &amp; is so cleane shreue </l>
                  <l>If ye to me conscent, to amend this heauie chaunce, </l>
                  <l>I wil inioyne him here, some open kind of pen-aunce. </l>
                  <l>Of this condition, where ye know my fee is twenty pence </l>
                  <l>For the bloodshed, I am agreed with you here to dispence, </l>
                  <l>Ye shal go quite, so that ye graunt, the matter now to run, </l>
                  <l>To end with mirth emong vs al euen as it was begun. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>Say yea master vicar, &amp; he shal sure confes to be your detter </l>
                  <l>And al we that be heare present, wil loue you much the better </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>My partis the worst,but since you alhere on agree. </l>
                  <l>Go euen to master Bayly, let it be so for mee, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>How saiest thou diccon, art content this shal on me depend </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Go to M. Bayly say on your mind, I know ye are my frend? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Then marke ye wel, to recompence this thy former action </l>
                  <l>Because thou hast offended al, to make them satisfaction, <pb n="66"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before their faces, here kneele downe, &amp; as I shal the teach </l>
                  <l>For thou shalt take on othe, of hodges leather breache </l>
                  <l>First for master Doctor, wpon paine of his cursse, </l>
                  <l>Where he wil pay for al, thou neuer draw thy pursse, </l>
                  <l>And when ye meete at one pot, he shal haue the first Pull, </l>
                  <l>And thou shalt neuer offer him the cup, but it be full </l>
                  <l>To goodwife chat thou shalt be swome, euen on the same wyse </l>
                  <l>If she refuse thy inoney once, neuer to offer it twise. </l>
                  <l>Thou shalt be bound by the same here, as thou dost take it </l>
                  <l>When thou maist drinke of free cost, thou neuer forsake it. </l>
                  <l>For gammer gurtons sake, againe sworne shalt hou bee </l>
                  <l>To helpe hir to hir nedle againe if it do lie in thee </l>
                  <l>And hkewise be bouind: by the vertue of that </l>
                  <l>To be of good abering to Gib hir great Cat </l>
                  <l>Last of al for Hodge, the othe to scanne, </l>
                  <l>Thou shalt neuer take him, for fine gentleman. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Come on fellow Diccon chalbe euen with thee now. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>Thou wilt not sticke to do this Diccon I trow. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>No by my fathers skin, my hand downe I lay it? </l>
                  <l>Loke as I haue promised, I wil not denay it, </l>
                  <l>But Hodge take good heede now, thou do not beshite me. </l>
               </sp>
               <stage type="mix">And gaue him a good blow on the buttocke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gogs hart thou false villame dost thou bite me? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>What Hodge doth he hurt the or euer he begin. <pb n="67"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>He thrust me into the buttocke, with a bodkin or a pin, </l>
                  <l>I saie Gammer, Gammer? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>How now Hodge, how now. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Gods malt Gammer gurton. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art inad ich trow. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Will you see the deuil Gammer. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>The deuil sonne, god blesse vs. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chould iche were hanged Gammer. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Mary so ye might dresse vs. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chaue it by the masse Gammer </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>What not my neele Hodge? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Your Neele Gammer, your neele. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>No fie, dost but dodge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Cha found your neele Gammer, here in my hand be it </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>For al the loues on earth Hodge, let me see it. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Soft Gammer. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Good Hodge. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Soft ich say, tarie a while. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Nay sweete Hodge say truth, and do not me begile. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Cham sure on it ich warrant you [mdash ] it goes no more a stray </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Hodge when I speake so faire: wilt stil say me nay </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Go neare the light gammer, this wel in faith good lucke: </l>
                  <l>Chwas almost vndone [mdash ] twas so far in my buttocke </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Tis min owne deare neele Hodge, sykerly I wot </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Chani I not a good sonne gammer, cham I not, </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Christs blessing light on thee, hast made me for euer </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                  <l>Ich knew that ich must finde it, els choud a had it neuer. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                  <l>By my troth Gossyp gurton, I am euen as glad </l>
                  <l>As though I mme owne selfe as good a turne had:. <pb n="68"/>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>And I by my concience, to see it so come forth, </l>
                  <l>Reioyce so much at it, as three nedles be worth. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                  <l>I am no whit sory to see you so reioyce. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Nor I much the gladder for al this noyce: </l>
                  <l>Yet say gramercy Diccon, for springing of the gaine </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
                  <l>Grammercy Diccon twenty times, o how glad cham, </l>
                  <l>If that Chould do so much, your masterdome to come hether, </l>
                  <l>Master Rat, goodwife Chat, and Diccon together: </l>
                  <l>Cha but one halfpeny, as far as iche know it, </l>
                  <l>And chil not rest this night, till ich bestow it. </l>
                  <l>If euer ye loue me, let vs go in and drinke </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
                  <l>I am content if the rest thmke as I thinke? </l>
                  <l>Master Rat it shalbe best for you if we so doo, </l>
                  <l>Then shall you warme you and dresse your self too. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
                  <l>Soft syrs, take vs with you, the company shalbe the more, </l>
                  <l>As proude coms behinde they say, as any goes before, </l>
                  <l>But now my good masters since we must be gone </l>
                  <l>And leaue you behinde vs, here all alon: </l>
                  <l>Since at our last ending thus mery we bee, </l>
                  <l>For Gammer Gurtons nedle sake, let vs haue a plaudytie. </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>Finis, Gurton. Perused and alowed, &amp;c.</trailer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

