<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Intelligencer</title>
            <author>Swift, Jonathan, 1667-1745</author>
            <author>Sheridan, Thomas, 1687-1738</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp>
               <name>Woolley, James D.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority xml:id="wooja1">deposited by<name type="person">Woolley, James D.</name>
               <name type="department">English Department</name>
               <name type="institution">Lafayette College</name>
               <name type="place">Easton</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>English Department</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Lafayette College</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Easton, PA, USA</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>18042</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="email">woolleyj@lafayette.edu</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>1992-03-12</date>
            </authority>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/3029</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106000285</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106000286</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
      </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Revised version of  <relatedItem type="older" target="http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/1642"/>
            </bibl>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Intelligencer</title>
                  <author>Swift, Jonathan, 1667-1745</author>
                  <author>Sheridan, Thomas, 1687-1738</author>
                  <editor>Woolley, James D.</editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                  <date>1990</date>
                  <idno type="isbn">0198126700</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Intelligencer was a weekly paper published in Dublin by Dean Swift and Dr. Thomas Sheridan; there were 20 numbers issued and printed collectively, [1728 - 1729]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notAfter="1729"/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <term type="genre">Irish periodicals -- 18th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-09-27">Header normalised</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div n="I" type="article">
            <head>Article I</head>
            <head>For Saturday May 11th, 1728. To be continued Weekly.   </head>
            <p>IT may be said, without offence to other Cities, of much 
greater consequence in the World, that our Town of Dublin 
doth not want it's due proportion of Folly, and Vice, both 
Native and Imported; And as to those Imported, we have the 
advantage to receive them last, and consequently after our 
happy manner to improve, and refine upon them. </p>
            <p>But, because there are many Effects of Folly and Vice 
among us, whereof some are general, others confined to 
smaller Numbers, and others again, perhaps to a few 
individuals; There is a Society lately established, who at 
great expence, have Erected an Office of Intelligence, from 
which they are to receive Weekly Information of all 
Important Events and Singularities, which this famous 
Metropolis can furnish. Strict injunctions are given to have 
the truest Information: In order to which, certain qualified 
Persons are employed to attend upon Duty in their several 
Posts; some at the Play-house, others in Churches, some at 
Balls, Assemblees, Coffee-houses, and meetings for 
Quadrille; some at the several Courts of Justice, both 
Spiritual and Temporal, some at the College, some upon my 
Lord Mayor and Aldermen in their publick Affairs; lastly, 
some to converse with favourite Chamber-maids, and to 
frequent those Ale-houses, and Brandy-Shops, where the 
Footmen of great Families meet in a Morning; only the 
Barracks and Parliament-house are excepted; because we have 
yet found no enfans perdus bold enough to venture their 
Persons at either. Out of these and some other Store-houses, 
we hope to gather Materials enough to Inform, or Divert, or 
Correct, or Vex the Town. </p>
            <p>But as Facts, Passages, and Adventures of all kinds, are 
like to have the greatest share in our Paper, whereof we 
cannot always Answer for the Truth; due Care shall be taken 
to have them applyed to feigned Names, whereby all just 
Offence will be removed; for if none be guilty, none will 
have cause to Blush or be Angry; if otherwise, then the 
guilty Person is safe for the future upon his present 
Amendment, and safe for the present, from all but his own 
Conscience. </p>
            <p>There is another Resolution taken among us, which I fear 
will give a greater and more general discontent, and is of 
so singular a Nature, that I have hardly confidence enough 
to mention it, although it be absolutely Necessary by way of 
Apology, for so bold and unpopular an Attempt. But so it is, 
that we have taken a desperate Counsel to produce into the 
World every distinguished Action, either of Justice, 
Prudence, Generosity, Charity, Friendship, or publick 
Spirit, which comes well attested to us. And although we 
shall neither here be so daring as to Assign Names, yet we 
shall hardly forbear to give some hints, that perhaps to the 
great displeasure of such deserving Persons may endanger a 
Discovery. For we think that even Virtue it self, should 
submit to such a Mortification, as by it's visibility and 
example, will render it more useful to the World. But 
however, the Readers of these Papers, need not be in pain of 
being over-charged, with so dull and ungrateful a Subject. 
And yet who knows, but such an occasion may be offered to 
us, once in a Year or two, after we shall have settled a 
Correspondence round the Kingdom. </p>
            <p>But after all our boasts of Materials, sent us by our 
several Emissaries, we may probably soon fall short, if the 
Town will not be pleased to lend us further Assistance 
towards entertaining it self. The World best knows it's own 
Faults and Virtues, and whatever is sent shall be faithfully 
returned back, only a little Embellished according to the 
Custom of AUTHORS. We do therefore Demand and Expect 
continual Advertisements in great Numbers, to be sent to the 
PRINTER of this Paper, who hath employed a Judicious 
Secretary to Collect such as may be most useful for the 
Publick. </p>
            <p>And although we do not intend to expose our own Persons 
by mentioning Names, yet we are so far from requiring the 
same Caution in our Correspondents, that on the contrary, we 
expressly Charge and Command them, in all the Facts they 
send us, to set down the Names, Titles, and Places of Abode 
at length; together with a very particular Description of 
the Persons, Dresses, and Dispositions of the several Lords, 
Ladies, Squires, Madams, Lawyers, Gamesters, Toupees, Sots, 
Wits, Rakes, and Informers, whom they shall have occasion to 
mention; otherwise it will not be possible for us to adjust 
our Style to the different Qualities, and Capacities of the 
Persons concerned, and Treat them with the Respect or 
Familiarity, that may be due to their Stations and 
Characters, which we are Determined to observe with the 
utmost strictness, that none may have cause to Complain.    </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="II" type="article">
            <head>Article II</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">Occursare capro, cornu ferit ille, caveto. Vir.   </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MY design, in Writing this Paper, being chiefly to expose 
such Barbarians, who think themselves exempt from those Laws 
of Hospitality, which have, through all Ages and Countries, 
been observed by the best and most distinguished part of 
Mankind; I hope I shall, even in my own Country, find 
Persons enough, to joyn with me in a hearty detestation of a 
certain Country-Squire, at the Relation of the following 
Fact, which I shall tell without the least Aggravation, or 
Partiality. </p>
            <p>Two Clergy-men, of some Distinction, Travelling to the 
Country for their Health, happened to set up together in a 
small Village, which was under the Dominion of a certain 
Animal, dignified with a brace of Titles, that of a 
Militia-Collonel, and a Squire. One of these Gentlemen 
standing in the Street, and observing a Coach-man driving 
his Coach and four Horses furiously against him, turned into 
the close Passage between his Inn and the Sign-post, but the 
Coach-man, instead of driving through the middle of the 
Street, which was the usual and most commodious way, turned 
short, and Drove full upon the Gentleman, without any 
Notice, so that he was on a sudden enclosed between the 
fore-horses, and if his Friend and another Gentleman, who 
were in the middle of the Street, had not suddenly cryed out 
to stop the Coach, he must have unavoidably been trodden 
under the Horses Feet, and his Body bruised to Death by the 
Wheels running over him. His Friend who saw with Terror what 
had like to have befallen him, full of Indignation, repaired 
immediately to the aforesaid Squire or Collonel (to whom he 
was told the Equipage belonged) with a Complaint against his 
Coach-man. But the Squire instead of expressing any Concern, 
or offering any Redress, sent the Doctor away with the 
following Answer. Sir, I have a great Regard for your 
Cloath, and have sent my Coach-man to ask your Friend's 
Pardon; for one of your Servants this moment, told me what 
had happened. But, Sir, said the Doctor, do you think that 
is sufficient? I dare venture to affirm, if the like had 
befallen you, within the Liberties of my Friend, and you 
were brought to the same Danger by his Servant, he would not 
only have him Punished, but at the same time, he would 
discharge him his Service. Sir, (said the Collonel) I tell 
you again, that I have sent my Coach-man to ask his Pardon, 
and I think that is enough, which he spoke with some 
sturdiness; and well he might; for he had two Cannons at his 
Back. Good God, said the Doctor to himself, (when he had got 
out of Gun-shot) what a Hottentot have I been talking to! 
who so little values the Life of a Gentleman, and as it 
happen'd that very Gentleman, to whom the Nation hath in a 
particular manner been obliged. Back he went full of 
Resentment, for the slighting Treatment his Friend met with, 
and very Candidly reported all that passed; who being a Man 
of a different Spirit from that wretched Collonel, ordered 
one of his Servants to Write the following Letter.  </p>
            <p>SIR, MY Master commanded me to tell you, That if you do 
not punish and turn off that Villain your Coach-man, he will 
think there was a Design upon his Life, I put this in 
Writing for fear of mistakes, </p>
            <p>I am your humble Servant to command </p>
            <p>                                                          
A. R.  </p>
            <p>The Superscription was, FOR SQUIRE WETHER, or some such 
Name. </p>
            <p>This Letter was delivered, and away went the Travellers. 
They had not Rode far, before they fell into the Company of 
a Gentleman, a degree above the common Level, and who seemed 
to be a Man of Candor and Integrity, which encouraged them 
to recount what had happened. He said in Answer, that they 
had a narrow escape; and it was a Wonder that the whole Town 
did not fall upon them at once, and worry them; for the 
People there, had little or no Devotion, besides what was 
engaged to the Squire, as an Effect of the Terrors, they lay 
under from their Landlord, who Rode them all down, as poor 
as his Fox-hunters. After this he took occasion with great 
Modesty, and Decency, to draw his Character, which was to 
the following purpose. That the Squire had about fifteen 
hundred Pounds a Year, and lived in a long White-Barn; where 
no Man living was one Farthing the better for him. That his 
Piety consisted in Six Psalms every Day after Dinner, 
without one Drop of Wine. That he had once reduced a certain 
Reverend Dean, plumper than any two of his Brethren, to be 
as slender about the Waste as a Weazle by a Fortnight 
Scouring of bad Ale, to which the Dean was not accustomed. 
That his hospitality was within the enclosure of a Rampart, 
with a Draw-bridge. That if any Gentleman was admitted by 
chance, his entertainment was lean Salt-beef, sour Beer, and 
Muddy Ale. That his Charity was as much upon the catch as a 
Pick-pocket; for his method was to bring others to erect 
Charity-Schools, by promising his Assistance, and so leaving 
them in the Lurch. </p>
            <p>That without the least Tincture of Learning, he was a 
great pretender to Oratory and Poetry, and eminently bad at 
both, which (I hope I shall be excused the Digression) 
brings to my Memory a Character, given by Julius Capitolinus 
of the Emperor VERUS. Melior quidem Orator fuisse dicitur, 
quam Poeta; imo (ut verius dicam) pejor Poeta quam Rhetor, 
(viz.) He was a better Orator than Poet, but, to speak the 
thing more properly, He was a viler Poet than an Orator. But 
to give you a Specimen of his Genius, I shall repeat an 
Epigram of his own Composition (and I am very sure it is 
every Line his own, without any help) which is drawn by a 
Sign-Dawber on the Cross-board of a Ferry-boat, in 
Characters that have hitherto stood the Fury of all 
Weathers.  </p>
            <l>All you that are </l>
            <l>To Andrew Heir, </l>
            <l>And you that him attend </l>
            <l>Shall Ferry'd be, </l>
            <l>Oe'r Carrick free, </l>
            <l>For Blank's the Boatman's Friend.  </l>
            <p>The behaviour of this Squire being of the most Savage 
kind, I think my self obliged out of the tender Regard, 
which I bear to all Strangers, and Travellers, to animadvert 
upon him in as gentle a manner as the occasion will allow. 
And therefore I shall first lay down a few Postulatums. That 
every Travelling-Gentleman is presumed to be under the 
Protection of the Governing-Mayor, Sovereign, Portriff, or 
Squire of the Town or Village, which he happens to make his 
Stage. That the Laws of Humanity, Hospitality and Civility, 
oblige him, if there be no Accommodation in the Publick 
Houses, fit for a Person of Distinction, to invite him to 
his own, or supply the Deficiencies as well as he can. That 
if any Insult or Injury be offered either to such a 
stranger, or his Servants, the Squire is obliged to justify, 
vindicate, and espouse their Cause. This was the method 
observed among the civilized People of the old Jewish, and 
Heathen World; Where we find some of the Patriarchs 
themselves condescending to wash the Feet of such 
Travellers, as they entertained. And so sacred was the 
Regard for Strangers among the Heathens, that they dignifyed 
their Supreme GOD with the Title of Jupiter Hospitalis. 
Nothing was thought so monstrous as to offer any Violence to 
Sojourners among them, which was so religiously observed, 
that it became the glory of the most distinguished Heroes, 
to destroy and extirpate such as were remarkable for their 
Cruelty to Strangers. This it was, which added so much glory 
to the character of Theseus, for the Punishments he 
inflicted on Sisiphus, Procrustes, &amp;c. It was owing 
likewise to a generous Indignation, That Hercules threw 
Diomede (The Collonel and Squire of that Age) to be devoured 
by those Horses, which he fed with the Flesh of poor 
Travellers, and I find upon enquiry that they were Coach-
Horses too. I shall make no farther remark upon this, nor 
Application, but say to the Squire, That it is very happy 
for him the present Age has not one Hercules left, or a Week 
would not pass, before he should feel the weight of that 
Heroe's Club, or be thrown by way of Reprizal under his own 
Horses feet. And I may farther add, that in this whole 
Kingdom, from one end of it to the other, another Squire 
could not be found, who would behave himself in the same 
manner to the same Person; but Hundreds, who on the 
Contrary, would have given all the Satisfaction, that 
Gentlemen of Justice, Humanity, and common Benevolence ought 
to do, upon the like accident, although they had never seen 
him before. I confess this Paper contains nothing besides a 
dry Fact, and a few occasional Observations upon it. But in 
the former I told my READERS, that Facts would be the chief 
part of the Entertainment, I meant to give them. If what I 
have said, may have any Effect on the Person concerned, (to 
whom care shall be taken to send this Account) or if it 
helps to revive the old spirit of Hospitality among us, or 
at least begets a Detestation of the like inhuman Use in 
others; one part of my design is answered. However, it 
cannot be unseasonable to expose Malice, Avarice, Brutality, 
and Hypocrisie, wherever we find it.     </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="III" type="article">
            <head>Article III</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">Ipse per Omnes ibit Personas, <lb/>
Et turbam reddet in uno.  </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Players having now almost done with the Comedy, 
called the Beggars Opera, for this Season, it may be no 
unpleasant Speculation, to reflect a little upon this 
Dramatick Piece, so singular in the Subject, and the manner, 
so much an Original, and which hath frequently given so very 
agreeable an Entertainment. </p>
            <p>Although an evil Tast be very apt to prevail, both here, 
and in London, yet there is a point which whoever can 
rightly Touch, will never fail of pleasing a very great 
Majority; so great, that the Dislikers, out of Dulness or 
Affectation will be silent, and forced to fall in with the 
Herd; the point I mean, is what we call Humour, which in its 
Perfection is allowed to be much preferable to Wit, if it be 
not rather the most useful, and agreeable Species of it. </p>
            <p>I agree with Sir William Temple, that the Word is 
peculiar to our English Tongue, but I differ from him in the 
Opinion, that the thing it self is peculiar to the English 
Nation, because the contrary may be found in many Spanish, 
Italian, and French Productions, and particularly, whoever 
hath a Tast for True Humour, will find a Hundred Instances 
of it in those Volumes Printed in France, under the Name of 
Le Theatre Italien, to say nothing of Rabelais, Cervantes, 
and many others. </p>
            <p>Now I take the Comedy or Farce, (or whatever Name the 
Criticks will allow it) called the Beggars Opera; to excell 
in this Article of Humour. And, upon that Merit, to have met 
with such prodigious success both here, and in England. </p>
            <p>As to Poetry, Eloquence, and Musick, which are said to 
have most Power over the minds of Men, it is certain that 
very few have a Tast or Judgment of the Excellencies of the 
two former, and if a Man succeeds in either, it is upon the 
Authority of those few Judges, that lend their Taste to the 
bulk of Readers, who have none of their own. I am told there 
are as few good Judges in Musick, and that among those who 
Crowd the Operas, Nine in Ten go thither meerly out of 
Curiosity, Fashion, or Affectation. </p>
            <p>But a Taste for Humour is in some manner fixed to the 
very Nature of Man, and generally Obvious to the Vulgar, 
except upon Subjects too refined, and Superior to their 
Understanding. </p>
            <p>And as this Taste of Humour is purely Natural, so is 
Humour it self, neither is it a Talent confined to Men of 
Wit, or Learning; for we observe it sometimes among common 
Servants, and the meanest of the People, while the very 
Owners are often Ignorant of the Gift they possess. </p>
            <p>I know very well, that this happy Talent is contemptibly 
Treated by Criticks, under the Name of low Humour, or low 
Comedy; but I know likewise, that the Spaniards and 
Italians, who are allowed to have the most Wit of any Nation 
in Europe, do most excell in it, and do most esteem it. </p>
            <p>By what Disposition of the mind, what Influence of the 
Stars, or what Situation of the Clymate this endowment is 
bestowed upon Mankind, may be a Question fit for 
Philosophers to Discuss. It is certainly the best Ingredient 
towards that kind of Satyr, which is most useful, and gives 
the least Offence; which instead of lashing, Laughs Men out 
of their Follies, and Vices, and is the Character which 
gives Horace the Preference to Juvenal. </p>
            <p>And although some things are too Serious, Solemn, or 
Sacred to be turned into Ridicule, yet the Abuses of them 
are certainly not, since it is allowed that Corruption in 
Religion, Politicks, and Law, may be proper Topicks for this 
kind of Satyr. </p>
            <p>There are two ends that Men propose in Writing Satyr, one 
of them less Noble than the other, as regarding nothing 
further than personal Satisfaction, and pleasure of the 
Writer; but without any View towards Personal Malice; The 
other is a Publick Spirit, prompting Men of Genius and 
Virtue, to mend the World as far as they are able. And as 
both these ends are innocent, so the latter is highly 
commendable. With Regard to the former, I demand whether I 
have not as good a Title to Laugh, as Men have to be 
Ridiculous, and to expose Vice, as another hath to be 
Vicious. If I Ridicule the Follies and Corruptions of a 
Court, a Ministry, or a Senate; are they not amply payed by 
Pensions, Titles, and Power, while I expect and desire no 
other Reward, than that of Laughing with a few Friends in a 
Corner. Yet, if those, who take Offence, think me in the 
Wrong, I am ready to Change the Scene with them, whenever 
they please. </p>
            <p>But if my Design be to make Mankind better, then I think 
it is my Duty, at least I am sure it is the Interest of 
those very Courts and Ministers, whose Follies or Vices I 
Ridicule, to reward me for my good Intentions; For, if it be 
reckoned an high point of Wisdom to get the Laughers on our 
side, it is much more easy, as well as Wise to get those on 
our side, who can make Millions Laugh when they please. </p>
            <p>My Reason for mentioning Courts, and Ministers, (whom I 
never think on, but with the most profound Veneration) is 
because an Opinion obtains, that in the Beggars Opera there 
appears to be some Reflections upon Courtiers and States-
Men, whereof I am by no means a Judge. </p>
            <p>It is true indeed that Mr. GAY, the Author of this Piece, 
hath been somewhat singular in the Course of his Fortunes, 
for it hath happened, that after Fourteen Years attending 
the Court, with a large Stock of real Merit, a Modest, and 
Agreeable Conversation, a Hundred Promises, and five Hundred 
Friends, he hath failed of Preferment, and upon a very 
Weighty Reason. He lay under the Suspicion of having Written 
a Libel, or Lampoon against a great M------ It is true that 
great M------ was demonstratively convinced, and publickly 
owned his Conviction, that Mr. Gay was not the Author; but 
having lain under the Suspicion, it seemed very just, that 
he should suffer the Punishment; because in this most 
reformed Age, the Virtues of a great M------ are no more to 
be suspected, than the Chastity of Cæsar's Wife. </p>
            <p>It must be allowed, That the Beggars-Opera is not the 
first of Mr. Gay's Works, wherein he hath been faulty, with 
regard to Courtiers and States-Men. For, to omit his other 
Pieces, even in his Fables, published within two Years past, 
and Dedicated to the D. of Cumberland, for which he was 
PROMISED a Reward; he hath been thought somewhat too bold 
upon Courtiers. And although it is highly probable, he meant 
only the Courtiers of former times, yet he acted unwarily, 
by not considering, that the Malignity of some people might 
misinterpret what he said to the disadvantage of present 
Persons, and Affairs. </p>
            <p>But I have now done with Mr. Gay as a Politician, and 
shall consider him henceforward only as Author of the 
Beggars Opera, wherein he hath by a turn of Humor, entirely 
New, placed Vices of all Kinds in the strongest and most 
odious Light; and thereby done eminent Service, both to 
Religion and Morality. This appears from the unparallel'd 
Success he hath met with. All Ranks, Parties and 
Denominations of Men, either crowding to see his Opera, or 
reading it with delight in their Closets, even Ministers of 
State, whom he is thought to have most offended (next to 
those whom the Actors more immediately represent) appearing 
frequently at the Theatre, from a consciousness of their own 
Innocence, and to convince the World how unjust a Parallel, 
Malice, Envy, and Disaffection to the Government have made. </p>
            <p>I am assured that several worthy Clergy-Men in this City, 
went privately to see the Beggars-Opera represented; and 
that the fleering Coxcombs in the Pit, amused themselves 
with making Discoveries, and spreading the Names of those 
Gentlemen round the Audience. </p>
            <p>I shall not pretend to vindicate a Clergy-Man, who would 
appear openly in his Habit at a Theatre, among such a 
vicious Crew, as would probably stand round him, and at such 
lewd Comedies, and prophane Tragedies as are often 
represented. Besides I know very well, that Persons of their 
Function are bound to avoid the appearance of Evil, or of 
giving cause of Offence. But when the Lords Chancellors, who 
are Keepers of the King's Conscience, when the Judges of the 
Land, whose Title is Reverend, when Ladies, who are bound by 
the Rules of their Sex, to the strictest Decency, appear in 
the Theatre without Censure, I cannot understand, why a 
young Clergy-man who goes concealed out of Curiosity to see 
an innocent and moral Play, should be so highly condemned; 
nor do I much approve the Rigor of a great P----te who said, 
he hoped none of his Clergy were there. I am glad to hear 
there are no weightier Objections against that Reverend 
Body, planted in this City, and I wish there never may. But 
I should be very sorry that any of them should be so weak, 
as to imitate a COURT-CHAPLAIN in England, who preached 
against the Beggars-Opera, which will probably do more good 
than a thousand Sermons of so stupid, so injudicious, and so 
prostitute a Divine. </p>
            <p>In this happy Performance of Mr. Gay, all the Characters 
are just, and none of them carried beyond Nature, or hardly 
beyond Practice.  It discovers the whole System of that 
Common-Wealth, or that Imperium in Imperio of Iniquity, 
established among us, by which neither our Lives, nor our 
Properties are secure, either in the High-ways, or in 
publick Assemblies, or even in our own Houses. It shews the 
miserable Lives, and the constant Fate of those abandoned 
Wretches; for how little they sell their Lives and Souls; 
betrayed by their Whores; their Comrades; and the Receivers 
and Purchasers of these Thefts and Robberies. This Comedy 
contains likewise a Satyr, which, although it doth by no 
means affect the present Age, yet might have been useful in 
the former and may possibly be so in Ages to come. I mean 
where the Author takes occasion of comparing those common 
Robbers to Robbers of the Publick; and their several 
Stratagems of betraying, undermining, and hanging each 
other, to the several Arts of Politicians in times of 
Corruption. </p>
            <p>This Comedy likewise exposeth with great Justice, that 
unnatural Taste for Italian Musick among us, which is wholly 
unsuitable to our Northern Climat, and the genius of the 
People, whereby we are over-run with Italian-Effeminacy, and 
Italian Nonsence. An old Gentleman said to me, that many 
Years ago, when the practice of an unnatural Vice grew so 
frequent in London, that many were Prosecuted for it, he was 
sure it would be a Fore-runner of Italian-Opera's, and 
Singers; and then we should want nothing but Stabbing or 
Poysoning, to make us perfect Italians. </p>
            <p>Upon the Whole, I deliver my Judgment, That nothing but 
servile Attachment to a Party, affectation of Singularity, 
lamentable Dullness, mistaken Zeal, or studied Hypocrisy, 
can have the least reasonable Objection against this 
excellent Moral-performance of the CELEBRATED MR. GAY.    </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="IV" type="article">
            <head>Article IV</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">Quando alea hos animos? </q>
               <bibl>Juv.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMONG all the Amusements, invented by the idle part of 
Mankind, to pass away their Time, there is not one, which is 
attended with so many Evil Consequences as that of Gaming, 
nor indeed any so much below the Dignity of Human-Nature, it 
being an Employment so Trifling in Appearance, that a Man 
with a Box and Dice, is hardly distinguishable from a Child 
with it's Rattle, nor when he Diverts himself with a few 
scraps of Painted Paste-board, does he make one whit a 
better figure. </p>
            <p>But setting Appearances of this kind aside, which can 
make even the Wisest look Ridiculous, I shall chiefly Dwell 
upon the more solid Evils, that attend all intemperate 
practitioners in this way, and these I shall Sum up in the 
following Losses, viz. Loss of Time; Loss of Reputation; 
Loss of Health; Loss of Fortune; Loss of Temper; and what is 
often the Effect of it, the Loss of Life it self. </p>
            <p>First, That it is a Loss of Time, is plain, because our 
Time may be employ'd to more advantage; for by Six Hours in 
the twenty four, I can make my self Wiser, and better, and 
Richer; whereas on the Contrary, by Cards or Dice, I do 
Infallibly grow more Stupid, and Worse; and a Hundred to One 
against me I grow Poorer. </p>
            <p>Secondly, That it is a Loss of Reputation, and Esteem in 
the World, is easily proved, because no Man of Reputation or 
Esteem was ever called a Gamester; Eo. vice versa, No 
Gamester can be called a Man of Reputation and Esteem. For 
in giving the best Characters to Men or Women, we never use 
the Word Gaming as an Epithet. We say, for Instance, A great 
and Glorious King; A wise and a good Governor; A learned and 
a Pious Bishop; An unbiassed and just Chancellor; a Virtuous 
and a Modest Lady, and so through the best Degrees of Men 
and Women. But how odly would it sound, if we should take 
out the latter Epithet from each of these, and put in their 
stead the Word Gaming. And say, A Wise and a Gaming King; A 
Learned and a Gaming Bishop; An unbiassed and Gaming 
Chancellor; A Virtuous and a Gaming Lady, &amp;c. From which 
it is plain, that Gaming must stand and agree with the worst 
Characters; For it Sounds very well to say, A Profligate 
Gaming Spendthrift; A Notorious Gaming Sharper; A Swearing 
Gaming Bully. And the same Epithet will agree as well with 
Pick-pockets, Rakes, Highway-men, and others of that 
distinguished Race of Mankind. </p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it is a Loss of Health follows from the 
Sedentary Life, to which those who follow Gaming are 
confined; whence, as I am told by a knowing Physician, 
proceed Dropsies, Gouts, Gravel, and Stone in the Men; and 
in the Women, Tympanies of both kinds, Hystericks, Vapours, 
and a load of bad Humours, for want of those Exercises, 
which produce Perspiration, and Evacuations necessary to 
Invigorate, Strengthen, and preserve the Animal Oeconomy, 
free from those Numerous Distempers, which Laziness and 
Sloth produce. </p>
            <p>Fourthly, That it is a Loss of Fortune is out of all 
Dispute, from the Numberless Instances, I cou'd give of 
Lords, Ladies, and Squires, some of whom have lost their 
whole Estates; others the most part; others again have laid 
themselves under such difficulties, that their Annual Income 
has fallen very short to supply them with the Common 
Necessaries of Life; so that they have been obliged to live 
upon the Credit of the ensuing Year. </p>
            <p>And as for Ladies whose Pride would not permit them to be 
so obliged to their Creditors, they either pawn their 
Houshold Moveables, or Sell (what next to Gaming, goes 
nearest to their Heart), their very Parapharnalia; but this 
I must Remark, has happend chiefly among those who have been 
seduced as Cullies to the Fashionable Game of Quadrill. It 
will not be here Foreign to my purpose, to Write down some 
few Inventories of Goods, lately hawked about by trusty 
Chamber-maids.  </p>
            <p>       Belonging to Lady FLAVIA near Stephen's-Green. 1 
Diamond Necklace, 1 Pair of Diamond Ear-Rings, 3 Diamond-
Rings, and a Gold Watch with Trinckets.  </p>
            <p>To Mrs. DORINDA of Dawson-Street. 2 Large Silver-Cups, 3 
Salvers, 2 Pair of Candlesticks, 1 Silver Sauce-Pan.  </p>
            <p>To Madam CHLOE in Jervice-Street. 2 Birth-Day Suits, 1 
Piece of French Damask, Broad Green Stripe, with White 
Flowers, Pawned for Nine Pounds, 4 Damask Table-Cloaths, and 
a Dozen of Napkins.  </p>
            <p>To Madam LIBERIA of College-Green. A fine wrought 
Coverlet of a Bed, A picture of her Husband's Father and 
Mother set in Gold, A Gold Snuff-box, 1 Dozen of Silver-
spoons, A Child's Bells and Coral.  </p>
            <p>I have had an Account of many more, but this is full 
enough to answer my Design, for I intend only by this 
discovery that their Husbands should add a little more to 
their Pin-money, and thereby enable them to pay their Debts 
of Honour, in a less Scandalous way. </p>
            <p>Indeed it would not be amiss, if Husbands should make use 
of their Authority, at least to regulate one Circumstance, 
that is, to bring their Wives to be content with two Hours 
Play, instead of twelve in the four and twenty; because some 
Inconveniences attend it. The Servants having all that Time 
to themselves, to Intreigue; to Juncket; to Filsh and Steal; 
to pawn the Inferior Moveables of the Pantry, and Kitchen; 
and lastly to Corrupt the Children; by teaching them 
Cursing, Swearing, Lying, and Lewdness, which in all 
probability may bring both Ruin and Disgrace to their 
Family. </p>
            <p>It is very well known that among the great and 
fashionable People of former ages, they very rarely had 
recourse to Gaming. We read that Artaxerxes, Cato, and 
Augustus, did sometimes Divert themselves this Way, but I 
cannot recollect that ever the Ladies entered into it at 
all, their Amusements being rather the Needle and the Loom; 
for which their Perfections are Celebrated by the Oldest and 
best Poet of the World. The Men of any Consequence, passed 
their Evenings in Learned and agreeable Conversation, such 
as tended to make them wiser and better, for which I appeal 
to the Symposiacks of Plato, the Feast of Xenophon, and 
those Accounts given by Macrobius. And to bring the matter 
nearer our own Times, the People of the greatest 
Consequence, in these British Isles, have chosen rather to 
pass away their Evenings in Polite Discourses with one 
another; and I should think that I failed in a due 
Veneration for their Memories, if I should pass their Names 
over in Silence. The Celebrated Lord Falkland, Earl 
Carnarvan, Endymion Porter, Mr. Waller, Sir John Sucklin; 
and among the conversible Ladies, The Countesses of Bedford, 
Carlisle, Devonshire, and several others. This way of 
Improvement is elegantly described by Horace.  </p>
            <l>      -------------Ergo </l>
            <l>Sermo oritur, non de villis domibusve alienis: </l>
            <l>Nec male necne Lepos Saltet: sed quod magis ad nos </l>
            <l>Pertinet, et nescire malum est agitamus: utrumne </l>
            <l>Divitiis homines, an sint virtute beati: </l>
            <l>Quidve ad amicitias, Usus, rectumne trahat nos: </l>
            <l>Et quæ sit natura boni, summumq; quid ejus.  </l>
            <l>Thus after plain Repast, each cheerful Guest, </l>
            <l>With useful Conversation, Crowns the Feast, </l>
            <l>Not Trifling Chat, on this, or tother Place, </l>
            <l>Or Lepos Dancing with a better Grace; </l>
            <l>But what is more Concern to Humane kind, </l>
            <l>To mend our Manners, and improve the mind. </l>
            <l>On Philosophick Questions wisely bent, </l>
            <l>As whether Wealth or Virtue gives content, </l>
            <l>What Cause directs us in the Choice of Friends, </l>
            <l>Our private Int'rest, or more Noble Ends. </l>
            <l>What Road to chuse, what End we should pursue, </l>
            <l>And how to keep the Good Supreme in View.  </l>
            <p>For my own Part I could rather Wish, and I believe many 
Husbands would agree with me, That the Ladies would rather 
employ themselves, as Juvenal Describes those in his Time, 
in Fighting Prizes upon a Publick Stage, whereby they would 
at least discover their Activity, and their Courage, in a 
much more becoming manner, than (according to the present 
Practice) pulling of Coifs upon a wrangle at Quadrill. </p>
            <p>The Ancients did so far abhor any Excess in Gaming, That 
Aristotle in his 4th Book of Ethicks, at the latter end of 
the 1st. Chap. places Tyrants, Gamester's and Robbers in one 
Class, their Dispositions being exactly the same: For who 
ever yet knew a right Gamester, that was not apt to insult 
upon Success, or to pillage all before him upon every 
Advantage. The Author I have now mentioned Stiles them very 
justly aischrokerdeis (I wish the Ladies understood Greek) 
We have no English Word expressive enough to explain it. The 
nearest meaning I can think of is base-gainers. And what can 
be baser, than to sit down deliberately with a Friend, 
either at his House, or my own, with an Intention to pick 
his Pocket, by a lucky Throw of a Dye, or a Cast of a Card. 
This has been frequently the Practice. However I shall 
content my self with a Relation of one Fact, because it is 
somewhat singular in it's kind. </p>
            <p>BRYANIA the Virago one Evening, invited the beautiful 
Morisda to a game of Cards at her House, which the latter 
declined, as having neither Skill, nor Inclination, nor 
Money for Play; yet by much Importunity was prevailed on to 
sup with her. Soon after BRYANIA calls for a Pack of Cards, 
and told the poor innocent Lady, she would instruct her in a 
Game, which a Child of four Years old might learn in four 
Minutes; to this the complying good-natured Morisda 
willingly consented, upon her Friend's telling her she might 
lose very little by low playing at this Game. Accordingly 
they fixt upon three-pence a Counter. They had not played 
above three Hours, when the poor Cully was told she had lost 
about a trifle of twenty Guineas. Being not able to command 
twenty Shillings in the world, she took her leave in great 
Confusion, and Grief, promising to discharge the Debt in a 
litle Time. The unmerciful BRYANIA dunned her the Day 
following, and so continued for a Week. This put the poor 
indigent Lady upon trying all Friends. In the mean Time, the 
following Letter was written to her, which I have 
Transcribed with the strictest Justice to the Writer.  </p>
            <l>MADDUM, </l>
            <p>I donat undarstand youar tretmint in giuin me they troble 
off </p>
            <p>Sendin so offen forr that trifil wich youe losst too me 
tuther </p>
            <p>nit If youe doo nott sende itt bye they berer I a shuar 
youe I </p>
            <p>wil rite too youar husbund forr itt, Maddum I amm &amp;c.  </p>
            <p>This terrible Letter put the poor Lady to her last Shifts 
(nor is it a wonder it should, her Husband being the 
greatest Bear living) which was to borrow the Money of a 
certain Collonel, and this, uncharitable People did 
misinterpret for a Valuable Consideration. </p>
            <p>The fifth Loss, I mentioned, was that of Temper. If any 
one doubts the Truth of this Position, I refer him to the 
Groom Porters, and Lucas's-Coffee-House, where the only 
Virtuosi of the Gaming Science are Daily and Nightly to be 
seen. If Blaspheming, Cursing, Swearing, Duelling, Runing of 
Heads against the Wall, Throwing Hats and Wigs in the Fire, 
Distortions of the Countenance, Biting of Nails, Burning of 
Cards, Breaking of Dice-Boxes, can be called a Loss of 
Temper, they are found in the aforesaid places, in the 
highest degree of Perfection. And to make out the last and 
greatest Loss, which is, The Loss of Life. </p>
            <p>I have, according to the best of my Memory, heard of no 
less than seven or eight worthy Gentlemen of the Trade, 
within a very few Years, upon some hasty Words and Blows, 
given at some of these Gaming-Tables, retire from their 
Company, and one of them bring in the News of the other's 
Death in about Six Minutes. </p>
            <p>Upon the whole, I cannot but remark, That Gaming proceeds 
from three Qualities of the basest kind, Avarice, Laziness 
and Ignorance; For it must undoubtedly be a thirst for Gain, 
which is a motive to high playing; and as for the Lazy and 
Ignorant (if they play low) I am more willing to indulge 
them, because they have naturally better Talents for sitting 
and trifling, than wholsome bodily Exercise, or spending the 
Evenings in a way of Conversation, agreeable to Rational 
Creatures. </p>
            <p>I shall end this Paper with a very useful Remark. Plato 
is my Author, that the Demon THEUTH was the Inventor of Dice 
(The Ladies know well enough, that the Devil and Demon are 
the same) and the Vulgar have it by Tradition, that Cards 
are the Devil's own Invention, for which reason, time out of 
mind, they are and have been called the Devil's Books, 
therefore I cannot but say after this Information given, if 
Gamesters will not desist, they are undoubtedly at the 
Devil's Devotion.       </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="V" type="article">
            <head>Article V</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">
                  <l>Describ'd it's thus: Defin'd would you it have?</l>
                  <l>Then the World's honest Man's an errant Knave.</l>
               </q>
               <bibl>BEN. JOHNSON </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THERE is no Talent so useful towards rising in the World, 
or which puts Men more out of the reach of Fortune, than 
that Quality generally possessed by the Dullest sort of 
People, and in common Speech, called Discretion, a species 
of lower Prudence, by the assistance of which, People of the 
meanest Intellectuals, without any other Qualification, pass 
through the World in great Tranquility, and with Universal 
good Treatment, neither giving nor taking Offence. Courts 
are seldom unprovided of Persons under this Character, on 
whom, if they happen to be of great Quality, most 
Employments, even the greatest naturally fall, when 
Competitors will not agree; and in such Promotions, no Body 
rejoyces or grieves. The Truth of this I could prove by 
several Instances, within my own Memory (for I say nothing 
of present Times.) </p>
            <p>And indeed as Regularity and Forms are of great use in 
carrying on the Business of the World, so it is very 
convenient, that Persons endued with this kind of 
Discretion, should have that share which is proper to their 
Talents in the Conduct of Affairs, but by no means to meddle 
in matters which require Genius, Learning, strong 
Comprehension, quickness of Conception, Magnanimity, 
Generosity, Sagacity, or any other superior Gift of Human 
minds. Because this sort of Discretion, is usually attended 
with a strong desire of Money, and few Scruples about the 
way of obtaining it, with servile Flattery and Submission, 
with a Want of all publick Spirit or Principle, with a 
perpetual wrong Judgment when the Owners come into Power, 
and High Place, how to dispose of Favour and Preferment, 
having no measure for Merit, and Virtue in others, but those 
very Steps by which themselves ascended; Nor the least 
Intention of doing Good or Hurt to the Publick, further than 
Either one or t'other, is likely to be subservient to their 
own Security or Interest. Thus being void of all Friendship 
and Enmity, they never complain nor find Fault with the 
Times, and indeed never have reason to do so. </p>
            <p>Men of eminent Parts and Abilities as well as Virtues do 
sometimes rise in Courts, sometimes in the Law, and 
sometimes even in the Church. Such were the Lord Bacon, the 
Earl of Strafford, Arch-bishop Laud in the Reign of King 
Charles I. and others in our own times whom I shall not 
Name: But these and many more under different Princes, and 
in different Kingdoms, were Disgraced or Banished, or 
suffered Death, meerely in Envy to their Virtues and 
Superior Genius, which emboldned them in great Exigencies 
and distresses of State (wanting a reasonable Infusion of 
this Aldermanly Discretion) to attempt the Service of their 
Prince and Country out of the common Forms. </p>
            <p>This evil Fortune, which generally attends extraordinary 
Men in the Management of great Affairs, hath been imputed to 
divers Causes, that need not be here set down, when so 
obvious a One occurs. For, if what a certain Writer 
observes, be true, that, when a great Genius appears in the 
World, the Dunces are all in Confederacy against him: And 
thus although he imploys his Talents wholly in his Closet, 
without interfaring with any Man's Ambition or Avarice; what 
must he expect when he ventures out to seek for Preferment 
in a Court, but Universal Opposition, when he is mounting 
the Ladder, and every hand ready to turn him off, when he is 
at the Top? And in this point Fortune generally Acts 
directly contrary to Nature, For in Nature we find, that 
Bodies full of Life and Spirit mount easily, and are hard to 
fall, whereas heavy Bodies are hard to rise, and come down 
with greater Velocity, in Proportion to their weight. But we 
find Fortune every Day Acting just the reverse of this. </p>
            <p>This Talent of Discretion, as I have described it in it's 
several Adjuncts and Circumstances, is no where so 
serviceable as to the Clergy, to whose Preferment, nothing 
is so fatal as the Character of Wit, Politeness in Reading, 
or Manners, or that kind of Behaviour which we contract, by 
having too much Conversed with Persons of high Stations and 
Eminency, these Qualifications being reckoned by the Vulgar 
of all Ranks to be marks of Levity, which is the last Crime 
the World will pardon in a Clergy-Man. To this I may add a 
free manner of speaking in mixt Company, and too frequent an 
Appearance in places of much resort, which are equally 
Noxious to Spiritual Promotions. </p>
            <p>I have known indeed a few Exceptions to some parts of 
these Regulations. I have seen some of the Dullest Men alive 
aiming at Witt, and others with as little Pretensions, 
affecting Politeness in Manners and Discourse, but never 
being able to persuade the World of their Guilt, they grew 
into considerable Stations, upon the firm Assurance which 
all People had of their Discretion, because they were a Size 
too low to deceive the World to their own Disadvantage. But 
this I confess is a Tryal too dangerous often to engage in. </p>
            <p>There is a known Story of a Clergy-Man, who was 
recommended for a Preferment by some great Man at Court, to 
A.B.C.T. His Grace said, he had heard that the Clergy-Man 
used to play at Whisk and Swobbers, that as to playing now 
and then a Sober Game at Whisk for pastime, it might be 
pardoned, but he could not digest those wicked Swobbers, and 
it was with some pains that my Lord S----rs could undeceive 
him. I ask, by what Talents we may suppose that great Pr---- 
ascended so high, or what sort of Qualifications he would 
expect in those whom he took into his Patronage, or would 
probably recommend to Court for the government of Distant 
Churches. </p>
            <p>Two Clergy-Men in my Memory stood Candidates for a small 
Free-School in ----Shire, where a Gentleman of Quality and 
Interest in the Country, who happened to have a better 
understanding than his Neighbours, procured the place for 
him who was the better Schollar, and more Gentlemanly Person 
of the two, very much to the Regret of all the Parish; The 
other being disappointed, came up to London, where he became 
the greatest Pattern of this lower Discretion, that I have 
known and possessed with as heavy Intellectuals, which 
together with the coldness of his Temper, and gravity of his 
Deportment, carried him safe through many Difficulties, and 
he lived and dyed in a great Station, while his Competitor 
is too obscure for Fame to tell us what became of him. </p>
            <p>This Species of Discretion which I so much celebrate, and 
do most heartly recommend, hath one Advantage not yet 
mentioned, that it will carry a Man safe through all the 
Malice and Variety of Parties, so far, that whatever Faction 
happen to be uppermost, his Claim is usually allowed for a 
share of what is going. And the thing seems to be highly 
reasonable. For in all great Changes, the prevailing side is 
usually so Tempestuous, that it wants the balast of those 
whom the World calls moderate Men and I call Men of 
Discretion, whom People in Power may with little Ceremony 
load as heavy as they please, drive them through the hardest 
and deepest Roads without danger of Foundring, or breaking 
their Backs, and will be sure to find them neither Resty nor 
Vicious. </p>
            <p>In some following Paper, I will give the Reader a short 
History of two Clergy-Men in England, the Characters of 
each, and the Progress of their Fortunes in the World. By 
which the force of worldly Discretion and the bad 
Consequences from the want of that Virtue will strongly 
appear.     </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="VI" type="article">
            <head>Article VI</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">O patria! o divum domus!  </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHEN I Travel through any part of this unhappy Kingdom 
(and I have now by several Excursions, made from Dublin, 
gone thro' most Counties of it) it raises two Passions in my 
Breast of a different kind; An Indignation against those 
vile betrayers and Insulters of it, who Insinuate themselves 
into Favour, by saying, It is a Rich Nation; and a sincere 
Compassion for the Natives, who are sunk to the lowest 
Degree of Misery and Poverty, whose Houses are Dunghills, 
whose Victuals are the Blood of their Cattle, or the Herbs 
in the Field; and whose Cloathing to the Dishonour of God 
and Man is Nakedness.  Yet Notwithstanding all these Dismal 
Appearances, it is the Common Phrase of an upstart Race of 
People, who have suddenly sprung up like the Dragons Teeth 
among us: That Ireland was never known to be so Rich as it 
is now; by which as I apprehend, they can only mean 
Themselves, for they have Skipt over the Channel from the 
Vantage Ground of a Dunghill upon no other Merit, either 
Visible or Divinable, than that of not having been born 
among us. </p>
            <p>This is the Modern way of Planting Colonies--Et ubi 
Solitudinem faciunt, id imperium vocant.  When those who are 
so unfortunate to be born here, are excluded from the 
meanest Preferments, and deem'd incapable of being 
entertain'd, even as common Soldiers, whose poor stipend is 
but Four pence a Day.  No Trade, no Emoluments, no 
Encouragement for Learning among the Natives, who yet by a 
perverse consequence are divided into Factions, with as much 
Violence, and Rancour, as if they had the Wealth of the 
Indies to contend for.  It puts me in mind of a Fable which 
I Read in a Monkish Author.  He quotes for it one of the 
Greek Mythologists, That once upon a Time a Colony of large 
Dogs (called the Molossi) Transplanted themselves from 
Epirus to [AElig ]tolia where they seized those parts of the 
Countries, most fertile in Flesh of all kinds, obliging the 
Native Dogs to retire from their best Kennels, to live under 
Ditches and Bushes.  But to preserve good Neighbourhood, and 
Peace, and finding likewise, that the [AElig ]tolian Dogs might 
be of some use in the low Offices of Life, they passed a 
Decree, That the Natives should be entituled to the Short-
Ribs, Tips of Tails, Knuckle-Bones, and Guts of all the 
Game, which they were obliged by their Masters to Run Down: 
This Condition was accepted, and what was a little Singular, 
while the Molossian Dogs kept a good understanding among 
themselves, living in Peace and Luxury, these [AElig ]tolian 
Curs were perpetually snarling, growling, barking, and 
tearing out each others Throats. Nay, sometimes those of the 
best Quality among them, were seen to Quarrel with as much 
Rancour for a Rotten Gut, as if it had been a fat haunch of 
Venison.  But what need we wonder at this in Dogs, when the 
same is every Day practised among Men. </p>
            <p>Last Year I Travelled from Dublin to Dundalk, thro' a 
Country esteemed the most Fruitful part of this Kingdom, and 
so Nature intended it.  But no Ornaments or Improvements of 
such a Scene were visible.  No Habitations fit for 
Gentlemen.  No Farmers Houses.  Few Fields of Corn, and 
almost a bare Face of nature, without new Plantations of any 
kind, only a few miserable Cottages, at least three or four 
Miles distance, and one Church in the Centre between this 
City and Droghedah.  When I arriv'd at this last Town, the 
first mortifying Sight, was the Ruins of several Churches, 
batter'd down by that Usurper Cromwell, whose Fanatick Zeal 
made more Desolation in a few Days, than the Piety of 
succeeding Prelates, or the Wealth of the Town have, in more 
than sixty Years attempted to repair. </p>
            <p>Perhaps the Inhabitants, through a high strain of Virtue, 
have in Imitation of the Athenians made a Solemn Resolution, 
never to rebuild those sacred Edifices, but rather leave 
them in ruins, as Monuments, to perpetuate the detestable 
memory of that hellish Instrument of Rebellion, Desolation 
and Murther.  For, the Athenians when Mardonius had ravaged 
a great part of Greece took a formal Oath at the Isthmus to 
lose their Lives rather than their Liberty.  To stand by 
their Leaders to the last.  To spare the Cities of such 
Barbarians as they conquered.  And, what crowned all, the 
Conclusion of their Oath was, We will never repair any of 
the Temples, which they have burned and destroyed, that they 
may appear to Posterity as so many Monuments of these wicked 
Barbarians.  This was a glorious Resolution.  And I am sorry 
to think, that the Poverty of my Country-men will not let 
the world suppose, they have acted upon such a generous 
Principle, yet upon this Occasion I cannot but observe that 
there is a fatality in some Nations, to be fond of those, 
who have treated them with the least humanity.  Thus I have 
often heard the memory of Cromwell, who has depopulated and 
almost wholly destroyed this miserable Country, celebrated 
like that of a Saint; and at the same time the Sufferings of 
the Royal Martyr turned into Ridicule, and his Murder 
justifyed even from the Pulpit, and all this done with an 
intent to gain favour under a Monarchy, which is a new 
strain of Politicks that I shall not pretend to account for. </p>
            <p>Examin all the Eastern Towns of Ireland, and you will 
trace this horrid Instrument of Destruction, in the defacing 
of Churches, and particularly in destroying whatever was 
Ornamental, either within or without them.  We see in the 
several Towns a very few Houses scattered among the Ruins of 
thousands, which he laid level with their Streets.  Great 
Numbers of Castles! the Country Seats of Gentlemen then in 
Being, still standing in ruin, habitations for Bats, Daws, 
and Owls, without the least Repairs or Succession of other 
buildings.  Nor have the Country Churches, as far as my Eye 
could reach, met with any better Treatment from him, nine in 
ten of them lying among their Graves, and God only knows 
when they are to have a Resurrection.  When I passed from 
Dundalk where this cursed Usurper's handy-work is yet 
visible, I cast mine Eyes around from the Top of a Mountain, 
from whence I had a wide and a waste Prospect of several 
venerable Ruins; It struck me with a Melancholy, not unlike 
that expressed by Cicero in one of his Letters which being 
much upon the like Prospect, and concluding with a very 
necessary Reflection on the uncertainty of things in this 
World, I shall here insert a translation of what he says.  
In my Return from Asia, as I Sailed from Agina, towards 
Megara, I began to take a prospect of the several Countries 
round about me.  Behind me was Agina: Before me Megara: On 
the right Hand the Piræus: and on the left was Corinth: 
Which Towns were formerly in a most flourishing Condition; 
now they lye prostrate and in Ruin. </p>
            <p>Thus I began to think with my self. Shall we who have but 
a trifling Existence express any resentment, when one of us 
either dies a natural Death, or is Slain, whose Lives are 
necessarily of a short Duration, when at one view I behold 
the Carcases of so many great Cities.  What if he had seen 
the Natives of those free Republicks, reduced to all the 
miserable consequences of a conquered People, living without 
the common defences against Hunger and Cold, rather 
appearing like Specters than Men?  I am apt to think that 
seeing his Fellow-Creatures in Ruin like this, it would have 
put him past all patience for Philosophick Reflections. </p>
            <p>As for my own Part, I confess, that the Sights and 
Occurrences which I had in this my last Journey, have so far 
transported me to a mixture of Rage and Compassion, that I 
am not able to decide, which has the greater Influence upon 
my Spirits; For this new Cant of a rich and flourishing 
Nation, was still upper-most in my Thoughts; Every Mile I 
travelled, giving me such ample Demonstrations to the 
Contrary.  For this reason, I have been at the pains to 
render a most exact and faithful Account of all the visible 
Signs of Riches, which I met with in sixty Miles riding 
through the most publick Roads, and the best part of the 
Kingdom.  First, As to Trade, I met nine Carrs loaden with 
old musty shrivel'd Hydes, one Car-load of Butter.  Four 
Jockeys driving eight Horses, all out of Case.  One Cow and 
Calf, driven by a Man and his Wife.  Six tattered Families 
flitting to be shipped off to the West-Indies.  A Colony of 
a hundred and fifty Beggars, all repairing to people our 
Metropolis, and by encreasing the number of Hands, to 
encrease it's Wealth, upon the old Maxim, that People are 
the Riches of a Nation.  And therefore ten thousand Mouths 
with hardly ten pair of Hands, or any Work to employ them, 
will infallibly make us a rich, and flourishing People.  
2dly, Travellers enough, but seven in ten wanting Shirts and 
Cravats; nine in ten going barefoot, and carrying their 
Brogues and Stockens in their Hands.  One Woman in twenty 
having a Pillion, the rest riding bare-backed.  Above two 
hundred Horsemen, with four pair of Boots amongst them all.  
Seventeen Saddles of Leather (the rest being made of Straw) 
and most of their Garrons only shod before.  I went into one 
of the principal Farmer's Houses, out of Curiosity, and his 
whole Furniture consisted of two Blocks for Stools, a Bench 
on each side the Fire-place made of Turf, six Trenchers, one 
Bowl, a Pot, six Horn-Spoons, three Noggins, three Blankets, 
one of which served the Man and Maid Servant; the others the 
Master of the Family, his Wife and five Children.  A small 
Churn, a wooden Candlestick, a broken Stick for a pair of 
Tongs.  In the publick Towns, one third of the Inhabitants 
walking the Street barefoot. Windows half built up with 
Stone, to save the expence of Glass, the broken Panes up and 
down supplied by brown Paper, few being able to afford 
white; in some places they were stopped with Straw or Hay.  
Another mark of our Riches, are the Signs at the several 
Inns upon the Road, viz. In some a Staff stuck in the 
Thatch, with a Turf at the End of it; a Staff in a Dunghill 
with a white Rag wrapped about the Head; A Pole, where they 
can afford it, with a Beesom at the Top.  An Oatmeal Cake on 
a Board in a Window; And, at the principal Inns of the Road, 
I have observed the Signs taken down and laid against the 
Wall near the Door, being taken from their Post to prevent 
the shaking of the House down by the Wind.  In short, I saw 
not one single House, in the best Town I travelled through, 
which had not manifest Appearances of Beggary and Want.  I 
could give many more Instances of our Wealth, but I hope 
these will suffice for the End I propose. </p>
            <p>It may be objected, What use it is of to display the 
Poverty of the Nation in the manner I have done.  In answer, 
I desire to know for what Ends, and by what Persons, This 
new Opinion of our flourishing State has of late been so 
Industriously advanced.  One thing is certain, that the 
Advancers have either already found their own Account, or 
have been heartily promised, or at least have been 
entertained with hopes, by seeing such an Opinion pleasing 
to those who have it in their power to reward. </p>
            <p>It is no doubt a very generous principle in any Person, 
to rejoice in the felicities of a Nation, where themselves 
are Strangers, or Sojourners.  But if it be found that the 
same Persons on all other Occasions express a hatred and 
contempt of the Nation and People in General, and hold it 
for a Maxim--That the more such a Country is humbled, the 
more their own will rise,  it need be no longer a Secret, 
why such an Opinion and the Advancers of it are encouraged.  
And besides, if the Bayliff reports to his Master, that the 
Ox is Fat and Strong, when in reality it can hardly carry 
it's own Legs, is it not natural to think, that command will 
be given, for a greater load to be put upon it.     </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="VII" type="article">
            <head>Article VII</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">------Probitas laudatur &amp; alget.  </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>CORUSODES an Oxford Student, and a Farmers Son, was never 
absent from Prayers, or Lecture, nor once out of his College 
after Tom had tolld. He spent every Day ten hours in his 
Closet, in Reading his Courses, Dozing, clipping Papers, or 
darning his Stockings, which last he performed to 
Admiration. He could be soberly Drunk at the expence of 
others, with College Ale, and at those Seasons was always 
most Devout. He wore the same Gown five Years, without 
dagling or tearing. He never once looked into a Play-book or 
a Poem. He Read Virgil and Ramus in the same Cadence, but 
with a very different Taste. He never understood a Jest, or 
had the least Conception of Wit. </p>
            <p>For one saying he stands in Renown to this Day. Being 
with some other Students over a Pot of Ale; one of the 
Company said so many pleasant things, that the rest were 
much diverted, only Corusodes was silent and unmoved. When 
they parted, he called this merry Companion aside, and said; 
Sir, I perceived by your often speaking, and our Friends 
laughing, that you spoke many jests, and you could not but 
observe my Silence. But Sir this is my humour, I never make 
a jest myself, nor ever laugh at another Man's. </p>
            <p>Corusodes thus endowed, and got into Holy Orders, having 
by the most extreme Parsimoney, saved thirty four Pounds out 
of a very Beggarly Fellowship, went up to London, where his 
Sister was Waiting-woman to a Lady, and so good a 
Sollicitor, that by her means he was admitted to Read 
Prayers in the Family twice a Day, at fourteen shillings a 
Month. He had now acquired a low Obsequious awkward Bow, and 
a talent of gross flattery both in and out of season; he 
would shake the Butler by the Hand; He taught the Page his 
Catechism, and was sometimes admitted to Dine at the 
Stewards Table. In short he got the good Word of the whole 
Family, and was Recommended by my Lady for Chaplain to some 
other Noble House, by which his Revenue (beside Vales) 
amounted to about 30 l. a Year. His Sister procured him a 
Scarf from my Lord (who had a small design of Gallantry upon 
her) And by his Lordships Sollicitation he got a Lectureship 
in Town of 60 l. a Year; where he Preached constantly in 
Person, in a grave manner, with an Audible Voice, a Style 
Ecclesiastick, and the matter (such as it was) well suited 
to the intellectuals of his Hearers. Some time after, a 
Country Living fell in my Lord's Disposal, and his Lordship 
who had now some encouragement given him of Success in his 
Amour, bestowed the Living on Corusodes, who still kept his 
Lectureship and Residence in Town, where he was a constant 
Attendant at all Meetings relating to Charity, without ever 
contributing further than his frequent Pious Exhortations. 
If any Women of better fashion in the Parish happened to be 
absent from Church, they were sure of a Visit from him in a 
Day or two, to Chide and to Dine with them. </p>
            <p>He had a select number of Poor constantly attending at 
the Street Door of his Lodgings, for whom he was a common 
Sollicitor to his former Patroness, dropping in his own Half 
Crown among the Collections and taking it out when he 
disposed the money. At a Person of Qualities House, he would 
never sit down till he was thrice bid, and then upon the 
corner of the most distant chair. His whole demeanor was 
formal and starched, which adhered so close, that he could 
never shake it off in his highest Promotion. </p>
            <p>His Lord was now in high Employment at Court, and 
attended by him with the most abject Assiduity, and his 
Sister being gone off with Child to a private Lodging, my 
Lord continued his Graces to Corusodes, got him to be a 
Chaplain in ordinary, and in due time a Parish in Town, and 
a Dignity in the Church. </p>
            <p>He paid his Curates punctually, at the lowest Sallery, 
and partly out of the communion money, but gave them good 
advice in abundance. He Marryed a Citizens Widow, who taught 
him to put out small sums at ten per cent, and brought him 
acquainted with Jobbers in Change-Alley. By her dexterity he 
sold the Clarkship of his Parish, when it became vacant. </p>
            <p>He kept a miserable house, but the Blame was layed wholly 
upon Madam; For the good Doctor was always at his Books, or 
visiting the Sick, or doing other Offices of Charity and 
piety in his Parish. </p>
            <p>He treated all his inferiors of the Clergy with a most 
sanctifyed pride; was rigorously and universally, censorious 
upon all his brethren of the Gown, on their first appearance 
in the world, or while they continued meanly preferred; But 
gave large allowance to the Layity of high rank, or great 
riches, using neither Eyes nor Ears for their faults. He was 
never sensible of the least corruption in Courts, 
Parliaments, or Ministries, but made the most favourable 
constructions of all publick proceedings; and Power, in 
whatever Hands, or whatever Party, was always secure of his 
most charitable opinion.  He had many wholsome maxims ready 
to excuse all miscarriages of State. Men are but Men. Erunt 
vitia donec homines; and Quod Supra nos nihil ad nos. with 
several others of equal weight. </p>
            <p>It would lengthen my paper beyond measure to trace out 
the whole System of his conduct: His dreadfull apprehensions 
of Popery; his great moderation towards Dissenters of all 
Denominations; with hearty wishes that by yielding somewhat 
on both sides, there might be a general Union among 
Protestants; his short inoffensive Sermons in his turns at 
Court, and the matter exactly suited to the present juncture 
of prevailing Opinions. The arts he used to obtain a Mitre, 
by writing against Episcopacy, and the proofs he gave of his 
loyalty by palliating or defending the murder of a martyred 
Prince. </p>
            <p>Endowed with all these accomplishments we leave him in 
the full Carrier of Success, mounting fast towards the top 
of the Ladder Ecclesiastical, which he hath a fair 
probability to reach, without the merit of one single 
Virtue, moderately stocked with the least valuable parts of 
Erudition, utterly devoyd of all Taste, Judgment or Genius; 
and in his grandeur naturally chusing to hawl up others 
after him, whose accomplishments most resemble his own, 
except his beloved Sons, Nephews, or other kindred be not in 
competition, or lastly except his inclinations be diverted 
by those who have power to mortify or further advance him. </p>
            <p>Eugenio Set out from the same University, and about the 
same time with Corusodes; He had the reputation of an arch 
Lad at School, and was unfortunately possessed with a Talent 
for Poetry, on which account he received many chiding 
Letters from his Father, and grave advice from his Tutor. He 
did not neglect his College Learning, but his chief Study 
was the Authors of Antiquity, with a perfect knowledge in 
the Greek and Roman Tongues; He could never Procure himself 
to be chosen Fellow; for it was objected against him that he 
had written Verses, and particularly some wherein he glanced 
at a certain Reverend Doctor, famous for Dullness: That he 
had been seen bowing to Ladies, as he met them in the 
Streets; And it was proved that once he had been found 
dancing in a private family with half a dozen of both Sexes. </p>
            <p>He was the younger Son to a Gentleman of a good birth, 
but small fortune, and his Father Dying he was driven to 
London, to seek his fortune: he got into Orders, and became 
Reader in a Parish Church at twenty Pounds a Year; was 
carryed by an Oxford friend to Wills Coffee-house, 
frequented in those Days by the Men of Wit; where in some 
time he had the bad luck to be distinguished. His Scanty 
Sallery compelled him to run deep in debt for a new Gown and 
Cassock, and now and then forced him to Write some Paper of 
Wit or humour, or Preach a Sermon for Ten shillings, to 
supply his Necessities. He was a thousand times recommended 
by his Poetical Friends to great Persons, as a young man of 
excellent parts, who deserved encouragement and received a 
thousand Promises; But his modesty, and a generous spirit 
which disdained the Slavery of continual application, and 
attendance, always disappointed him, making room for 
Vigilant Dunces, who were sure to be never out of sight. </p>
            <p>He had an excellent faculty in preaching, if he were not 
sometimes a little too refined, and apt to trust too much to 
his own way of thinking, and reasoning. </p>
            <p>When upon the vacancy of Preferment he was hardly drawn 
to attend upon some promising Lord he received the usual 
Answer, that he came too late, for it had been given to 
another the very day before. And he had onely this comfort 
left, that every body said, it was a thousand pities some 
thing could not be done for Poor Mr. Eugenio. </p>
            <p>The Remainder of his Story will be dispatched in a few 
Words. Wearied with weak hopes, and weaker pursuits he 
accepted a Curacy in Darby-Shire, of thirty Pounds a Year, 
and when he was five and forty, had the great felicity to be 
preferred by a friend of his Father to a Vicaridge worth 
annually 60 pound, in the most desert parts of Lincolnshire, 
where his spirit quite sunk with those reflections, that 
solitude and disappointments bring, he married a Farmers 
widow, and is still alive, utterly undistinguished and 
forgotten, onely some of the Neighbours have accidentally 
heard that he had been a notable man in his Youth.    </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="VIII" type="article">
            <head>Article VIII</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">Par coeatque pari.  </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HAVING lately had an Account, that a certain Person of 
some Distinction swore in a publick Coffee-house, that Party 
should never Dye while he lived (although it has been the 
Endeavour of the best and wisest among us, to Abolish the 
Ridiculous Appellations of Whig and Tory, and entirely to 
turn our thoughts to the good of our Prince and Constitution 
in Church and State) I hope those, who are well-wishers to 
our Country, will think my Labour not ill bestowed in giving 
this Gentleman's Principles the proper Embellishments which 
they deserve, and since mad Mullinix is the only Tory now 
remaining, who dares own himself to be so, I desire I may 
not be Censured by those who are of his Party, for making 
him hold a Dialogue with one of less Consequence on 'tother 
side.  I shall not venture so far, as to give the Christian 
Nick-name of the Person chiefly concerned, lest I should 
give offence, for which reason, I shall call him Timothy, 
and leave the rest to the Conjecture of the World.  </p>
            <p>MAD MULLINIX and TIMOTHY.  </p>
            <l>M. I Own 'tis not my Bread and Butter, </l>
            <l>But prithee Tim, why all this Clutter? </l>
            <l>Why ever in these raging Fits, </l>
            <l>Damning to Hell the Jacobits? </l>
            <l n="5">When, if you search the Kingdom round, </l>
            <l>There's hardly twenty to be found; </l>
            <l>No, not among the Priests and Fryers. </l>
            <l>  T.  'Twixt you and me G---- Damn the Lyers. </l>
            <l>  M.  The Tories are gone ev'ry Man over </l>
            <l n="10">To our Illustrious House of Hanover. </l>
            <l>From all their Conduct this is plain, </l>
            <l>And then--  T. G---- Damn the Lyars again. </l>
            <l>Did not an Earl but lately Vote </l>
            <l>To bring in (I could Cut his Throat) </l>
            <l n="15">Our whole Accounts of publick Debts? </l>
            <l>  M.  Lord, how this Frothy Coxcomb frets! (aside) </l>
            <l>  T.  Did not an able Statesman </l>
            <l>This dang'rous horrid motion Dish up? </l>
            <l>As Popish Craft?  Did he not rail on't? </l>
            <l n="20">Shew Fire and Faggot in the Tail on't? </l>
            <l>Proving the Earl a grand Offender, </l>
            <l>And in a Plot for the Pretender? </l>
            <l>Whose Fleet, 'tis all our Friends Opinion, </l>
            <l>Was then embarking at Avignion. </l>
            <l n="25">  M.  In every A---- you run your Snout </l>
            <l>To find this Damn'd Pretender out, </l>
            <l>While all the silly Wretch can do </l>
            <l>Is but to frisk about like you. </l>
            <l>But Tim Convinc't by your Perswasion, </l>
            <l n="30">I yield there might be an Invasion, </l>
            <l>And you who ever F---- in vain, </l>
            <l>Can F---- his Navy back again. </l>
            <l>  T.  Z----ds Sir.  M.  But to be short and serious; </l>
            <l>For long disputes will only weary us. </l>
            <l n="35">These brangling jars of Whig and Tory, </l>
            <l>Are Stale, and Worn as Troy-Town Story. </l>
            <l>The Wrong, 'tis certain, you were both in, </l>
            <l>And now you find you fought for nothing. </l>
            <l>Your Faction, when their Game was new, </l>
            <l n="40">Might want such noisy Fools as you; </l>
            <l>But you when all the Show is past </l>
            <l>Resolve to stand it out the last; </l>
            <l>Like Martin Marrall, gaping on, </l>
            <l>Not minding when the Song was done. </l>
            <l n="45">When all the Bees are gone to settle, </l>
            <l>You Clatter still your Brazen Kettle. </l>
            <l>The Leaders whom you listed under, </l>
            <l>Have dropt their Arms, and seiz'd the Plunder. </l>
            <l>And when the War is past, you come </l>
            <l n="50">To rattle in their Ears your Drum. </l>
            <l>And, as that hateful hideous Grecian </l>
            <l>Thersites (he was your Relation) </l>
            <l>Was more abhor'd, and scorn'd by those </l>
            <l>With whom he serv'd, than by his Foes, </l>
            <l n="55">So thou art grown the Detestation </l>
            <l>Of all thy Party through the Nation. </l>
            <l>Thy peevish and perpetual teizing, </l>
            <l>With Plots, and Jacobites and Treason; </l>
            <l>Thy busy, never-meaning Face; </l>
            <l n="60">Thy Screw'd up front; thy State Grimace; </l>
            <l>Thy formal Nods; important Sneres; </l>
            <l>Thy Whisp'rings foisted in all Ears; </l>
            <l>(Which are, whatever you may think, </l>
            <l>But Nonsence wrapt up in a Stink) </l>
            <l n="65">Have made thy Presence, in a true Sence, </l>
            <l>To thy own Side so Damn'd a Nuisance, </l>
            <l>That when they have you in their Eye, </l>
            <l>As if the Devil drove, they fly. </l>
            <l>  T.  My good Friend Mullinix, forbear. </l>
            <l n="70">I vow to G---- you're too severe. </l>
            <l>If it could ever yet be known </l>
            <l>I took Advice except my own, </l>
            <l>It shou'd be yours.  But D---- my Blood, </l>
            <l>I must pursue the publick Good. </l>
            <l n="75">The Faction, (is it not Notorious?) </l>
            <l>Keck at the Memory of Glorious. </l>
            <l>'Tis true, nor need I to be told, </l>
            <l>My quondam Friends are grown so Cold, </l>
            <l>That scarce a Creature can be found, </l>
            <l n="80">To Prance with me the Statue round. </l>
            <l>The publick Safety, I foresee, </l>
            <l>Henceforth depends alone on me. </l>
            <l>And while this Vital Breath I blow, </l>
            <l>Or from above, or from below, </l>
            <l n="85">I'll Sputter, Swagger, Curse and Rail, </l>
            <l>The Tories Terror, Scourge and Flail. </l>
            <l>  M.  Tim, you mistake the matter quite, </l>
            <l>The Tories! you are their Delight. </l>
            <l>And should you act a diff'rent Part, </l>
            <l n="90">Be grave and wise, 'twou'd break their Heart. </l>
            <l>Why, Tim, you have a Taste I know, </l>
            <l>And often see a Puppet-show. </l>
            <l>Observe, the Audience is in Pain, </l>
            <l>While Punch is hid behind the Scene, </l>
            <l n="95">But when they hear his rusty Voice, </l>
            <l>With what Impatience they rejoice. </l>
            <l>And then they value not two Straws, </l>
            <l>How Solomon decides the Cause, </l>
            <l>Which the true Mother, which Pretender, </l>
            <l n="100">Nor listen to the Witch of Endor; </l>
            <l>Shou'd Faustus, with the Devil behind him, </l>
            <l>Enter the Stage they never mind him; </l>
            <l>If Punch, to spur their fancy, shews </l>
            <l>In at the door his monstrous Nose, </l>
            <l n="105">Then sudden draws it back again, </l>
            <l>O what a pleasure mixt with pain! </l>
            <l>You ev'ry moment think an Age, </l>
            <l>Till he appears upon the Stage. </l>
            <l>And first his Bum you see him clap </l>
            <l n="110">Upon the Queen of Sheba's lap. </l>
            <l>The Duke of Lorrain drew his Sword, </l>
            <l>Punch roaring ran, and running roar'd. </l>
            <l>Reviles all People in his Jargon, </l>
            <l>And sells the King of Spain a Bargain. </l>
            <l n="115">St. George himself he plays the wag on, </l>
            <l>And mounts astride upon the Dragon. </l>
            <l>He gets a thousand Thumps and Kicks, </l>
            <l>Yet cannot leave his roguish Tricks; </l>
            <l>In every Action thrusts his Nose, </l>
            <l n="120">The reason why, no Mortal knows. </l>
            <l>In doleful Scenes, that break our heart, </l>
            <l>Punch comes, like you, and lets a F----t. </l>
            <l>There's not a Puppet made of Wood; </l>
            <l>But what wou'd hang him if they cou'd. </l>
            <l n="125">While teizing all, by all he's teiz'd, </l>
            <l>How well are the Spectators pleas'd! </l>
            <l>Who in the motion have no share; </l>
            <l>But purely come to hear, and stare; </l>
            <l>Have no concern for Sabra's sake, </l>
            <l n="130">Which gets the better, Saint, or Snake. </l>
            <l>Provided Punch (for there's the Jest) </l>
            <l>Be soundly mawl'd, and plagues the rest. </l>
            <l>  Thus Tim, Philosophers suppose, </l>
            <l>The World consists of Puppet-shows; </l>
            <l n="135">Where petulant, conceited Fellows </l>
            <l>Perform the part of Punchinelloes; </l>
            <l>So at this Booth, which we call Dublin, </l>
            <l>Tim thour't the Punch to stir up trouble in; </l>
            <l>You Wrigle, Fidge, and make a Rout, </l>
            <l n="140">Put all your Brother Puppets out, </l>
            <l>Run on in a perpetual Round, </l>
            <l>To Teize, Perplex, Disturb, Confound, </l>
            <l>Intrude with Monkey grin, and clatter, </l>
            <l>To interrupt all serious Matter, </l>
            <l n="145">Are grown the Nuissance of your Clan, </l>
            <l>Who hate and scorn you, to a Man; </l>
            <l>But then the Lookers on, the Tories </l>
            <l>You still divert with merry Stories; </l>
            <l>They wou'd Consent, that all the Crew </l>
            <l n="150">Were hanged, before they'd part with you. </l>
            <l>  But tell me, Tim, upon the spot, </l>
            <l>By all this Coyl what hast thou got? </l>
            <l>If Tories must have all the sport, </l>
            <l>I fear you'll be disgrac'd at Court. </l>
            <l n="155">  T. Got? D---- my Blood I frank my Letters, </l>
            <l>Walk by my place, before my Betters, </l>
            <l>And simple as I now stand here, </l>
            <l>Expect in time to be a P---- </l>
            <l>Got? D---- me, why I got my will! </l>
            <l n="160">Ne're hold my peace, and ne'er stand still. </l>
            <l>I F----t with twenty Ladies by; </l>
            <l>They call me Beast, and what Care I? </l>
            <l>I bravely call the Tories Jacks, </l>
            <l>And Sons of Whores--behind their Backs. </l>
            <l n="165">But cou'd you bring me once to think, </l>
            <l>That when I strut, and stare, and stink, </l>
            <l>Revile, and slander, fume and storm, </l>
            <l>Betray, make Oath, impeach, inform, </l>
            <l>With such a constant, Loyal Zeal, </l>
            <l n="170">To serve my self, and Common-weal, </l>
            <l>And fret the Tories Souls to Death, </l>
            <l>I did but lose my precious Breath, </l>
            <l>And when I damn my Soul to plague 'em, </l>
            <l>Am, as you tell me, but their may-game, </l>
            <l n="175">Consume my Vitals! they shall know, </l>
            <l>I am not to be treated so; </l>
            <l>I'd rather hang my self by half, </l>
            <l>Than give those Rascals cause to laugh. </l>
            <l>  But how, my Friend, can I endure </l>
            <l n="180">Once so renown'd to Live obscure? </l>
            <l>No little Boys and Girls to cry </l>
            <l>There's Nimble Tim a passing by. </l>
            <l>No more my dear Delightful way tread, </l>
            <l>Of keeping up a party hatred. </l>
            <l n="185">Will none the Tory Dogs pursue, </l>
            <l>When thro' the streets I cry holloo? </l>
            <l>Must all my D--mee's, Bl--s and W--ds </l>
            <l>Pass only now for empty sounds? </l>
            <l>Shall Tory Rascals be Elected, </l>
            <l n="190">Although I swear them Disaffected? </l>
            <l>And when I roar a Plot, a Plot, </l>
            <l>Will our own Party mind me not? </l>
            <l>So qualify'd to Swear and Lye, </l>
            <l>Will they not trust me for a Spy? </l>
            <l n="195">Dear Mullinix, your good Advice </l>
            <l>I beg, you see the Case is nice. </l>
            <l>O, were I equal in Renown, </l>
            <l>Like thee, to please this thankless Town! </l>
            <l>Or blest with such engaging Parts, </l>
            <l n="200">To win the Truant School-Boys Hearts! </l>
            <l>Thy Vertues meet their just Reward, </l>
            <l>Attended by the Sable-guard, </l>
            <l>Charm'd by thy voice the 'Prentice drops </l>
            <l>The Snow-ball destin'd at thy Chops; </l>
            <l n="205">Thy graceful Steps, and Coll'nell's Air </l>
            <l>Allure the Cinder-picking Fair. </l>
            <l>  M.  No more--In mark of true Affection </l>
            <l>I take thee under my Protection. </l>
            <l>Your Parts are good, 'tis not deny'd, </l>
            <l n="210">I wish they had been well apply'd. </l>
            <l>But now observe my Counsel (viz) </l>
            <l>Adapt your Habit to your Phiz. </l>
            <l>You must no longer thus equip 'ye </l>
            <l>As Horace says, Optat ephippia. </l>
            <l n="215">There's Latin too that you may see </l>
            <l>How I improv'd by Dr. ---- </l>
            <l>I have a Coat at home, that you may try, </l>
            <l>'Tis just like this, which hangs by Geometry. </l>
            <l>My Hat has much the nicer air, </l>
            <l n="220">Your Block will fit it to a hair. </l>
            <l>That Wig, I wou'd not for the world </l>
            <l>Have it so formal, and so Curl'd, </l>
            <l>'Twill be so oyly, and so sleek </l>
            <l>When I have lain in it a Week! </l>
            <l n="225">You'll find it well prepar'd to take </l>
            <l>The figure of Toope and Snake. </l>
            <l>Thus drest alike from Top to Toe, </l>
            <l>That which is which, 'tis hard to know. </l>
            <l>When first in publick we appear, </l>
            <l n="230">I'll lead the Van, keep you the Rear. </l>
            <l>Be careful, as you walk behind, </l>
            <l>Use all the Talents of your mind. </l>
            <l>Be studious well to imitate </l>
            <l>My portly Motion, Mien, and Gate. </l>
            <l n="235">Mark my Address, and learn my Style, </l>
            <l>When to look Scornful, when to Smile, </l>
            <l>Nor sputter out your Oaths so fast, </l>
            <l>But keep your Swearing to the last. </l>
            <l>Then at our leisure we'll be witty, </l>
            <l n="240">And in the Streets divert the City: </l>
            <l>The Ladies from the Windows gaping, </l>
            <l>The Children all our motions Aping. </l>
            <l>Your Conversation to refine, </l>
            <l>I'll take you to some Friends of mine; </l>
            <l n="245">Choice Spirits, who employ their Parts, </l>
            <l>To mend the World by useful Arts. </l>
            <l>Some cleansing hollow Tubes, to spy </l>
            <l>Direct the Zenith of the Sky; </l>
            <l>Some have the City in their Care, </l>
            <l n="250">From noxious Steams to purge the Air; </l>
            <l>Some teach us in these dang'rous Days, </l>
            <l>How to walk upright in our ways; </l>
            <l>Some whose reforming Hands engage, </l>
            <l>To lash the Lewdness of the Age; </l>
            <l n="255">Some, for the publick Service go, </l>
            <l>Perpetual Envoys to and fro; </l>
            <l>Whose able Heads support the Weight, </l>
            <l>Of twenty M----rs of State. </l>
            <l>We scorn, for want of talk, to jabber </l>
            <l n="260">Of Parties o're our Bonny-Clabber. </l>
            <l>Nor are we studious to enquire, </l>
            <l>Who votes for Manners, who for Hire. </l>
            <l>Our Care is to improve the mind, </l>
            <l>With what concerns all human kind; </l>
            <l n="265">The various Scenes of mortal Life, </l>
            <l>Who beats her Husband, who his Wife; </l>
            <l>Or how the Bulley at a stroke </l>
            <l>Knockt down the Boy, the Lanthorn broke; </l>
            <l>One tells the Rise of Cheese, and Oat-meal, </l>
            <l n="270">Another when he got a hot Meal; </l>
            <l>One gives Advice in Proverbs Old, </l>
            <l>Instructs us how to tame a Scold; </l>
            <l>One shows how bravely Audoin Dy'd, </l>
            <l>And at the Gallows all deny'd; </l>
            <l n="275">How by the Almanack 'tis clear, </l>
            <l>That Herrings will be cheap this Year. </l>
            <l>  T.  Dear Mullinix, I now lament </l>
            <l>My precious Time, so long mispent, </l>
            <l>By nature meant for nobler Ends, </l>
            <l n="280">O, introduce me to your Friends! </l>
            <l>For whom, by Birth, I was design'd, </l>
            <l>'Till Politicks debas'd my mind. </l>
            <l>I give my self intire to you, </l>
            <l>G---- d---- the Whigs and Tories too.    </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="IX" type="article">
            <head>Article IX</head>
            <p>FROM frequently reflecting upon the Course and Method of 
Educating Youth in this and a Neighbouring Kingdom, with the 
general Success and consequence thereof; I am come to this 
Determination, That Education is always the worse in 
Proportion to the Wealth and Grandeur of the Parents. Nor do 
I doubt in the least, that if the whole World were now under 
the Dominion of one Monarch (provided I might be allowed to 
chuse where he should fix the Seat of his Empire) the only 
Son and Heir of that Monarch, would be the worst Educated 
Mortal, that ever was born since the Creation: And, I doubt 
the same Proportion will hold through all Degrees and 
Titles, from an Emperor downwards, to the common Gentry. I 
do not say that this hath been always the case: for in 
better times it was directly otherwise; and a Scholar may 
fill half his Greek and Roman Shelves with Authors of the 
Noblest Birth, as well as highest Virtue. Nor, do I tax all 
Nations at present with this defect, for I know there are 
some to be excepted, and particularly Scotland, under all 
the Disadvantages of it's Clymate and Soyle, if that 
happiness be not rather owing even to those very dis-
advantages. What is then to be done, if this Reflection must 
fix on two Countries, which will be most ready to take 
Offence, and which of all others it will be least prudent or 
safe to offend? </p>
            <p>But there is one Circumstance yet more Dangerous and 
Lamentable. For if, according to the Postulatum already laid 
down, the higher Quality any Youth is of, he is in greater 
likelyhood to be worse Educated, it behooves me to dread, 
and keep far from the Verge of Scandalum Magnatum. </p>
            <p>Retracting therefore that hazardous Postulatum, I shall 
venture no further at present than to say, that perhaps some 
Additional Care in Educating the Sons of Nobility, and 
principal Gentry, might not be ill employed. If this be not 
delivered with softness enough, I must for the future be 
Silent. </p>
            <p>In the mean time, let me ask only two Questions, which 
relate to a Neighbouring Kingdom, from whence the Chief 
among us are descended, and whose manners we most affect to 
follow. I ask first, how it comes about, that for above 60 
Years past, the Chief Conduct of Affairs in that Kingdom 
hath been generally placed in the Hands of New-men, with 
very few Exceptions. The Noblest Blood of England having 
been shed in the grand Rebellion, many great Families became 
extinct, or supported only by Minors: when the King was 
Restored, very few of those Lords remained, who began, or at 
least had improved their Education, under the happy Reign of 
King James, or King Charles I, of which Lords the two 
principal were the Marquiss of Ormonde, and the Earl of 
Southampton. The Minors had, during the Rebellion and 
Usurpation, either received too much Tincture of bad 
Principles from those Fanatick Times, or coming to Age at 
the Restoration, fell into the Vices of that dissolute 
Reign. </p>
            <p>I Date from this [AElig ]ra, the Corrupt Method of Education 
among us, and the consequence thereof, in the Necessity the 
Crown lay under of Introducing New-men into the chief 
Conduct of publick Affairs, or to the Office of what we now 
call Prime Ministers, Men of Art, Knowledge, Application, 
and Insinuation, meerly for want of a supply among the 
Nobility. They were generally (though not always) of good 
Birth, sometimes Younger Brothers, at other times, such who 
although inheriting good Estates, yet happened to be well 
Educated, and provided with Learning; such under that King, 
were Hyde, Bridgman, Clifford, Coventry, Osborn, Godolphin, 
Ashley-Cooper; Few or none under the short Reign of King 
James II. Under King William; Summers, Montague, Churchil, 
Vernon, Harry Boyle, and many others: Under the Queen; 
Harley, St. John, Harcourt, Trevers, who indeed were Persons 
of the best private Families, but unadorn'd with Titles. So 
in the last Reign, Mr. Robert Walpole, was understood for 
many Years, to be Prime Minister, in which Post he still 
happily continues; His Brother Horace is Ambassador 
Extraordinary to France. Mr. Addison, and Mr. Craiggs, 
without the least Allyance to support them, have been 
Secretaries of State. </p>
            <p>If the Facts have been thus for above 60 years past 
(whereof I could with a little further Recollection produce 
many more Instances) I would ask again, how it hath 
happened, that in a Nation plentifully abounding with 
Nobility, so great share in the most important parts of 
publick management, hath been for so long a Period chiefly 
entrusted to Commonners; unless some Omissions, or Defects 
of the highest Import, may be charged upon those to whom the 
care of Educating our Noble Youth hath been committed. For, 
if there be any difference between human Creatures in the 
point of natural Parts, as we usually call them, it should 
seem, that the Advantage lyes on the side of Children born 
from Noble and Wealthy Parents; the same Traditional Sloth 
and Luxury which render their Body Weak and Effeminate, 
perhaps refining and giving a freer motion to the Spirits, 
beyond what can be expected from the gross robust Issue of 
meaner Mortals. Add to this, the peculiar Advantages, which 
all young Noblemen possess, by the Priviledges of their 
Birth; Such as a free access to Courts, and a universal 
Deference pay'd to their Persons. </p>
            <p>But as my Lord Bacon chargeth it for a fault on Princes, 
that they are impatient to compass Ends without giving 
themselves the trouble of consulting or executing the means. 
So perhaps it may be the disposition of young Nobles, either 
from the Indulgence of Parents, Tutors and Governors, or 
their own Inactivity, that they expect the accomplishments 
of a good Education without the least expence of Time or 
Study, to acquire them. </p>
            <p>What I said last, I am ready to retract; For the case is 
infinitely worse; and the very Maxims set up to direct 
modern Education, are enough to destroy all the Seeds of 
Knowledge, Honour, Wisdom, and Virtue among us. The current 
Opinion prevails that the study of Greek and Latin is loss 
of Time; that publick Schools by mingling the Sons of 
Noblemen, with those of the Vulgar, engage the former in bad 
Company; That whipping breaks the Spirits of Lads well Born; 
That Universities make young Men Pedants. That, to Dance, 
Fence, speak French, and know how to behave your self among 
great Persons of both Sexes, comprehends the whole duty of a 
Gentleman. </p>
            <p>I cannot but think this wise System of Education, hath 
been much cultivated among us by those Worthies of the Army, 
who during the last War returning from Flanders at the close 
of each Campaign, became the Dictators of Behaviour, Dress 
and Politeness to all those Youngsters, who frequent 
Chocolate-Coffee-Gaming-Houses, Drawing-Rooms, Opera's, 
Levees, and Assemblies; where a Colonel by his Pay, 
Perquisites, and Plunder, was qualifyed to outshine many 
Peers of the Realm; and by the influence of an exotick Habit 
and Demeanor, added to other foreign Accomplishments, gave 
the Law to the whole Town, and were copyed as the Standard-
Patterns of whatever was refined in Dress, Equipage, 
Conversation, or Diversions. </p>
            <p>I remember in those Times, an Admired Original of that 
Vocation, sitting in a Coffee-house near two Gentlemen, 
whereof one was of the Clergy, who were engaged in some 
discourse that savoured of Learning; This Officer thought 
fit to interpose, and professing to deliver the Sentiments 
of his Fraternity as well as his own (and probably did so of 
too many among them) turning to the Clergyman, spoke in the 
following manner. D--n me, Doctor, say what you will, the 
Army is the only School for Gentlemen. Do you think my Lord 
Marlborough beat the French, with Greek and Latin. D--n me, 
a Scholar when he comes into good Company; what is he but an 
Ass? D--n me, I would be glad by G--d to see any of your 
Schollars with his Nouns, and his Verbs, and his Philosophy, 
and Trigonometry, what a figure he would make at a Siege or 
Blockado or reconoitring -- D--n me &amp;c. After which he 
proceeded with a Volley of Military Terms, less significant, 
sounding worse, and harder to be understood than any that 
were ever Coyned by the Commentators upon Aristotle. I would 
not here be thought to charge the Soldiery with Ignorance 
and contempt of Learning, without allowing Exceptions, of 
which I have known many, and some even in this Kingdom, but 
however, the worse example, especially in a great Majority 
will certainly prevail. </p>
            <p>I have heard that the late Earl of Oxford in the time of 
his Ministry, never past by White's Chocolate-house (the 
common Rendezvous of infamous Sharpers, and noble Cullies) 
without bestowing a Curse upon that famous Accademy, as the 
Bane of half the English Nobility. I have been likewise told 
another passage concerning that great Minister; which 
because it gives a humorous Idea of one principal Ingredient 
in modern Education, take as followeth. Le-Sac the Famous 
French Dancing-master in great Admiration asked a friend, 
whether it were true that Mr. Harley was made an Earl, and 
Lord Treasurer: And finding it confirmed, said; Well, I 
wonder what the Devil the Queen could see in him; for I 
attended him two Years, and he was the greatest Dunce that 
ever I taught. </p>
            <p>Another hindrance to good Education, and I think, the 
greatest of any, is that pernicious custom in Rich and Noble 
Families, of entertaining French Tutors in their Houses. 
These wretched Pædagogues are enjoyned by the Father, to 
take special care, that the Boy shall be perfect in his 
French; By the Mother, that Master must not walk till he is 
hot, nor be suffered to play with other Boys, nor be wet in 
his Feet, nor daub his Cloaths, and to see that the 
Dancing-master attends constantly, and does his Duty: she 
further insists that the Child be not kept too long poring 
on his Book, because he is subject to sore Eyes, and of a 
weakly Constitution. </p>
            <p>By these methods the young Gentleman is in every Article 
as fully accomplished at 8 Years old as at eight and twenty 
(Age adding only to the growth of his Person and his Vice) 
so that if you should look at him in his Boyhood through the 
magnifying end of a Perspective, and in his Manhood through 
the other, it would be impossible to spy any difference: The 
same Airs, the same Strutt, the same Cock of his Hat, and 
posture of his Sword (as far as the change of fashions will 
allow) the same understanding, the same compass of 
knowledge, with the very same Absurdity, Impudence, and 
Impertinence of Tongue. </p>
            <p>He is taught from the Nursery that he must inherit a 
great Estate, and hath no need to mind his Book, which is a 
Lesson he never forgets to the end of his life. His chief 
Solace is to steal down and play at Span-farthing with the 
Page, or young Black-a-moor, or little favorite Foot-boy, 
one of which is his principal Confident, and Bosom-friend. </p>
            <p>There is one young Lord in this Town, who by an 
unexampled piece of good Fortune, was miraculously snatched 
out of the Gulph of Ignorance, confined to a publick School 
for a due Term of Years, well Whipped when he deserved it; 
clad no better than his Comrades, and always their Play-
fellow on the same foot, had no Precedence in the School, 
but what was given him by his Merit, and lost it whenever he 
was Negligent. It is well known how many Mutinies were bred 
at this unpresidented Treatment, what complaints among his 
Relations, and other Great ones of both Sexes; that his 
Stockings with silver Clocks were ravished from him, that he 
wore his own Hair, that his dress was undistinguished; that 
he was not fit to appear at a Ball or Assembly, nor suffered 
to go to either. And it was with the utmost difficulty that 
he became qualifyed for his present removal, where he may 
probably be farther Persecuted, and possibly with Success, 
if the firmness of a very Worthy Governor, and his own good 
Dispositions will not preserve him. I confess, I cannot but 
wish he may go on in the way he began, because I have a 
curiosity to know by so singular an Experiment, whether 
Truth, Honour, Justice, Temperance, Courage and good Sense 
acquired by a School and College Education, may not produce 
a very tolerable Lad, although he should happen to fail in 
one or two of those accomplishments, which in the general 
Vogue, are held so important to the finishing of a 
Gentleman. </p>
            <p>It is true, I have known an Accademical Education to have 
been exploded in publick Assemblies; and have heard more 
than one or two Persons of high Rank, declare they could 
learn nothing more at Oxford and Cambridge, than to drink 
Ale and smoke Tobacco; wherein I firmly believ'd them, and 
could have added some hundred Examples from my own 
observation in one of those Universities, but they all were 
of young Heirs sent thither, only for form, either from 
Schools where they were not suffered by their careful 
Parents, to stay above three Months in the Year, or from 
under the management of French Family-Tutors, who yet often 
attended them to their College, to prevent all possibility 
of their Improvement. But, I never yet knew any one Person 
of Quality, who followed his Studies at the University, and 
carryed away his just Proportion of Learning, that was not 
ready upon all occasions to celebrate and defend that course 
of Education, and to prove a Patron of Learned Men. </p>
            <p>There is one circumstance in a learned Education, which 
ought to have much weight, even with those who have no 
Learning at all. The Books read at Schools and Colleges, are 
full of Incitements to Virtue, and Discouragements from 
Vice, drawn from the wisest Reasons, the strongest Motives, 
and the most influencing Examples. Thus, young Minds are 
filled early with an inclination to Good, and an abhorrence 
of Evil, both which encrease in them, according to the 
advances they make in Literature: And, although they may be, 
and too often are, drawn by the Temptations of Youth, and 
the Opportunities of a large Fortune, into some 
Irregularities, when they come forward into the great World, 
it is ever with Reluctance and Compunction of Mind, because 
their Byas to Virtue still continues. They may stray 
sometimes out of Infirmity or Complyance, but they will soon 
return to the right Rode, and keep it always in view. I 
speak only of those Excesses, which are too much the 
Attendants of Youth and warmer Blood; for, as to the Points 
of Honour, Truth, Justice, and other noble Gifts of the 
Mind, wherein the temperature of the Body hath no concern, 
they are seldom or never known to be misled. </p>
            <p>I have engaged my self very unwarily in too copious a 
Subject for so short a Paper. The present Scope I would aim 
at is to prove, that some Proportion of human Knowledge 
appears requisite to those, who by their Birth or Fortune, 
are called to the making of Laws, and in a subordinate way 
to the execution of them; and that such Knowledge is not to 
be obtained without a Miracle, under the frequent, corrupt, 
and sottish Methods, of educating those who are born to 
Wealth or Titles. For, I would have it remembred, that I do 
by no means confine these Remarks to young Persons of Noble 
Birth; the same Errors running through all Families, where 
there is Wealth enough to afford, that their Sons (at least 
the Eldest) may be good for nothing. Why should my Son be a 
Scholar, when it is not intended that he should live by his 
Learning? By this Rule, if what is commonly said be true, 
that Money answereth all Things, why should my Son be 
honest, temperate, just, or charitable, since he hath no 
intention to depend upon any of these Qualities for a 
Maintenance? </p>
            <p>When all is done, perhaps upon the whole, the matter is 
not so bad as I would make it; and, God, who worketh good 
out of evil, acting only by the ordinary Course and rule of 
Nature, permits this continual Circulation of human things, 
for his own unsearchable Ends. The Father grows rich by 
Avarice, Injustice, Oppression; he is a Tyrant in the 
Neighbourhood, over Slaves and Beggars, whom he calls his 
Tenants. Why should he desire to have qualities infused into 
his Son, which himself never possessed, or knew, or found 
the want of in the acquisition of his Wealth? The Son bred 
in Sloth and Idleness, becomes a Spendthrift, a Cully, a 
Profligate, and goes out of the World a Beggar, as his 
Father came in: Thus, the former is punished for his own 
Sins, as well as for those of the latter. The Dunghil having 
raised a huge Mushroom of short duration, is now spread to 
enrich other Mens Lands. It is indeed of worse consequence, 
where noble Families are gone to decay; because their Titles 
and Priviledges out-live their Estates: And, Politicians 
tell us, that nothing is more dangerous to the Publick, than 
a numerous Nobility without Merit or Fortune. But even here, 
God hath likewise prescribed some Remedy in the order of 
Nature; so many great Families coming to an end by the 
Sloth, Luxury, and abandoned Lusts, which enervated their 
Breed thorough every Succession, producing gradually a more 
effeminate Race, wholly unfit for Propagation.    </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="X" type="article">
            <head>Article X</head>
            <p>Magnas Componere lites.  </p>
            <p>Lucass's Coffee-house, July 4th.  </p>
            <p>Mr. Intelligencer,  </p>
            <p>I Am desired to return you the Thanks of this House, for 
that Seasonable Dialogue between Timothy and Mullinix. You 
have intirely reconciled them both by it, and thereby given 
the finishing stroke to a Party, which gives universal Joy 
and Satisfaction to all well-wishers of our Constitution.  
It was very much lamented, that Men of their extraordinary 
Talents, (and who might by their united Interest contribute 
very much to the good of our Country) should not have a 
better understanding between them; because the perpetual 
Feuds and Animosities which they raised, had like to have 
proved of the most fatal ill Consequence to this 
unfortunate, poor, divided Nation. Now the Clouds which hung 
over us, are dispelled; Things begin to clear up; and we 
have the best reason to think, by this Union, that we shall 
be a Great and a Flourishing People. We are now in a 
profound Peace, Trade flourishes.--Plenty, which fled from 
hence to Scotland, is returned.--You see Joy and Fatness in 
every Countenance, especially in those of the Natives.--The 
younger Sons of Gentlemen, who languished, loitering at 
Home, for want of Business, are now in a fair way of 
Employment. Arts and Sciences begin to revive in our 
University; that great Nursery of the best Education! which 
Annually supplies the Pulpit, Bench and Bar, and every other 
useful Office.  All our Nobility and Gentry, who fled to 
Great-Brittain, to avoid the Civil Broils occasioned by Tim 
Cæsar, and Mullinix Pompey, are now returning, to live 
quietly at Home, and to bring a Blessing to their Native 
Soil, by residing in it; which will be a means to keep our 
Money at Home; to encourage Agriculture, especially Tillage; 
and then, Sing O be Joyful, we shall all wallow in Wealth, 
because by this we shall have nine hundred thousand Pounds a 
Year more in this Nation. These and numberless Advantages 
beside, we owe to your excellent Paper, which Tim himself 
allows to be written with a very good Intention, although it 
places him in a ludicrous Light, but he is a Man of such 
excellent Taste and Temper, that a Jest, when it is finely 
Couched, never gives him the least Offence.  This encourages 
me to let you know, he is very angry at Mr. Gay; for he 
thinks the Fable of the Monkey which had seen the World is 
levelled at him.  If you have leisure to write something 
merry upon the occasion, let us have it immediately, and 
answer this Letter another time. For, you must know, we are 
very great Jokers in this Coffee-House.  There is a little 
dapper Lord, an Acquaintance of Tim's, will laugh and teize 
him into his Chair, and home again.  -  </p>
            <p>Tim and the Fables.  </p>
            <l>MY meaning will be best unravell'd, </l>
            <l>When I premise, that Tim has Travell'd. </l>
            <l>In Lucass's by chance there lay </l>
            <l>The Fables writ by Mr. Gay, </l>
            <l n="5">Tim set the Volume on a Table, </l>
            <l>Read over here and there a Fable, </l>
            <l>And found, as he the pages twirl'd, </l>
            <l>The Monkey, who had seen the World. </l>
            <l>(For Tonson had, to help the Sale, </l>
            <l n="10">Prefixt a Cut to ev'ry Tale.) </l>
            <l>The Monkey was compleatly drest, </l>
            <l>The Beau in all his Ayrs exprest. </l>
            <l>Tim with surprize and pleasure staring, </l>
            <l>Ran to the Glass, and then comparing </l>
            <l n="15">His own sweet Figure with the Print, </l>
            <l>Distinguish'd ev'ry Feature in't; </l>
            <l>The Twist, the Squeeze, the Rump, the Fidge an' all, </l>
            <l>Just as they lookt in the Original. </l>
            <l>By ---- says Tim (and let a F----t) </l>
            <l n="20">This Graver understood his Art. </l>
            <l>'Tis a true Copy, I'll say that for't, </l>
            <l>I well remember when I sat for't. </l>
            <l>My very Face, at first I knew it, </l>
            <l>Just in this dress the Painter drew it. </l>
            <l n="25">Tim, with his likeness deeply smitten, </l>
            <l>Wou'd read what underneath was written, </l>
            <l>The merry Tale with moral Grave. </l>
            <l>He now began to storm and rave; </l>
            <l>The cursed Villain! now I see </l>
            <l n="30">This was a Libel meant at me; </l>
            <l>These Scriblers grow so bold of late, </l>
            <l>Against us Ministers of State! </l>
            <l>Such Jacobites as he deserve,---- </l>
            <l>Dammee, I say, they ought to starve. </l>
            <l n="35">Dear Tim, no more such angry Speeches, </l>
            <l>Unbutton and let down your Breeches, </l>
            <l>Tare out the Tale, and wipe your A---- </l>
            <l>I know you love to act a Farce.    </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XI" type="article">
            <head>Article XI</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">--Ut dehinc Speciosa miracula promat.  Hor.   </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Mr. Intelligencer, </p>
            <p>HAVING but lately met with the following Proposals in a 
Letter to the Author of the London-Journal, bearing Date 
March 30th. 1728. And having the greatest Veneration and 
Esteem for the Writer of it, as well as the best Opinion of 
his vast Abilities for the Undertaking; I hope, I do not 
come too late, in giving a helping Hand to spread it abroad 
for the Author's Advantage, and Benefit of the Learned 
World, by giving it a Poetick Dress, which I think would 
have been much better from his own Pen, had he been in a 
humour of versifying; for he has the most extraordinary 
Talents that way of any Man now living, except A. P.  There 
is a turn and beauty of Language, as well as Thought, 
carry'd on with the greatest Perspicuity thro' the whole, 
much in the manner of Voiture.  This I own has been of 
singular Advantage to me; for the easiness and politeness of 
his Prose, contributed much to the smoothness and Musick of 
my Verses, purely owing to my Transferring as much of his 
Expression, as I possibly could, into my Performance.  From 
this elegant Specimen of his, the World will see what they 
are to expect from him; at least a vast deal of Orthodox 
Divinity, Critical Remarks, Solid Argument, wholesome 
Instruction, clear Information, with an entertaining beauty 
of Style, peculiar to the Great and Learned S---d---l---y.  
And now I have named him, I need say no more to recommend 
the Work but what follows.  </p>
            <l>	Your great Admirer and Well-wisher, </l>
            <l>					A. B.    </l>
            <p>Church-street, Soho, March 30, 1728.  </p>
            <p>To the Author of the LONDON JOURNAL.  </p>
            <p>SIR,  I have published the Specimen of a Book, entitled, 
An Universal View of all the eminent Writers on the Holy 
Scriptures; being a Collection of the Dissertations, 
Explications, and Opinions, of learned Men in all Ages, 
concerning the difficult Passages and obscure Texts of the 
Bible; and of whatsoever is to be met with in Profane 
Authors, which may contribute towards the better 
Understanding of Them. </p>
            <p>I beg the Favour of communicating to the World, by means 
of your Paper, what I think at present necessary to say, 
towards the unfolding my Design in this Work, and to answer 
the Objections which I have heard made against it. </p>
            <p>Most of the Articles whereof I treat, are, at one time or 
other, made the Subject of common Discourse; and too many 
Persons, who debate in private on these Points, are 
unfurnish'd with proper and rational Materials for such 
Conversation. </p>
            <p>These Observations occasion'd my forming a Design, to 
collect, into one View, the chief Sentiments of the best 
Authors, in most Languages, on those Subjects, for the 
Benefit only of common Discourse and Instruction: But when I 
came to reflect more closely on the Matter, I found, besides 
my obliging the Generality of Readers, and my enlarging the 
Fund of Scriptural Knowledge amongst the Unlearned, that I 
was in a fair way of doing Service to the Learned and more 
Intelligent Part of my Countrymen likewise; because, by 
means of this Work, they wou'd save abundance of Time, which 
is now lost, in turning over from Book to Book, and from 
Page to Page, the numberless Authors, which I shall quote.  
And if any of them are inclin'd to consult the Originals, I 
promise to refer them faithfully to the Line and Page; and I 
began further to conceive, that I should oblige many amongst 
the Learned, by saving them abundance of Cost and Expence in 
purchasing several Books, which it will be sufficient for 
them to see and hear of, in the Quotations of my View. </p>
            <p>The Reader is desir'd to observe, that there is no 
Bibliotheque, no Collection of this kind, so compleat, now 
extant, in any Language, as I shall shew in my general 
Preface to the Whole; and it must not be forgot, that the 
English want such a Collection, more than most other 
Christian Nations. </p>
            <p>All the Objections, which I have heard, will be answer'd 
by what follows; whereby those Persons, particularly, will 
find themselves mistaken, who imagine, that the Immensity of 
the Work ought both to terrifie them from encouraging, and 
me from undertaking it.  For I shall not go thro' the whole 
Bible Verse by Verse, as in the Specimen.  MOSES's first 
Chapter is an entire Piece, on the Creation, and I could not 
omit one Line of it; but my subsequent Articles will be 
taken from Books, Chapters and Verses, very distant often 
from one another: Nay, I shall leave whole Books of the 
Bible untouch'd, viz. such as are Moral or Poetical only, or 
meerly Historical; and I shall take Notice of no Parts of 
those Books, but such as are very Curious and Intricate, and 
have occasion'd something extraordinary to be said on them.  
Besides, it must be considered that I shall omit numberless 
Authors, on every Subject; and that, without any dread of 
displeasing, or hopes of pleasing any Sects or Parties of 
People; and I shall only collect from the most received 
Authors on every Article, and such as none shall except 
against for Learning or Abilities, whatever they may do for 
Opinion. </p>
            <p>The Sentiments of the Fathers and antient Commentators 
will be sufficiently answer'd for out of POOLE's Synopsis; 
for it wou'd be an endless, idle and dusty Work, to contract 
all their heavy and voluminous Writings; but whatever may be 
still thought wanting of these Antients, will be supplied 
even to Satiety, from PETAVIUS, CALMET, and others. Further, 
nothing could be so disagreeable either to me or to the 
Reader, as to give a full Detail of all the Stuff that was 
published Abroad about the Time of, and a long while after 
the Reformation; and it wou'd be more nauseous still to 
revive what was writ at Home, from the Beginning of the last 
Century till towards the End of it, and indeed for some part 
of the Century before it. </p>
            <p>But, God be thanked, there wanted not great Genius's, who 
wrote in several Places at the same Times; and if I raise 
the Work to Two large Vols. in Folio, with what the learned 
and bright Part of Mankind alone have left us, I may 
reasonably expect Forgiveness for not swelling my Labours 
into Four or more Folio's, by interspersing tedious 
Observations, and ridiculous, wild and low Expositions. </p>
            <p>I shall print the Two Vols. within a reasonable time 
after my Subscriptions come in; for I have my Additions and 
Amendments, that are to compleat the Specimen, ready and 
prepared: which Specimen being to be reprinted for the Body 
of the Work, will, together with what Collections I have by 
me for succeeding Articles, give me all imaginable Advantage 
of the Printer, who cannot work at the Press so fast as I 
can supply him with Copy; besides which I have procur'd the 
Assistance of some learned Persons to collect for me, and 
have got so diligent and expert an Amanuensis, to transcribe 
for the Press, that it can never stand still. </p>
            <p>I beg leave to remark, that besides the Benefit which 
every English Reader, of common Sense, will reap by this 
Undertaking, it will be of more special Service to young 
Divines, who may hereby at the same time procure variety of 
Learning, and indulge a studious Curiosity, at a small 
Expence; and who, by means of this Collection, will be 
sufficiently furnish'd with a Bibliotheca Sacra; to which, 
if they add only POOLE's English Annotations on the Old, and 
HAMMOND's Exposition of the New Testament, they will need 
few other Books for some Years, unless it be a Concordance 
to understand Scripture. </p>
            <p>As to those who object, that such a Variety of Opinions 
on one Subject, as I shall always produce, will rather 
confound than satisfy People, I beg leave to disagree with 
them: because every intelligent Person can judge for 
himself; and because those of meaner Capacities may consult 
others of better Understanding; every thing being laid 
before them in plain English. </p>
            <p>And, in Truth, I cannot but esteem such a Work, to be, in 
justice, due to the Inhabitants of our Islands.  Monsieur 
CALMET gives the following reason for publishing Nine 
Volumes in Folio, containing, not only, his own Comments, 
but Variety of Opinions, concerning the difficult Parts of 
the Bible, viz. that his Countrymen might, now, read in 
their own Language, what has hitherto been conceal'd from 
them in Hebrew, Greek, and Latin. </p>
            <p>A noble Attempt in a Papist! and his Work is so well 
executed, that I wish Encouragement were given to have it 
all translated into English. </p>
            <p>However, tho' CALMET's Religion, and the Laws of his 
Country, would not permit him to quote so freely as he 
ought; yet, thank God, we have that Liberty here; and, I 
hope, the use I make of it won't want Encouragement, since 
my Design is the same with CALMET's, viz. publick 
Information. </p>
            <p>His Religion, indeed, has no way to subsist, but by the 
Benefit of unknown Tongues; but the Truth of Holy Scripture, 
and of the Protestant Religion, want no learned Veils, or 
Foreign Couvertures. </p>
            <p>English Popery is much more abominable, than the Romish! </p>
            <p>I wou'd now have it remembred, that I shall produce 
nothing but what has been publish'd already in some Language 
or other; unless, perhaps, some private Piece, very new and 
extremely curious, should fall in my way.  And I would have 
those Persons who are too fearful of my encouraging 
Scepticism by these Books, believe, that I shall insert no 
Opinions which give Offence either to Natural, or Reveal'd 
Religion; my intent being to establish Truth, which can only 
be done by comparing different Sentiments on the same 
Subject. </p>
            <p>To let the Reader further into the Nature of my Design, I 
here present him with the Titles of my Articles, from the 
Creation, to the Deluge; by which he may form a Judgment of 
the rest.  </p>
            <l>1.  Of the Creation. </l>
            <l>2.  Of the Sabbath. </l>
            <l>3.  Of the Paradisaical State. </l>
            <l>4.  Of the Fall. </l>
            <l>5.  Of Sacrifice. </l>
            <l>6.  Of Cain and Enoch. </l>
            <l>7.  Of the Depravity of Men, before the Flood. </l>
            <l>8.  Of the Deluge.  </l>
            <p>I cannot make an End, without observing, that I shall 
neither oppose, nor interfere with the Proposals of Dr. 
INNES.  The Doctor's Work (as I am told) is wholly Moral; 
mine is wholly  Critical: He designs to make Men Better; my 
Aim is to make them Wiser. </p>
            <p>The Doctor resolves, (as I hear) to pass by what ever 
has, hitherto, been written in the Moral way, on the Bible, 
and to moralize anew on it himself.  I am in a quite 
different Train: I shall publish little or nothing of my 
own, nor shall I produce any one Author in the Doctor's way 
of Proceeding. </p>
            <l>		I am, SIR, </l>
            <l>		Your humble Servant, </l>
            <l>			JONATHAN SMEDLEY.   </l>
            <l>YOU that would read the Bible turn all </l>
            <l>To April 6 the London Journal, </l>
            <l>And by a Letter there you'll see </l>
            <l>How much the Text will owe to me. </l>
            <l n="5">Five thousand Years and more--'tis odd </l>
            <l>None cou'd explain the Word of GOD! </l>
            <l>Of all the Learned, in all Ages, </l>
            <l>Thro' all their long, laborious Pages, </l>
            <l>'Till I, the Top of IRISH DEANS, </l>
            <l n="10">Have made it out with Wond'rous pains. </l>
            <l>I've Read the Dev'l and all of Books, </l>
            <l>The World may Read 'em in my looks: </l>
            <l>Above ten Waggon load at least, </l>
            <l>Within my Skull in Order place't; </l>
            <l n="15">From thence to sally forth anew, </l>
            <l>One Universal single View. </l>
            <l>I've likewise ransack'd Books prophane, </l>
            <l>Which I shall muster, to explain </l>
            <l>Whate'er is hid obscure, perplext, </l>
            <l n="20">As plain as Pike-staff, ev'ry Text. </l>
            <l>Most Articles, whereof I treat, </l>
            <l>Have been the Subject of Debate, </l>
            <l>Full often o'er a Pot of Ale, </l>
            <l>When I was Rabby at Kinsale. </l>
            <l n="25">But then, for want of Antient Learning, </l>
            <l>The Scripture Sense not well discerning, </l>
            <l>Our Nights were past in great Confusion, </l>
            <l>No mortal making one Conclusion. </l>
            <l>To find a Remedy for this, </l>
            <l n="30">I hope it will not be amiss, </l>
            <l>To furnish my Associates quondam, </l>
            <l>(That they no more dispute at randome) </l>
            <l>With choice Collected Dissertations, </l>
            <l>Answers, Rejoinders, Replications, </l>
            <l n="35">That each may have enough to say, </l>
            <l>And hold the Scripture his own way. </l>
            <l>Profecto legi plus quam satis, </l>
            <l>More Languages than Mithridates. </l>
            <l>All which I Learn'd (as will appear </l>
            <l n="40">Since I left Ireland) in one Year; </l>
            <l>Where such, as knew my stock, can tell, </l>
            <l>I scarcely cou'd Read English well. </l>
            <l>In this one Book I've done much more, </l>
            <l>Than all the World has done before; </l>
            <l n="45">No Bibliotheque, that is now extant, </l>
            <l>Has half so well explain'd a Text on't; </l>
            <l>With so much ease I can Command it, </l>
            <l>The greatest Dunce may understand it. </l>
            <l>If any thinks the Work too long </l>
            <l n="50">For one Man's Head, I'll shew he's wrong; </l>
            <l>Because the way, which I intend </l>
            <l>Will bring it quickly to an end. </l>
            <l>In Chapters here and there I'll dip, </l>
            <l>Whole Books not worth the Reading Skip, </l>
            <l n="55">Whate'er's Poetical, or Moral, </l>
            <l>To them I have a mortal Quarrel; </l>
            <l>What meerly is Historical, </l>
            <l>I shall not touch upon at all; </l>
            <l>You'll see me such a Bible-trimmer, </l>
            <l n="60">That I'll reduce it to a Primmer. </l>
            <l>As for the Fathers, they are all met, </l>
            <l>In Pool, Petavius, and Calmet, </l>
            <l>I've Read 'em Page by Page, and find </l>
            <l>No gleaning Work for me behind. </l>
            <l n="65">And when I cut one Folio short, </l>
            <l>Will not the Reader thank me for't? </l>
            <l>For I have so much Antient Lore </l>
            <l>I could have swell'd 'em into four. </l>
            <l>We wait Subscriptions coming in, </l>
            <l n="70">We're just beginning to begin; </l>
            <l>'Tis this the Printer's sole pretence is, </l>
            <l>We've Paper, Types, Amanuensis; </l>
            <l>And all, but what few Pence are owing, </l>
            <l>To set the Press and me a going. </l>
            <l n="75">One thing I beg leave to remark---- </l>
            <l>For Young Divines, who're in the dark; </l>
            <l>And English Readers, who are straining </l>
            <l>In every Chapter for a meaning; </l>
            <l>For Men of Letters, and good Sense, </l>
            <l n="80">Here's Learning at a small expence; </l>
            <l>They'll find my Books, when well examin'd, </l>
            <l>Will do by Help of Pool and Hammond; </l>
            <l>And if the Parsons can afford once </l>
            <l>A Bible with a large Concordance, </l>
            <l n="85">I know not any thing they lack </l>
            <l>Except it be an Almanack. </l>
            <l>In my Compilement they shall see </l>
            <l>Opinions, great Variety! </l>
            <l>That every Schismatick with ease, </l>
            <l n="90">May find a Gloss himself to please. </l>
            <l>Now Monsieur Calmet (like an Olio) </l>
            <l>Disht up nine Tracts of his in Folio. </l>
            <l>To all his Country-Men reveal'd, </l>
            <l>What Latin, Hebrew, Greek conceal'd, </l>
            <l n="95">So plain in French, hat every Peasant </l>
            <l>Breaks out with Rapture in the praise on't. </l>
            <l>O what a Glorious learned heap is't! </l>
            <l>A wond'rous Author for a Papist! </l>
            <l>I wish in English 'twere Translated, </l>
            <l n="100">And mine to wipe his Rev'rence fated. </l>
            <l>To what Perfection had he brought </l>
            <l>His Books, with Liberty of Thought! </l>
            <l>But all along he's Crampt I find, </l>
            <l>And therefore durst not speak his mind; </l>
            <l n="105">For had he said a Word 'gainst Popery, </l>
            <l>The Laws wou'd turn his Neck with Rope a wry. </l>
            <l>Thus Foreign Pop'ry is a Curse, </l>
            <l>But English Popery is worse. </l>
            <l>		Remember all, before you're told, </l>
            <l n="110">That what I Write for New, is Old; </l>
            <l>If any Man of Reading looks </l>
            <l>He'll find it all in other Books; </l>
            <l>As I'm an Orthodox Divine, </l>
            <l>I've stol'n my Comments ev'ry line. </l>
            <l n="115">There's all the wrangling Tracts I know </l>
            <l>Collected here both con and pro, </l>
            <l>So well dispos'd of, ev'ry Man </l>
            <l>May find the Truth out, if he can. </l>
            <l>From the Creation to the Flood </l>
            <l n="120">(To shew you that my Work is good) </l>
            <l>I've drawn a Sketch, as I thought best, </l>
            <l>To form a Judgment of the rest. </l>
            <l>A word or two before I close all, </l>
            <l>One Doctor Innis makes Proposal, </l>
            <l n="125">A poor Insipid Moral Tool, </l>
            <l>He'd have the World to walk by Rule. </l>
            <l>He thinks I've nought to do, but nose him, </l>
            <l>I'd see him hang'd e'er I oppose him. </l>
            <l>He strives to make Men good, but I Sir </l>
            <l n="130">Resolve to make them worse, and Wiser. </l>
            <l>It ever was my way to love </l>
            <l>The Serpent, rather than the Dove. </l>
            <l>The Doctor, by a vain Pretension, </l>
            <l>Depends upon his own Invention; </l>
            <l n="135">But I, who always liv'd on loan, </l>
            <l>Shan't Write a Sentence of my own.   </l>
            <p>SIR, I Have inserted your Poem, and think you have done 
your self great Honour, by shewing so much Regard to a 
Person remarkably Eminent; besides a most laudable Zeal in 
recommending a Work, which is likely to prove of the 
Greatest Advantage to our Church in general, in this 
degenerate Age of Prophaness and Infidelity.  </p>
            <l>	I am with due Respect Your's, &amp;c.  </l>
            <l>		The Intelligencer.    </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XII" type="article">
            <head>Article XII</head>
            <opener>SINCE our English Friends have done us the Honour to 
Publish to their Countrymen, some of the Pieces from this 
Paper; We think ourselves oblig'd in Justice to return the 
Favour, by making the following Tale from the Country-
Journal, Dated the 3d of Aug. 1728, the Subject of this 
Day's Entertainment.   </opener>
            <p>From my own Chambers.  </p>
            <p>WHEN I was a young Man, I was very curious in collecting 
all the occasional State Tracts, or Pieces of Poetry, which 
were publish'd at that Time; and, upon looking them over, I 
find some, which I believe my Readers will think not 
altogether mal apropos at present.  The following Verses are 
of this kind, which appear plainly enough to be levell'd at 
some Pensionary Parliament; but as the Author of this little 
Piece hath not sufficiently distinguished the Characters, 
which He designed to expose, by any particular Marks; so my 
Memory will not enable me to explain the Sentiments of the 
Publick on that Occasion.  However, as it seems to contain a 
good, general Moral, I have ventur'd to give it to my 
Readers; and if it should happen to meet with any Success, I 
may, perhaps, communicate others, which are not to be met 
with in any of the publick Miscellanies of those Times.  </p>
            <p>The Progress of PATRIOTISM.  A TALE.  </p>
            <p>Vendidit HIC Auro Patriam.  </p>
            <l>SIR RALPH, a simple, rural Knight, </l>
            <l>Could just distinguish Wrong from Right; </l>
            <l>When He receiv'd a Quarter's Rent, </l>
            <l>And almost half in Taxes went, </l>
            <l n="5">He rail'd at Places, Bribes and Pensions, </l>
            <l>And secret Service, new Inventions; </l>
            <l>Preach'd up the true, old English Spirit, </l>
            <l>And mourn'd the great Neglect of Merit; </l>
            <l>Lamented our forlorn Condition, </l>
            <l n="10">And wish'd the Country would Petition; </l>
            <l>Said, He would first subscribe his Name, </l>
            <l>And added, 'Twas a burning shame </l>
            <l>That some Men large Estates should get, </l>
            <l>And fatten on the Publick Debt; </l>
            <l n="15">Of his poor Country urg'd his Love, </l>
            <l>And shook his Head at Those above. </l>
            <l>		This Conduct, in a private Station, </l>
            <l>Procur'd the Knight great Reputation; </l>
            <l>The Neighbours all approv'd his Zeal, </l>
            <l n="20">(Though few Men judge, yet all Men feel) </l>
            <l>And with a general Voice declar'd </l>
            <l>Money was scarce, the Times were hard; </l>
            <l>That what Sir Ralph observ'd was true, </l>
            <l>And wish'd the Gallows had its Due. </l>
            <l n="25">		Thus blest in popular Affection, </l>
            <l>Behold! there came on an Election, </l>
            <l>And who more proper than Sir Ralph </l>
            <l>To guard their Privileges safe? </l>
            <l>So, in Return for Zeal and Beer, </l>
            <l n="30">They chose him for a Knight o'th' Shire. </l>
            <l>		But mark how Climates change the Mind, </l>
            <l>And Virtue chops about like Wind! </l>
            <l>Duely the Knight came up to Town, </l>
            <l>Resolv'd to pull Corruption down, </l>
            <l n="35">Frequented Clubs of the same Party, </l>
            <l>And in the Cause continued hearty, </l>
            <l>Broach'd his Opinions, wet and dry, </l>
            <l>And gave some honest Votes awry. </l>
            <l>		At length, in that old, spacious Court, </l>
            <l n="40">Where Members just at Noon resort, </l>
            <l>Up to our Knight Sir Bluestring came, </l>
            <l>And call'd him frankly by his Name, </l>
            <l>Smil'd on Him, shook Him by the Hand, </l>
            <l>And gave Him soon to understand, </l>
            <l n="45">That though his Person was a Stranger, </l>
            <l>Yet that in Times of greatest Danger, </l>
            <l>His faithful Services were known, </l>
            <l>And all his Family's here in Town, </l>
            <l>For whom He had a great Affection; </l>
            <l n="50">And wish'd Him Joy of his Election, </l>
            <l>Assur'd him that his Country's Voice </l>
            <l>Could not have made a better Choice. </l>
            <l>		Sir Ralph, who, if not much bely'd, </l>
            <l>Had always some Degrees of Pride, </l>
            <l n="55">Perceiv'd his Heart begin to swell, </l>
            <l>And lik'd this Doctrine mighty well, </l>
            <l>Took Notice of his Air and Look, </l>
            <l>And how familiarly He spoke; </l>
            <l>Such Condescensions, such Professions </l>
            <l n="60">Remov'd all former ill Impressions. </l>
            <l>		The Statesman (who, we must agree, </l>
            <l>Can far into our Foibles see, </l>
            <l>And knows exactly how to flatter </l>
            <l>The weak, blind Sides of human Nature) </l>
            <l n="65">Saw the vain Wretch begin to yield, </l>
            <l>And farther thus his Oil instill'd. </l>
            <l>		Sir Ralph, said He, all Forms apart, </l>
            <l>So dear I hold you at my Heart, </l>
            <l>Have such a Value for your Worth, </l>
            <l n="70">Your Sense and Honour and so forth, </l>
            <l>That in some Points, extremely nice, </l>
            <l>I should be proud of your Advice; </l>
            <l>Let me, good Sir, the Favour pray, </l>
            <l>To eat a Bit with me to Day; </l>
            <l n="75">Nay, dear Sir Ralph, you must agree---- </l>
            <l>Your Honour's Hour?----exactly Three. </l>
            <l>		These Points premis'd, they bow and 
part, </l>
            <l>With Hands press'd hard to either Heart; </l>
            <l>For now the publick Business calls </l>
            <l n="80">Each Patriot to St. Stephen's Walls; </l>
            <l>Whether the present Debts to State;\}\ </l>
            <l>Or on some new Supplies debate, </l>
            <l>Would here be needless to relate. </l>
            <l>		From thence, at the appointed Hour, </l>
            <l n="85">The Knight attends the Man of Power, </l>
            <l>Who, better to secure his Ends, </l>
            <l>Had likewise bid some courtly Friends, </l>
            <l>His Brother Townly and his Grace, </l>
            <l>Great Statesmen both and both in Place; </l>
            <l n="90">Our British Horace, fam'd for Wit, </l>
            <l>Alike for Courts and Senates fit; </l>
            <l>Sir William, from his early Youth, </l>
            <l>Renown'd for Honour, Virtue, Truth; </l>
            <l>And Bub-ble, just restor'd to Favour, </l>
            <l n="95">On Pardon ask'd for late Behaviour. </l>
            <l>		The Statesman met his Convert-Guest,\}\ </l>
            <l>Saluted, clasp'd Him to his Breast, </l>
            <l>Then introduc'd Him to the rest. </l>
            <l>		Whilst He, with Wonder and Amaze, </l>
            <l n="100">The Splendour of the House surveys, </l>
            <l>Huge China Jars and Piles of Plate, </l>
            <l>And modish Screens and Beds of State, </l>
            <l>Gilt Sconces, of stupendous Size, </l>
            <l>And costly Paintings strike his Eyes, </l>
            <l n="105">From Italy and Flanders brought </l>
            <l>At the Expence of Nations bought; </l>
            <l>Yet doth not one of these relate </l>
            <l>The tragick End of R----s of State, </l>
            <l>Although such Pictures might supply </l>
            <l n="110">Fit Lessons to the Great Man's Eye; </l>
            <l>But o'ergrown Favourites dread to think </l>
            <l>From whence they rose, and how may sink. </l>
            <l>		Dinner now waited on the Board, </l>
            <l>Rich as this City would afford, </l>
            <l n="115">(For every Element supplies, </l>
            <l>His Table with its Rarities) </l>
            <l>The Guests promiscuous take their Place, </l>
            <l>Pro more, without Form or Grace; </l>
            <l>There might the little Knight be seen </l>
            <l n="120">With Ribons blue and Ribons green, </l>
            <l>All complaisant and debonair, </l>
            <l>As if the King Himself were there; </l>
            <l>Obsequious each consults his Tast, </l>
            <l>And, begging to be serv'd the last, </l>
            <l n="125">Points round by turns to every Dish; </l>
            <l>Will you have Soop, Sir Ralph, or Fish? </l>
            <l>This Fricasee or that Ragoust? </l>
            <l>Pray, Sir, be free and let me know. </l>
            <l>		The Cloth remov'd, the Glass goes round, </l>
            <l n="130">With loyal Healths and Wishes crown'd; </l>
            <l>May King and Senate long agree! </l>
            <l>Success attend the Ministry! </l>
            <l>Let publick Faith and Stocks increase! </l>
            <l>And grant us Heav'n! a speedy Peace! </l>
            <l n="135">		Discourse ensues on homebred 
Rage, </l>
            <l>That rank Distemper of the Age, </l>
            <l>And instantly they all agree, </l>
            <l>They never were so blest, or free; </l>
            <l>That all Complaints were nought but Faction, </l>
            <l n="140">And Patriotism meer Distraction, </l>
            <l>Though full of Reason, void of Grace, </l>
            <l>And only meant to get in Place. </l>
            <l>		Sir Ralph in Approbation bow'd; </l>
            <l>Yet own'd, that with the giddy Croud, </l>
            <l n="145">He formerly had gone astray, </l>
            <l>And talk'd in quite another Way, </l>
            <l>Possess'd with Jealousies and Fears, </l>
            <l>Dispers'd by restless Pamphleteers, </l>
            <l>In Libels weekly and diurnal, </l>
            <l n="150">Especially the * Country Journal; </l>
            <l>\note begin\ </l>
            <l>	* From hence it appears that a Paper was published 
under that Name, </l>
            <l>   long before this, in which we are at present 
engaged. </l>
            <l>	\note end\ </l>
            <l>But as he felt sincere Contrition, </l>
            <l>He hop'd his Faults would find Remission. </l>
            <l>		Dear Sir, reply'd the Blue-string 
Knight, </l>
            <l>I'm glad you think Affairs go right, </l>
            <l n="155">All Errors past must be excus'd, </l>
            <l>(Since the best Men may be abus'd) </l>
            <l>What's in my Power you may command, </l>
            <l>Then shook Him once more by the Hand, </l>
            <l>Gave him great Hopes (at least his Word) </l>
            <l n="160">That He should be a Treasury-Lord, </l>
            <l>And to confirm his good Intention, </l>
            <l>At present order'd him a Pension. </l>
            <l>		By these Degrees, Sir Ralph is grown </l>
            <l>The stanchest Tool in all the Town, </l>
            <l n="165">At Points and Job-work never fails; </l>
            <l>At all his old Acquaintance rails; </l>
            <l>Holds every Doctrine now in Fashion; </l>
            <l>That Debts are Blessings to a Nation; </l>
            <l>That Bribery, under Whig-Direction, </l>
            <l n="170">Is needful to discourage Faction; </l>
            <l>That standing Armies are most fitting </l>
            <l>To guard the Liberties of Britain; </l>
            <l>That F----e is her sincerest Friend, </l>
            <l>On whom, she always should depend; </l>
            <l n="175">That Ministers, by Kings appointed, </l>
            <l>Are, under them, the Lord's anointed; </l>
            <l>Ergo, it is the self-same Thing, </l>
            <l>T' oppose the Minister or King; </l>
            <l>Ergo, by Consequence of Reason, </l>
            <l n="180">To censure Statesmen is High Treason. </l>
            <l>		In fine, his standing Creed is this; </l>
            <l>That right or wrong, or hit or miss, </l>
            <l>No Mischiefs can befal a Nation, </l>
            <l>Under so wise a Ministration; </l>
            <l n="185">That Britain is Sir Blue-string's Debtor, </l>
            <l>And Things did surely ne'er go better! </l>
            <l>		So the plain Country Girl, untainted, </l>
            <l>Nor yet with wicked Man acquainted, </l>
            <l>Starts at the first leud Application, </l>
            <l n="190">Though warm perhaps by Inclination, </l>
            <l>And swears she would not, with the King, </l>
            <l>For all the World do such a Thing; </l>
            <l>But when, with long, assiduous Art, </l>
            <l>Damon hath once seduc'd her Heart, </l>
            <l n="195">She learns her Lesson in a trice, </l>
            <l>And justifies the pleasing Vice, </l>
            <l>Calls it a natural, harmless Passion, </l>
            <l>Implanted from our first Creation, </l>
            <l>Holds there's no Sin between clean Sheets, </l>
            <l n="200">And lies with every Man she meets.    </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XIII" type="article">
            <head>Article XIII</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">Sermo datur cunctis, animi sapientia paucis.</q>
               <bibl>Cato.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THERE is one kind of Conversation, which every one Aims 
at, and every one almost fails in; It is that of Story-
telling. I know not any thing which engages our Attention 
with more Delight, when a Person has a sufficient stock of 
Talents Necessary for it, such as Good Sense, True Humour, a 
clear Head, a ready Command of Language, and a Variety of 
proper Gesture, to give Life and Spirit to what he says. If 
any of these be wanting, the Listners, instead of being 
diverted, are made very uneasy; but if the Person be utterly 
Void of them all, as it is very often the Case, he becomes a 
Nuissance to the Company, and they are so long upon the Rack 
as he speaks. It has sometimes fallen to my Lot, that a Man 
whom I never offended, has laid me under the Persecution of 
a long Story, and Compelled me to hear, what neither 
concerned himself, nor me, nor indeed any Body else, and at 
the same time, he was as much in earnest, as if both our 
Lives and Fortunes, and the Felicity of the whole Kingdom 
depended upon what he said. A Humour very unaccountable! 
That a Man shall be letting off Words for an hour or two, 
with a very innocent Intention, and after he has done his 
best, only makes me uneasy, and himself Contemptible. </p>
            <p>This natural Infirmity in Men, is not only confined to 
Story-telling, but it appears likewise in every Essay 
whatsoever of their Intellectuals. As for Instance; If one 
of these be a Preacher of GOD's Word, by far fetched 
Criticisms, numerous Divisions, and Sub-divisions, in-
coherent Digressions, tedious Repetitions, useless Remarks, 
Weak Answers to strong Objections, Inferences to no 
Premises, tedious Exhortations, and many other Methods of 
Protraction, he shall draw you out a Discourse for an hour 
and a quarter, unequally dispensing Opium and Edification to 
his Flock, there being seven Sleepers for one Hearer. If he 
be a Lawyer, he shall, by an uncommon Way of Amusement, run 
away with a Subject, which might be explained in two 
Minutes, and Dilate upon it two hours, with such a 
Volubility of Tongue, such Affluence of Expression, with 
something so like a good Style, and manner of Thinking, that 
the Judges and Jury, attend with as much Gravity, as if 
there were a continued Chain of true Reasoning, and solid 
Argument. If he be a Member of the Upper or Lower House, he 
does not proceed four Sentences, before the Rest know where 
to have him an hour hence; in the mean time they Divert one 
another, in talking of matters indifferent, till the 
Gentleman has done. I could give many more Instances, but 
that I think these sufficient for my present purpose; 
beside, least I should incur the like Reproach my self, I 
must in a few Words, divide the Story-tellers, into the 
short, the long, the marvellous, the Insipid, and the 
Delightful. </p>
            <p>The short Story-teller is he, who tells a great deal in 
few Words, engages your Attention, pleases your Imagination, 
or quickly excites your Laughter. Of this Rank were 
Xenophon, Plutarch, Macrobius, among the Ancients. Ex. gr. </p>
            <p>When the Nephelai of Aristophanes, a Satyr upon Socrates 
was Acting, his Friends desired him to retire, and hide 
behind them. No said Socrates, I will stand up here, where I 
may be seen; for now I think my self like a good Feast, and 
that every one has share of me. vid. Feast of Xenophon. </p>
            <p>Brasidas the Famous Lacedemonian General caught a Mouse. 
It bit him, and by that means made its escape. O Jupiter, 
said he, what Creature so Contemptible, but may have it's 
Liberty if it will Contend for it. vid. Plutarch. de 
profect. virtut. </p>
            <p>Diogenes having sailed to Chios, while it was under the 
Dominion of the Persians, said in a full Assembly, the 
Inhabitants were Fools for Erecting a Colledge, and Building 
Temples, since the Persians would not allow them the 
privilege of making their own Priests, but sent them over 
the most Illiterate of their Magi. </p>
            <p>Augustus while he was encamped with his Army, some where 
near Mantua, was disturbed three Nights successively, by the 
hooting of an Owl. Proclamation was made to the Soldiers, 
that whoever caught the Offender, (so that he might be 
brought to Justice,) should have an ample reward for his 
pains. Every one was Loyally engaged in the pursuit of this 
Bird. At last, one more Vigilant than the rest, found him in 
a Hollow-tree, so brought him in Triumph to the Emperor, who 
saw him with the greatest Joy, but gave the Soldier a sum of 
Money, so far below his Expectation, that he let the Owl fly 
away that Instant, so true a Sense of Liberty, ran through 
the very meanest of the Romans.  Macrob. Sat. </p>
            <p>The long Story-teller is one, who tells little or nothing 
in a great number of Words; for this, many among the Moderns 
are famous, particularly the French. And among our selves in 
this Kingdom we have a vast Number of the better sort. As 
well as I can recollect there are six Deans, four Judges, 
six and thirty Councellors at Law, sixty five Attorneys, 
some few Fellows of the College, every Alderman through the 
whole Nation, except one, all old Gentlemen, and Ladies, 
without exception, five of the College of Physicians, three 
or four Lords, two hundred Squires, and some few People of 
distinction beside. </p>
            <p>I shall here insert a fragment of a long Story, by way of 
example, containing 129 Words, which might have been said in 
these ten following, viz. Nine Years ago I was to Preach for 
a Friend. </p>
            <p>I remember once, I think it was about seven Years ago--No 
I lye--It was about nine Years ago; for it was just when my 
Wife was Lying in of Dicky, I remember particularly the 
Mid-wife would have had me stay to keep her company, and it 
was the heaviest Day of Storm and Rain, that I ever saw 
before, or since, but because I engaged to Preach for a very 
Worthy Friend of mine, who lived about twenty Miles off, and 
this being Saturday, I could not defer it to the next 
Morning, though I had an excellent Nag, which could have Rid 
it in three hours, I bought him of a Neighbour one Mr. 
Masterson, yet because I would not put my Friend in a fright 
&amp;c. Thus far he went in one Minute. The Story lasted an 
Hour, so that upon a fair computation he Spoke 7740 Words, 
instead of 600, by which means he made use of 7140 more than 
he had occasion for. If a right application were made of 
this hint, which I have given, it would be of admirable 
Effect in the dispatch of publick business, as well as 
private conversation, nay in the very Writing of Books, for 
which I refer the reader to the Fable of the Bees, and the 
two Elaborate Treatises, Written by the Learned Mr. H------
n. </p>
            <p>The marvellous, is he, who is fond of telling such things 
as no Man alive, who has the least use of his reason, can 
believe. This humour prevails very much in Travellers, and 
the Vain glorious, but is very pardonable, because no Man's 
Faith is imposed upon, or if it should be so, no ill 
consequence attends it. And beside, there is some kind of 
Amusement in seeing a Person seriously extravagant, 
expecting another should give Credit to what he knows 
impossible for the greatest Dunce to Swallow. </p>
            <p>One of these, who had travelled to Damascus, told his 
Company, that the Bees of that Country were as big as 
Turkies. Pray Sir, said a Gentleman (begging pardon for the 
Question) How large were the Hives? The same size with Ours, 
replied the Traveller. Very strange, said the other. But how 
got they into their Hives? That is none of my business, I 
Gad let them look to that. </p>
            <p>Another, who had Travelled as far as Persia, spoke to his 
Man John, as he was returning home, telling him, how 
Necessary it was, that a Traveller should draw things beyond 
the Life, or else, he could not hope for that respect from 
his Country-Men, which otherwise he might have. But at the 
same time, John, said he, wheresoever I shall Dine, or Sup, 
keep you close to my Chair, and if I do very much exceed the 
bounds of Truth, Punch me behind, that I may correct my 
self. It happened on a Day, that he Dined with a Certain 
Gentleman, who shall be Nameless, where he affirmed, that he 
saw a Monkey in the Island Borneo, which had a Tail three-
score Yards long. John punched him. I am certain it is fifty 
at least. John punched again. I believe to speak within 
compass, for I did not measure it, it must have been forty. 
John gave him tother Touch. I remember it lay over a Quick-
set hedge, and therefore could not be less than thirty. John 
at him again. I could take my Oath it was twenty. This did 
not satisfy John. Upon which the Master turned about in a 
Rage and said, Damn you for a Puppy, would you have the 
Monkey without any Tail at all? </p>
            <p>Did not the famous Dr. Burnet, whose History is much of 
the same stamp with his Travels, affirm that he saw an 
Elephant play at Ball? And that grave Gentleman Ysbrant 
Ides, in his Travels through Muscovy to China, assures us, 
that he saw Elephants, which were taught to low like Cows, 
to yell like Tigers, and to mimick the sounding of a 
Trumpet; but their highest Perfection, as he relates it, was 
that of singing like Canary birds. However this is not so 
marvellous (for Pliny relates Wonderful things of their 
Docility) as what a Gentleman told a full Company in my 
hearing within this fortnight. That he had seen a Show at 
Bristol, which was a Hare, taught to stand upon her hind-
legs and bow to all the Company, to each Person in 
particular, with a very good Grace, and then proceed to beat 
several Marches on the Drum. After this a Dog was set upon 
the Table. His Master, the Show-man, made many grievous 
Complaints against him, for High Crimes, and Misdemeanors. 
The Hare nits her Brows, kindles her Eyes like a Lady, falls 
in a Passion, attacks the Dog with all her Rage and Fury, as 
if she had been his Wife, Scratches, bites, and cuffs him 
round the Table, till the Spectators had enough for their 
Money. </p>
            <p>There is a certain Gentleman, now in Ireland, most 
remarkably fond of the marvellous (but this through Vanity) 
who among an infinite Number of the like Rarities, affirms, 
that he has a Carp, in a Pond by it self, which has for 
twenty Years past, supplyed him and his Friends, with a very 
good Dish of Fish, when they either came to Dine, or Sup 
with him. And the manner of it is thus. The Cook-maid goes 
with a large Kitchin-knife, which has a Whistle in its 
handle; she no sooner blows it, but the Carp comes to the 
Sluice and turns up its Belly, till she cuts out as much as 
she has occasion for, and then away it scuds. The Chasm is 
filled in a Day or two, and the Carp is as sound as a Roach, 
ready for the Knife again. Now, if he and his Cook-maid took 
the most solemn Oath to the truth of this, or the most 
sanctifyed Quaker should say YEA to it, which is made equal 
to any Prelate's Oath, I would no more give Credit to them, 
than I would to the Collonel, who said he was at the Battle 
of Landen, where his Majesty King William, of Glorious 
Memory, lost the Day. And this Collonel, being in the utmost 
Confusion, fled among the rest. He Swore he had Galloped 
above two miles, after his Horses Head was Shot off, by a 
Cannon-ball, which he should not have missed, if the poor 
Creature had not stooped at a River side to Drink. </p>
            <p>I should be glad to spend an Evening with half a dozen 
Gentlemen of this uncommon Genius, for I am certain they 
would improve upon one another, and thereby I might have an 
Oportunity of observing how far the Marvellous could be 
carryed, or whether it has any bounds at all. </p>
            <p>The insipid, who may not unfitly be called Soporifick, is 
one who goes plodding on in a heavy dull Relation of 
unimportant Facts. You Shall have an Account from such a 
Person of every Minute Circumstance, which happened in the 
Company where he has been, what he did, and what they did, 
what they said, and what he said, with a Million of trite 
Phrases, with an and so beginning every Sentence. And to 
make a long Story short. And as I was saying, with many more 
expletives of equal Signification. It is a most dreadful 
thing, when Men have neither the Talent of speaking, nor the 
Discretion of holding their Tongues, and that, of all 
People, such as are least qualifyed, are commonly the most 
earnest in this way of Conversation. </p>
            <p>The Delightful Story-teller is one, who speaks not a Word 
too much, or too little; who can, in a very careless manner, 
give a great deal of pleasure to others, and desires rather 
to Divert, than be Applauded; who shews good understanding, 
and a delicate turn of Wit in every thing which comes from 
him; who can entertain his Company better with the History 
of a Child and its Hobby-horse, than one of the Soporificks 
can with an Account of Alexander, and Bucephalus. Such a 
Person is not unlike a bad Reader who makes the most 
ingenious Piece his own, that is, Dull and Detestable, by 
only coming through his Mouth. But to return to the 
Delightful Story-teller, I cannot describe him by any Words 
so well, as his own, and therefore take the following Story 
to shew him in the most agreeable light. </p>
            <p>A Mountebank in Leicester-Fields had drawn a huge 
Assembly about him; among the rest a Fat unwieldy Fellow, 
half stifled in the Press, would be every fit Crying out 
Lord! what a filthy Crowd is here! pray good People give Way 
a litle! bless me! what a Devil has raked this Rable 
together? Zounds what squeezing is this! Honest Friend 
remove your Elbow. At last a Weaver, that stood next him, 
could hold no longer. A Plague confound you, said he, for an 
Over grown Sloven; and who, in the Devil's Name, helps to 
make up the Crowd half so much as your self? Don't you 
consider (with a Pox) that you take up more room with that 
Carcass than any five here? Is not the Place as fit for us, 
as for you? bring your own Guts to a reasonable Compass (and 
be Damnd) and then I'll engage we shall have room enough for 
us all. </p>
            <p>This I have transcribed from a most Celebrated Author, 
with great pleasure, and do earnestly recommend it to my 
Country-men, as the true standard of Story-telling, both as 
to Style, and Manner, and every thing requisite not only to 
please the Hearer, but to gain his favour and Affection. And 
for the Time to come, be it Enacted, that if any person, of 
what Rank soever, shall presume to exceed Six Minutes in a 
Story, to hum or haw, use hyphens between his Words, or 
Digressions, or offers to engage the Company to hear another 
Story when he has done, or speaks one Word more than is 
Necessary, or is a Stammerer in his Speech, that then it 
shall, and may be lawful for any one of the said Company, or 
the whole Company together, to pull out his, hers, or their 
Watches to make use of broad hints, or inuendoes for him the 
said Story-teller, to break off, although abruptly, 
otherwise he is to have a Glove, or Handkerchief, crammed 
into his Mouth for the first default, and for the second, to 
be kicked out of Company.     </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XIV" type="article">
            <head>Article XIV</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">Naturam expellas furc[acirc ] licet usque recurret. </q>
               <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THERE is an old Heathen Story, That Prometheus, who was a 
Potter in Greece, took a frolick to turn all the Clay in his 
Shop into Men and Women, separating the Fine from the 
Course, in order to distinguish the Sexes. The Males were 
formed of a mixture Blue and Red, as being of the toughest 
Consistence, fitter for Creatures destin'd to Hardships, 
Labour, and difficult Enterprizes; the Females were molded 
out of the most refined Stuff, much of the like substance 
with China-ware, Transparent, and Brittle; designing them 
rather for Show and Beauty, than to be of any real use in 
Life, farther than that of Generation. By the Transparency 
he intended the Men might see so plainly through them, that 
they should not be capable of Hypocrisy, Falshood or 
Intrigue; and by their britleness, he taught them, they were 
to be handled with a Tenderness suitable to their delicacy 
of Constitution. </p>
            <p>It was pleasant enough, to see with what Contrivance and 
Order, he disposed of his Journey-men in their several 
Appartments, and how judiciously he assigned each of them 
his Work, according to his Natural Capacity, and Talents, so 
that every Member, and part of the Humane Frame, was 
finished with the utmost exactness and Beauty. </p>
            <p>In one Chamber you might see a Leg-shaper; in another a 
Skull-roller; in a third an Arm-stretcher; in a fourth a 
Gut-winder; for each Workman was distinguished by a proper 
Term of Art, such as Knuckle-turner, Tooth-grinder, Rib-
cooper, Muscle-maker, Tendon-drawer, Paunch-blower, Vein-
brancher, and such like; but Prometheus himself made the 
Eyes, the Ears, and the Heart, which, because of their Nice 
and Intricate Structure, were chiefly the business of a 
Master-Workman. Beside this, he compleated the whole, by 
fitting and joyning the several parts together, according to 
the best Symetry and Proportion. The Statues are now upon 
their Legs. Life the chief ingredient is wanting, Prometheus 
takes a Ferula in his Hand, (a Reed of the Island Chios 
having an Oily Pith) steals up the Back-stairs to Apollo's 
Lodgings, lights it Clandestinely at the Chariot of the Sun, 
so down he creeps upon his Tip-toes to his Ware-house, and 
in a very few Minutes, by an Application of the Flame to the 
Nostrils of his Clay Images, sets them all a stalking and 
staring through one another, but intirely insensible of what 
they were doing. They looked so like the latter end of a 
Lord-Mayor's Feast, he could not bear the sight of them. He 
then saw it was absolutely Necessary to give them Passions, 
or Life would be an insipid thing, and so from the Super-
abundance of them in other Animals, he culls out enough for 
his purpose, which he Blended and Tempered so well, before 
Infusion, that his Men and Women became the most amiable 
Creatures, that thought can conceive. </p>
            <p>Love was then like a pure Vestal-flame, not made up of 
sudden Joy, Transports, and Extasies, but Constant, Friendly 
and Benevolent. </p>
            <p>Anger did not appear horrid, and frightful by Turbulent 
Emotions of the Breast, and Distortions of the Face, but 
preserved a Dignity of Resentment in the Countenance, 
commanding a Reverential awe in the Offender. </p>
            <p>Fear did not in the least encroach upon the Bounds of 
Fortitude, by a slavish Dejection of Spirits, nor was it 
ever seen upon any occasion, but as a Monitor, to prevent 
the doing of any Action, which might be attended with 
Disgrace, or Repentance. </p>
            <p>In the same manner was every Passion and Appetite under 
the best Regulation and Dominion of reason. The World would 
have been a most delightful Scene had People continued in 
this Situation, but alass! there can be no Happiness here 
without a mixture of misery. </p>
            <p>Prometheus is apprehended for his Theft, and Presumption, 
bound fast in Chains to a Rock, with a Vulture to prey upon 
his Liver. His Journey-men get Drunk for joy, they were now 
their own Masters, during which interval, they fall to Man 
and Woman making with excessive Precipitation and hurry. Now 
you might see a small Head set upon a pair of broad 
Shoulders; a Nose too long, too short, too thick, too small, 
or awry on the Face; A large heavy Carcass reard upon a 
small pair of Spindle Shanks, by which means they became 
bandy; a long Chin to a short Face; One Arm longer than the 
other; Eyes too big for their Sockets; Mouths three times 
too wide, or too narrow; every Part and Limb almost chosen 
and put together at random. But to conclude the Farce, when 
they came to the Passion-work, instead of blending, and 
tempering them in true Proportion, they took them from the 
worst of Animals simply, and by guess. To one was given the 
Rage and Fury of a Wolf. Hence came a most Virulent, 
Persecuting, Malicious Villain; from whom has descended 
those boistrous and outragious Pests of Society, who are 
every Day disturbing our Peace; the only blessing we can 
enjoy upon Earth. To another the Poison and Rancour of a 
Toad, from whom sprang the revengeful, who upon the least 
touch of Offence, are ever upon the watch, to ruin the 
inadvertent. To another the Subtilty and Cunning of a Fox, 
from whom we trace the Politician, who turns all the motions 
of his Soul to Seducing, Betraying, Surprizing, Fair-
Promises with foul Intentions, perpetual Stratagems to his 
own advantage, under the Specious appearance of the publick 
Good. </p>
            <p>To another the Alertness of a Monkey. He begat a large 
family of Jibers, Buffoons, and Mimicks; these are a 
numerous breed and dispersed over the Face of the whole 
Earth. The chief business of their Lives is to make People 
laugh at one another, and not to spare even their nearest 
Friends; who while they are Copying the imperfections of 
others, bring themselves to be Originals. You may 
distinguish this happy Race by their Hawk-noses, One Eye 
less than t'other, and a perpetual Sneer, which by repeated 
Habit, becomes inseparable from their Faces. To another the 
Pride of a Peacock. He turns Beau, stiches all the Tinsel 
about him, that he can; hangs a Tayl to his Head, and so 
Walks through the World. To another the Gluttony, Laziness 
and Luxury of a Hog. From him are descended your pamper'd 
Citizens, and others, whose chief exercise consists in 
Eating and Drinking: They are very easily distinguished by 
the Plumpness and Rotundity of their Dewlap, the Torosity of 
their Necks and Breasts, and the prominence of their 
Abdomen. Numberless are the Instances might be given of the 
predominance of Brutes, thus occasioned in Men, but that I 
hasten to give a Summary Account of the Animals, chiefly 
chosen by these Journey-men, to give proper accomplishments 
to the other Sex, viz. Cats, Ferets, Weazels, Vipers, 
Magpies, Geese, Wagtails, Rats, Stoats, Ratle-Sneaks, Wasps, 
Hornets, and some few others. It is needless to inform the 
Reader, what Qualities were infused from these, when he can 
behold them so plainly in one half or more of his Female 
Acquaintance. And I dare venture to say, that you can hardly 
go into a Family, where you may not distinguish some one 
Lady eminently remarkable for a lively resemblance to one, 
or more of the aforesaid Animals. Upon the whole, I shall 
make this Remark, that the Handy-work of Prometheus, and 
their Progeny, are to be distinguished with the greatest 
ease, from that of his Journey-men; his being all Humane, 
Benevolent, Easy, Affable, Good-humoured, Charitable and 
Friendly; whereas those of his Journey-men are Cruel, 
Malicious, Turbulent, Morose, Ill-natured, Snarling, 
Quarrelsome, Pragmatical, Covetous, and Inhuman, which we 
dayly experience among the great Vulgar and the Small, nor 
can all the Power of Art, or Education, intirely Wash away 
the Dirt of the Journey-man's Palm, or quite Abolish, or 
restrain that Exuberance of wrong Passions which are owing 
to the cause already assigned. And I will say farther, that 
I know nothing else in Nature, but what may by Cultivation, 
or Chymistry change it's Nature, such Persons only excepted, 
who have had a wrong Impression at first, and Human 
Excrements; But this being of too foul a Nature, to bear a 
Dissertation in prose, I shall Transcribe it, as it was 
Cooked up in verse, for the Taste of the Polite, being a 
very fit Emblem, to explain this Great, and useful Maxim, 
That there is no method, as yet found out, to change Natural 
Inclination.   </p>
            <p>THE TALE OF THE T--D.  </p>
            <l>A Pastry-Cook once molded up a T---- </l>
            <l>(You may beleive me when I give my Word) </l>
            <l>With nice Ingredients of the fragrant kind, </l>
            <l>And Sugar of the best, right Doubl' refin'd, </l>
            <l n="5">He blends them all; for he was fully bent </l>
            <l>Quite to annihilate it's Taste, and Scent. </l>
            <l>With Out-stretcht Arms, he twirls the Rolling-Pin, </l>
            <l>And spreads the yielding Ordure smooth and Thin. </l>
            <l>'Twas not to save his Flow'r, but shew his Art, </l>
            <l n="10">Of such foul Dough to make a sav'ry Tart. </l>
            <l>He heats his Ov'n with care, and bak'd it well, </l>
            <l>But still the Crust's offensive to the Smell; </l>
            <l>The Cook was vext to see himself so foil'd, </l>
            <l>So Works it to a Dumpling, which he boyl'd; </l>
            <l n="15">Now out it comes, and if it stunk before, </l>
            <l>It stinks full twenty times as much, and more. </l>
            <l>He breaks fresh Eggs, converts it into Batter, </l>
            <l>Works them with Spoon about a Wooden-Platter, </l>
            <l>To true consistence, such as Cook-maids make </l>
            <l n="20">At Shrovetide, when they toss the pliant Cake. </l>
            <l>In vain he twirls the Pan, the more it fries, </l>
            <l>The more the Nauseous, fetid Vapours rise. </l>
            <l>Resolv'd to make it still a sav'ry bit, </l>
            <l>He takes the Pan-Cake, rolls it round a Spit, </l>
            <l n="25">Winds up the Jack, and sets it to the fire, </l>
            <l>But roasting rais'd it's pois'nous fumes the high'r. </l>
            <l>Offended much (although it was his own,) </l>
            <l>At length he throws it, where it shou'd be thrown, </l>
            <l>And in a Passion, storming loud, he cry'd, </l>
            <l n="30">If neither bak'd, nor boyl'd, nor roast, nor 
fry'd, </l>
            <l>Can thy offensive Hellish Taint reclaim, </l>
            <l>Go to the filthy Jakes from whence you came. </l>
            <l> </l>
            <l>                           THE MORAL. </l>
            <l> </l>
            <l>THIS Tale requires but one short Application, </l>
            <l>It fits all Upstart Scoundrels in each Nation, </l>
            <l>Minions of Fortune, Wise Men's jest in Pow'r, </l>
            <l>Like Weeds on Dunghils Stinking, Rank, and Sour.    </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XV" type="article">
            <head>Article XV</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Lamentations, Chap. 2. v. 19.  </title>
               </bibl>
               <q type="verse">
                  <l>Arise, cry out in the Night: in the beginning </l>
                  <l>of the Watches, pour out thine Heart like </l>
                  <l>Water, before the Face of the Lord: lift up thy </l>
                  <l>Hands towards him, for the Life of thy Young </l>
                  <l>Children that faint for Hungar, </l>
                  <l>in the Top of every Street.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Do remember to have Read an Account, that an Ode which 
Pindar Writ, in honour to the Island Delos, was Inscribed in 
the Temple of Minerva, at Athens, in large Letters of Gold; 
A publick and very laudable acknowledgment for the Poet's 
Ingenuity, and for no more than a bare Compliment! Such was 
the encouragement given by the great, and publick Spirited 
Athenians. Had the same Poet, inspired by a Noble and 
Heroick Ardor, by another Ode, awakened and rouzed their 
whole State against an invading Enemy; or opened their Eyes 
against any Secret and Wicked Contrivers of their 
Destruction, they would have erected him a Statue at least. 
But Alass that Spirit is fled from the World! and, long 
since neglected. Virtue is become her own Pay-master. My 
Country-men, I hope, will forgive me, if I complain there 
has been so little Notice taken of a small, but most 
excellent Pamphlet, Written by the DRAPIER. It is Intitled, 
A SHORT VIEW OF THE STATE OF IRELAND. There never was any 
Treatise yet published, with a Zeal more generous for the 
Universal good of a Nation, or a design more seasonable, 
considering our present lamentable Condition, yet we listen 
not to the Voice of the Charmer. Whereas it should have been 
Inscribed in Capital Letters (as Glorious as those of the 
Poet) in the most publick part of every Corporation-town, 
through this whole Kingdom, that People might behold the 
several unprovoked causes of their Poverty, our Offences 
towards Heaven excepted. Nay, I will proceed farther, and 
say, that every Head of every Family, ought to instruct the 
Children so far in this most incomparable Pamphlet, that 
they should not only understand, but be able, to repeat by 
Heart every single Paragraph, through the Whole. This was 
the Method laid down by the wisest Law-giver, that ever the 
World produced; To gain the Hearts of the People, by working 
upon their Memories. </p>
            <p>Deut. chap. 6. v. 7. And thou shalt Teach them diligently 
unto thy Children, and shalt talk of them, when thou sittest 
in thine House, and when thou walkest by the Way, and when 
thou liest down, and when thou risest up. </p>
            <p>8. And thou shalt bind them for a Sign upon thine Hand, 
and they shall be as frontlets between thine Eyes. </p>
            <p>9. And thou shalt Write them upon the Posts of thy House, 
and on thy Gates. </p>
            <p>And, where would be the great Trouble, since we have 
little else to do, if every Man would read a Lecture of the 
Short View every Day in his Family, after Reading Prayers? 
Nor do I think the expence would be extravagant, if he 
should have every Page of it Re-printed, to be hung up in 
Frames, in every Chamber of his House. That it might be as 
evident, as, the Hand Writing on the Wall. </p>
            <p>And, since I have ventured thus far, to praise and 
recommend this most inimitable Piece, let me Speak a few 
Words in favour of it's AUTHOR. </p>
            <p>I would propose to My Country-men, before all their MONY 
goes off, (it is going as fast as possible) to convert it 
into a few Statues to the DRAPIER, in those Memorable parts 
of this Kingdom, where our Heroes have shone with the 
greatest Lustre, in Defence of our Liberty, and the 
PROTESTANT RELIGION over all Europe. At DERRY, at 
ENNISKILLEN, at BOYN, at AUGHRIM. Nor would it be amiss, to 
set up a few more about our Metropolis, with that Glorious 
Inscription Libertas et Natale Solum. </p>
            <p>If our MONY were metamorphosed upon such a good occasion, 
as this, it would not be in the Power of any * Cypselus, 
\note begins\ </p>
            <p>* Cypselus, A Governor of Corinth, who Contrived a Tax, 
which </p>
            <p>brought all the Mony of that State to himself in ten 
Years Time. </p>
            <p>vid. Aristot. polit. </p>
            <p>\note ends\ to get it into his own Coffers, and it would 
be the only method, to prevent it's being carry'd off, 
except our Vice-roys should Act like the Roman Prefects, and 
Run away with our very Statues.  </p>
            <p>Courteous READER, Mark well what follows.  I Am assured 
that it hath for some time been practised as a method of 
making Men's Court, when they are asked about the Rate of 
Lands, the Abilities of Tenants, the State of Trade and 
Manufacture in this Kingdom, and how their Rents are payed; 
to Answer, That in their Neighbourhood all things are in a 
flourishing Condition, the Rent and Purchase of Land every 
Day encreasing. And if a Gentleman happens to be a little 
more sincere in his Representations, besides being looked on 
as not well affected, he is sure to have a Dozen 
Contradictors at his Elbow. I think it is no manner of 
Secret why these Questions are so cordially asked, or so 
obligingly Answered. </p>
            <p>But since with Regard to the Affairs of this Kingdom, I 
have been using all Endeavours to subdue my Indignation, to 
which indeed I am not provoked by any Personal Interest, 
being not the Owner of one Spot of Ground in the whole 
Island, I shall only enumerate by Rules generally known, and 
never Contradicted, what are the true Causes of any 
Countries flourishing and growing Rich, and then examine 
what Effects arise from those Causes in the Kingdom of 
Ireland. </p>
            <p>The first Cause of a Kindgom's thriving is the 
Fruitfulness of the Soyl, to produce the Necessaries and 
Conveniencies of Life, not only sufficient for the 
Inhabitants, but for Exportation into other Countries. </p>
            <p>The Second, is the Industry of the People in Working up 
all their Native Commodities to the last degree of 
Manufacture. </p>
            <p>The Third, is the Conveniency of safe Ports and Havens, 
to Carry out their own Goods, as much manufactured, and 
bring in those of others, as little manufactured, as the 
Nature of mutual Commerce will allow. </p>
            <p>The Fourth, is, That the Natives should as much as 
possible, Export and Import their Goods in Vessels of their 
own Timber, made in their own Country. </p>
            <p>The Fifth, is the Liberty of a free Trade in all Foreign 
Countries which will permit them, except to those who are in 
War with their own Prince or State. </p>
            <p>The Sixth, is, by being Governed only by Laws made with 
their own Consent, for otherwise they are not a free People. 
And therefore all Appeals for Justice, or Applications for 
Favour or Preferment to another Country, are so many 
grievous Impoverishments. </p>
            <p>The Seventh, is, by Improvement of Land, encouragement of 
Agriculture, and thereby encreasing the Number of their 
People, without which any Country, however Blessed by 
Nature, must continue Poor. </p>
            <p>The Eighth, is the Residence of the Prince, or Chief 
Administrator of the Civil Power. </p>
            <p>The Ninth, is the Concourse of Foreigners for Education, 
Curiosity or Pleasure, or as to a general Mart of Trade. </p>
            <p>The Tenth, is by disposing all Offices of Honour, Profit 
or Trust, only to the Natives, or at least with very few 
Exceptions, where Strangers have long Inhabited the Country, 
and are supposed to Understand, and regard the Interest of 
it as their own. </p>
            <p>The Eleventh is, when the Rents of Lands, and Profits of 
Employments, are spent in the Country which produced them, 
and not in another, the former of which will certainly 
happen, where the Love of our Native Country prevails. </p>
            <p>The Twelfth, is by the publick Revenues being all Spent 
and Employed at Home, except on the Occasions of a Foreign 
War. </p>
            <p>The Thirteenth, is, where the People are not obliged, 
unless they find it for their own Interest, or Conveniency, 
to receive any Monies, except of their own Coynage by a 
publick Mint, after the manner of all Civilized Nations. </p>
            <p>The Fourteenth, is a Disposition of the People of a 
Country to wear their own Manufactures, and Import as few 
Incitements to Luxury, either in Cloaths, Furniture, Food or 
Drink, as they possibly can live conveniently without. </p>
            <p>There are many other Causes of a Nation's thriving, which 
I cannot at present recollect; but without Advantage from at 
least some of these, after turning my Thoughts a long time, 
I am not able to discover from whence our Wealth proceeds, 
and therefore would gladly be better informed. In the mean 
time, I will here examine what share falls to Ireland of 
these Causes, or of the Effects and Consequences. </p>
            <p>It is not my Intention to complain, but barely to relate 
Facts, and the matter is not of small Importance. For it is 
allowed, that a Man who lives in a Solitary House far from 
help, is not Wise in endeavouring to acquire in the 
Neighbourhood, the Reputation of being Rich, because those 
who come for Gold, will go off with Pewter and Brass, rather 
than return empty; and in the common Practice of the World, 
those who possess most Wealth, make the least Parade, which 
they leave to others, who have nothing else to bear them 
out, in shewing their Faces on the Exchange. </p>
            <p>As to the first Cause of a Nation's Riches, being the 
Fertility of the Soyl, as well as Temperature of Clymate, we 
have no Reason to complain; for although the Quantity of 
unprofitable Land in this Kingdom, reckoning Bog, and Rock, 
and barren Mountain, be double in Proportion to what it is 
in England, yet the Native Productions which both Kingdoms 
deal in, are very near on equality in point of Goodness, and 
might with the same Encouragement be as well manufactured. I 
except Mines and Minerals, in some of which however we are 
only defective in point of Skill and Industry. </p>
            <p>In the Second, which is the Industry of the People, our 
misfortune is not altogether owing to our own Fault, but to 
a million of Discouragements. </p>
            <p>The conveniency of Ports and Havens which Nature bestowed 
us so liberally is of no more use to us, than a beautiful 
Prospect to a Man shut up in a Dungeon. </p>
            <p>As to Shipping of it's own, this Kingdom is so utterly 
unprovided, that of all the excellent Timber cut down within 
these fifty or sixty Years, it can hardly be said that the 
Nation hath received the Benefit of one valuable House to 
dwell in, or one Ship to Trade with. </p>
            <p>Ireland is the only Kingdom I ever heard or read of, 
either in ancient or modern Story, which was denyed the 
Liberty of exporting their native Commodities and 
Manufactures wherever they pleased, except to Countries at 
War with their own Prince or State, yet this by the 
Superiority of meer Power is refused us in the most 
momentous parts of Commerce, besides an Act of Navigation to 
which we never consented, pinned down upon us, and 
rigorously executed, and a thousand other unexampled 
Circumstances as grievous as they are invidious to mention. 
To go unto the Rest. </p>
            <p>It is too well known that we are forced to obey some Laws 
we never consented to, which is a Condition I must not call 
by it's true uncontroverted Name, for fear of my L-- C-- J-- 
W--'s Ghost with his LIBERTAS ET NATALE SOLUM, written as a 
Motto on his Coach, as it stood at the Door of the Court, 
while he was Perjuring himself to betray both. Thus, we are 
in the Condition of Patients who have Physick sent them by 
Doctors at a Distance, Strangers to their Constitution, and 
the nature of their Disease: And thus, we are forced to pay 
five hundred per Cent to decide our Properties, in all which 
we have likewise the Honour to be distinguished from the 
whole Race of Mankind. </p>
            <p>As to improvement of Land, those few who attempt that or 
Planting, through Covetousness or want of Skill, generally 
leave things worse than they were, neither succeeding in 
Trees nor Hedges, and by running into the fancy of Grazing 
after the manner of the Scythians, are every Day 
depopulating the Country. </p>
            <p>We are so far from having a King to reside among us, that 
even the Viceroy is generally absent four Fifths of his time 
in the Government. </p>
            <p>No Strangers from other Countries make this a part of 
their Travels, where they can expect to see nothing but 
Scenes of Misery and Desolation. </p>
            <p>Those who have the Misfortune to be born here, have the 
least Title to any considerable Employment, to which they 
are seldom preferred, but upon a Political Consideration. </p>
            <p>One third part of the Rents of Ireland is spent in 
England, which with the Profit of Employments, Pensions, 
Appeals, Journeys of Pleasure or Health, Education at the 
Inns of Court, and both Universities, Remittances at 
Pleasure, the Pay of all Superior Officers in the Army and 
other Incidents, will amount to a full half of the Income of 
the whole Kingdom, all clear profit to England. </p>
            <p>We are denyed the Liberty of Coining Gold, Silver, or 
even Copper. In the Isle of Man, they Coin their own Silver; 
every petty Prince, Vassal to the Emperor can Coin what 
Money he pleaseth. And in this as in most of the Articles 
already mentioned, we are an exception to all other States 
or Monarchies that were ever known in the World. </p>
            <p>As to the last, or Fourteenth Article, we take special 
Care to Act diametrically contrary to it in the whole Course 
of our Lives. Both Sexes, but especially the Women despise 
and abhor to wear any of their own Manufactures, even those 
which are better made than in other Countries, particularly 
a sort of Silk Plad, through which the Workmen are forced to 
run a sort of Gold-thread that it may pass for Indian. Even 
Ale and Potatoes in great quantity are Imported from England 
as well as Corn, and our foreign Trade is little more than 
Importation of French Wine, for which I am told we pay ready 
Money. </p>
            <p>Now if all this be true, upon which I could easily 
enlarge, I would be glad to know by what secret method it is 
that we grow a Rich and Flourishing People, without Liberty, 
Trade, Manufactures, Inhabitants, Money, or the privilege of 
Coining; without Industry, Labour or Improvement of Lands, 
and with more than half of the Rent and Profits of the whole 
Kingdom, Annually exported, for which we receive not a 
single Farthing: And to make up all this, nothing worth 
mentioning, except the Linnen of the North, a Trade casual, 
corrupted and at Mercy, and some Butter from Cork. If we do 
flourish, it must be against every Law of Nature and Reason, 
like the Thorn at Glassenbury, that blossoms in the midst of 
Winter. </p>
            <p>Let the worthy C------rs who come from England ride round 
the Kingdom, and observe the face of Nature, or the faces of 
the Natives, the Improvement of the Land, the thriving 
numerous Plantations, the noble Woods, the abundance and 
vicinity of Country-Seats, the commodious Farmers-Houses and 
Barns, the Towns and Villages, where every body is busy and 
thriving with all kind of Manufactures, the Shops full of 
Goods wrought to Perfection, and filled with Customers, the 
comfortable Dyet and Dress, and Dwellings of the People, the 
vast Numbers of Ships in our Harbours and Docks, and 
Shipwrights in our Seaport-Towns, the Roads crouded with 
Carryers laden with rich Manufactures, the perpetual 
Concourse to and fro of pompous Equipages. </p>
            <p>With what Envy and Admiration would these Gentlemen 
return from so delightful a Progress? What glorious Reports 
would they make when they went back to England? </p>
            <p>But my Heart is too heavy to continue this Irony longer, 
for it is manifest that whatever Stranger took such a 
Journey, would be apt to think himself travelling in Lapland 
or Ysland, rather than in a Country so favoured by Nature as 
Ours, both in Fruitfulness of Soyl, and Temperature of 
Climate. The miserable Dress, and Dyet, and Dwelling of the 
People. The general Desolation in most parts of the Kingdom. 
The old Seats of the Nobility and Gentry all in Ruins, and 
no new Ones in their stead. The Families of Farmers who pay 
great Rents, living in Filth and Nastiness upon Butter-milk 
and Potatoes, without a Shoe or Stocking to their Feet, or a 
House so convenient as an English Hog-sty to receive them. 
These indeed may be comfortable sights to an English 
Spectator, who comes for a short time only to learn the 
Language, and returns back to his own Country, whither he 
finds all our Wealth transmitted. </p>
            <p>                  Nostr[acirc ] miseri[acirc ] magnus es. </p>
            <p>There is not one Argument used to prove the Riches of 
Ireland, which is not a logical Demonstration of it's 
Poverty. The Rise of our Rents is squeesed out of the very 
Blood and Vitals, and Cloaths, and Dwellings of the Tenants, 
who live worse than English Beggars. The lowness of 
Interest, in all other Countries a sign of Wealth, is in us 
a proof of misery, there being no Trade to employ any 
Borrower. Hence alone comes the Dearness of Land, since the 
Savers have no other way to lay out their Money. Hence the 
Dearness of Necessaries for Life, because the Tenants cannot 
afford to pay such extravagant Rates for Land (which they 
must take, or go a begging) without raising the Price of 
Cattle, and of Corn, although themselves should live upon 
Chaff. Hence our encrease of Buildings in this City, because 
Workmen have nothing to do but employ one another, and one 
half of them are infallibly undone. Hence the daily encrease 
of Bankers, who may be a necessary Evil in a Trading-
Country, but so ruinous in Ours, who for their private 
Advantage have sent away all our Silver, and one third of 
our Gold; so that within three Years past, the running Cash 
of the Nation, which was about Five hundred thousand Pounds, 
is now less than two, and must daily diminish unless we have 
Liberty to Coin, as well as that important Kingdom the Isle 
of Man, and the meanest Prince in the German Empire, as I 
before observed. </p>
            <p>I have sometimes thought, that this Paradox of the 
Kingdom growing Rich, is chiefly owing to those worthy 
Gentlemen the BANKERS, who, except some Custom-house 
Officers, Birds of Passage, oppressive thrifty 'Squires, and 
a few others that shall be Nameless, are the only thriving 
People among us: And I have often wished that a Law were 
enacted to hang up half a Dozen Bankers every Year, and 
thereby interpose at least some short Delay, to the further 
Ruin of Ireland. </p>
            <p>Ye are idle, ye are idle, answered Pharoah to the 
Isrælites, when they complained to his MAJESTY, that they 
were forced to make Bricks without Straw. </p>
            <p>England enjoys every one of these Advantages for 
enriching a Nation, which I have above enumerated, and into 
the Bargain, a good Million returned to them every Year 
without Labour or Hazard, or one Farthing value received on 
our side. But how long we shall be able to continue the 
payment, I am not under the least Concern. One thing I know, 
that when the Hen is starved to Death, there will be no more 
Golden Eggs. </p>
            <p>I think it a little unhospitable, and others may call it 
a subtil piece of Malice, that, because there may be a Dozen 
Families in this Town able to entertain their English 
Friends in a generous manner at their Tables, their Guests 
upon their Return to England, shall report that we wallow in 
Riches and Luxury. </p>
            <p>Yet I confess I have known an Hospital, where all the 
Household-Officers grew Rich, while the Poor for whose sake 
it was built, were almost starving for want of Food and 
Raiment. </p>
            <p>To Conclude. If Ireland be a rich and flourishing 
Kingdom, it's Wealth and Prosperity must be owing to certain 
Causes, that are yet concealed from the whole Race of 
Mankind, and the Effects are equally Invisible. We need not 
wonder at Strangers when they deliver such Paradoxes, but a 
Native and Inhabitant of this Kingdom, who gives the same 
Verdict, must be either ignorant to Stupidity, or a Man-
pleaser at the Expence of all Honour, Conscience and Truth.    </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XVI" type="article">
            <head>Article XVI</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">
                  <l>Sed virum ver[acirc ] virtute vivere animatum addecet, </l>
                  <l>Fortiterq; innoxium vacare adversum adversarios. Enn:</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Mr. Intelligencer.  </p>
            <p>IT may appear to you perhaps a thing very unnatural, to 
receive a Complaint from a Son against his Father, but the 
treatment, which I meet with from mine, is of such a Nature, 
that it is impossible for me not to complain. </p>
            <p>You must know there are three Brethren of us, George, 
Patrick, and Andrew; I am the second, but the last in 
Affection with my Father, for which I call Heaven and Earth 
to Witness, I never committed any Fault to incur his 
displeasure, or to deserve his neglect. But so it is, that 
the best of Men have oftentimes been misled in the choice of 
their Minions, and very undiscerning in conferring their 
favours where they ought. </p>
            <p>If Parents could but once bring themselves to be 
impartial, it would beyond all doubt, produce a delightful 
Union in their Children, and be the most binding Cement, 
that could be thought of, to preserve their Affections, 
because an equal Dispensation of favours would entirely 
remove all cause of murmuring, repining, or envy. And, what 
is of the greatest Consequence, would secure the love and 
esteem of their Children; whereas a partial behaviour in 
Parents, must necessarily produce the contrary. </p>
            <p>But to State my Case, in the best manner I can, and with 
an unbiassed regard to Truth, I think it first necessary to 
give you our Characters, with an Account of my Father's 
behaviour, that you may be the better able to give me your 
Advice. </p>
            <p>First then, to begin with my Brother George. He was ever 
a great lover of his Belly, and formerly used to Cram 
himself with Beef, Pudding, and White-pot, but for some time 
past, he has taken more delight in New-fangled Toss-ups, and 
French Kick-shaws. This high Feeding does naturally dispose 
him to be Haughty, Stuborn, Cholerick and Rebellious, 
insomuch, that beside his insults towards others, he is 
ready, upon all occasions, to fly in his own Father's Face, 
and apt to despise every Body, but himself. </p>
            <p>He is so various in his Opinions, that he is of as many 
Religions, as there are and have been Sects, since the 
beginning of Christianity; but the True and Reformed Church, 
as by Law Established, is what he chiefly frequents. He was 
once a great Admirer of Ancient Learning, but he has long 
since quitted this, for the Reading of News-Papers, 
Pamphlets, and Modern Languages. In his younger Years, he 
was fond of Manly Exercises, such as Fencing, Leaping, 
Boxing, Pitching the Bar, Wrestling, Hurling, Foot-ball, 
Hunting, &amp;c. But of late he has faln into a strange and 
unaccountable Effeminacy, and seems to take delight in 
nothing, but Masquerades, Plays, and Italian Operas. He is 
very fond of Italian Magnificent Buildings, although 
entirely inconsistent with our Climate, extravagant in the 
highest degree, in purchasing fine Paintings, and Statues, 
and no less expensive in vast extensive Parks and Gardens, 
by which means, he has almost run out all his Fortune. </p>
            <p>My youngest Brother Andrew, who has cunning enough to 
outwit the Devil, joyned with Brother George some Years ago, 
and they manage so dextrously together, that whatever they 
say is a Law with my Father; however, they are not without 
their Quarrels now and then, but Brother Andrew still comes 
by the worst, although he is cautious enough, to go always 
armed; for Brother George wears a longer Sword. Brother 
Andrew is not very nice in his Food, but loves fine Cloaths. 
This I suppose he has learned abroad; for he is a great 
Traveller. His chief Studies are Mathematicks, and the 
Civil-law, in both which he has made a considerable 
Progress. As for his Religion, although he openly professes 
himself a most Rigid Fanatick of the Kirk, yet he is 
shrewdly suspected, to have a hankering after Popery. He has 
one eminent bad Quality, which is, that he cannot easily 
forgive and forget. I remember I was once so unfortunate, as 
to tell a fair Lady, (a Mistress of mine) before his Face, 
that I would stand by her against him, and all her other 
Adversaries, which he took hainously ill, and has not 
forgiven me to this hour, but lies upon the Watch, to do me 
all the ill Offices he can. </p>
            <p>I come now to my own Character, in which I shall not 
Conceal, nor Gloss over my Vices, Errors, or Failings, but 
at the same time, I shall not think it inconsistent with 
Modesty, to tell you my Virtues. </p>
            <p>I have but a small Fortune, can hardly keep Soul and Body 
together, yet out of a regard to my Family, which is very 
Ancient, I love to make what they call a Figure, upon 
extraordinary occasions. And now and then I furnish my Table 
with Victuals, and Liquors of the best kinds, which makes my 
Father, and Brother George, think I have got the World in a 
String. I am kind and hospitable to Strangers, although they 
frequently Rob my House, and turn my Children to ly in the 
Barn. </p>
            <p>I am so fond of Learning, that I put them to the best 
School in the Kingdom, and I plainly see they will be only 
the wiser, but never the richer for it, because my Father 
uses all his Interest for brother Georges Sons, and the 
greatest Dunce among them shall be better provided for, than 
the most Ingenious of mine. And I must say I have some who 
are equal in Learning to the best of his. I had a designe 
once, to follow Merchandise; that I might be the better able 
to Provide for my Poor Children, but Brother George having a 
mind to make a Monopoly, prevailed upon my Father, to join 
against me, and so at last they contrived it, that I should 
sell nothing but a few of my Catle, and some Linnen Cloath, 
which is all the Support I have; Whereas brother George can 
Sell every thing he has, all the World over. And so cruel is 
he to me, that he will not let me have even a bit of his 
dirt, if he thinks it will be of any advantage to me. My 
Religion is of three Sorts, The Established, Popish and 
Presbyterian, but I have a greater Share of the First in me. 
I think it is best, because it encourages obedience to my 
Father, more than either of the other two. It is not long 
since Brother George, and Andrew, were in a confederacy 
against my Father, with an Intent to turn him out of his 
House, and give another the Possession, at which critical 
Juncture, I mustered up a great Number of my Sons, and 
Servants, to his Assistance, and for ought I know saved both 
his Life, and Fortune. </p>
            <p>Soon after this, I had like to have been ruined by a 
Project; for one of my Brother George's Family endeavoured 
to perswade my Father, that Gold, and Silver, were of no use 
to me, and desired leave to furnish me with a few Counters, 
in lieu thereof, and I fear I should have been so Weak, as 
to accept of them, had it not been for the Seasonable 
Remonstrances, made by Some of my own House. </p>
            <p>These are a fewe of the many Hardships I have suffered, 
notwithstanding all which, I am willing to continue a 
Passive Obedience, to my Dear Father; for I have Reason to 
believe, that his unkindness to me is owing to ill Advisers, 
who have prejudiced him against me, and my Children; but I 
Hope, before long, he will be able to distinguish his most 
faithful Son. In the mean time, I do humbly entreat the 
Favour of you to Write a Letter to my Father, which he may 
See in Print, for I Fear all my Letters to him hitherto have 
been Intercepted.  </p>
            <p>SIR, YOU have not told me your Father's Name, nor his 
Quality, and therefore I am at a loss in what manner I 
should Address him. But in common Humanity (because I think 
your case deplorable) I will give you what Comfort I am 
able, together with my best Advice. </p>
            <p>You are not the only Instance of Suffering Innocence, and 
therefore it ought not to Surprize you that Providence (for 
reasons unaccountable to us) has laid two great Tryals in 
your way, Oppression from your Brethern, and Unkindness from 
your Father, this too without any Fault on your Side. If you 
did not meet with these Afflictions, you would want an 
Opportunity of shewing your Humility, and Resignation, as I 
understand you do not by your Letter. </p>
            <p>Let me Advise you, to consider that your Condition is not 
quite so Lamentable, as that of Joseph, who triumphed in 
GOD's own time over all his Misfortunes, and sufferings, and 
at last had the pleasure of doing good, even to his 
Persecutors; but indeed there is this Difference, that his 
grievance was chiefly from his Brethern; for had his Father 
joined in the Cruelty, the Wounds would have Pierced nearer 
to his Heart. </p>
            <p>I do not in the least doubt, but there are some about 
your Father, who do you ill Offices, (I hope some time or 
other they will be detected). You may find a convenient 
Oportunity of getting fairly at him. State your Case and 
expostulate with him concerning your own and your Children's 
Sufferings. When he hears your Story, and beholds your 
Sincerity, you may be sure of his Compassion, and a Redress; 
for there is no Heart so hard as not to Sympathize with real 
Woe, no Advocate so Powerful, as Innocence. In the mean 
time, let me Conjure you, not to turn aside to the Right or 
to the Left, from that indispensable Duty, which the express 
Laws of GOD enjoin you, for let me assure you, that 
Ingratitude to a Parent is, no less than Rebellion, like the 
Sin of Witchcraft. </p>
            <p>I Commit you to his Care and Direction, who is best able 
to Govern the unruly affections of Men, to turn the Hearts 
of the Malicious, and to Relieve and Support those who 
suffer for the Sake of Righteousness.  </p>
            <l>I am your faithful Friend; </l>
            <l>	The Intelligencer.     </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XVII" type="article">
            <head>Article XVII</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">
                  <l>Quantum stagna Tagi rudibus stillantia venis </l>
                  <l>Effluxere decus! quanto pretiosa metallo </l>
                  <l>Hermi ripa micat; quantas per Lydia culta </l>
                  <l>Despumat rutilas dives Pactolus arenas. 
<bibl>
                        <author>	Claudian.</author>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Mr. Intelligencer, </p>
            <p>HAVING lately, with great Candor, and Impartiality, 
perused some of your Papers, upon the Distress and Poverty 
of this Island, which you take care to describe in the most 
Pathetick manner, you must forgive me if I differ from you, 
and think it one of the most Flourishing and Wealthy 
Kingdoms in the whole world, and to support my Opinion, I 
will venture to affirm, that there never was such Affluence 
of ready Cash, as at this present juncture; For have we not 
more Bankers than ever were known among us? And whether the 
Money Circulates in Specie, or Paper, it is the same thing 
to us, since those, who would rather have Cash than Paper, 
can (as is well known) have their choice, whenever they 
please. It is to be presumed that no Banker gives a NOTE 
before the Money is first laid down on his Counter; then of 
Consequence there is as much Money, as there is Paper, and 
that we have a great deal of Paper is most certain, 
therefore a great deal of Money. But I will proceed farther, 
and prove that we have much more Money than Paper, because 
there are Multitudes who keep their own Money. This appears 
from the great number of Iron-chests imported from Holland, 
within these last seven Years; For what use can they be of, 
but to lodge Money. They are at least two hundred. We will 
suppose, that these, one with another, may contain two 
thousand pounds a piece, then the Sum total, amounts to Four 
hundred thousand pounds, which is so much Superfluous, and 
unnecessary Cash. </p>
            <p>If this Island were not very Wealthy, it is strongly to 
be presumed, That so many Wise and Able Heads, Men of great 
Learning and Superior Talents, whose Reputations reacht us 
from distant Regions, long before they came among us, so 
well distinguished in their own Countries for their great 
Knowledge, in their several professions, and here more 
especially; remarkable for their speaking in publick, and 
their profound Skill in Religion, Politicks, and Law; I say 
that Men of such Accomplishments would never quit their own 
Native Soil, where so many great Estates are daily made, if 
they were not sure that this Island must, on Account of its 
greater Wealth, Afford them Opportunities of making larger 
Acquisitions, than they could at home. </p>
            <p>Have not almost all the Gentlemen through this Kingdom, 
for some years past, declined all profitable Employments, 
and left them to be filled by others. Can there be a 
stronger Argument of their Wealth, than their choosing to 
live at their ease, out of Office, rather than be at the 
small trouble, which attends the discharge of a beneficial 
Employment? </p>
            <p>Could so many Estated Gentlemen, through the North of 
Ireland, afford to keep so much of their Lands waste, and 
untenanted, if they had not Money enough by them, to live 
without Tenants, and would not the Tenants likewise be glad, 
to take this Waste Land to Plow, and Sow, but that they have 
ready money enough to buy Bread Corn, and other Necessaries, 
from all the World beside. </p>
            <p>As another signal mark of our Riches, there is Scarce a 
Gentleman, who does not educate his Sons at our UNIVERSITY 
(which as the World sees, wants not it's due Encouragement) 
where they live at vast Expences, take Degrees, return to 
their Fathers, who without ever troubling Law, or Gospel, 
maintain them afterwards at Home, like Gentlemen. </p>
            <p>Do not many of our Nobility through Wantonness, and 
superfluity, reside constantly in another Kingdom, where, it 
is well known, they make a better Figure, as to Houses, 
Coaches, and Equipages, than their Neighbours? And do not 
our young Peers, and Gentry, who go thither to see the 
World, Game, Race, Drink, &amp;c. beyond any in Great-
Brittain, of the same Age, and Quality, which they could not 
Possibly do, if their Agents here had not an undrainable 
fund, to suply them? for as the Philosopher says, Nemo dat 
quod non habet. Or as the Jugler very Elegantly expresses 
it, Where nothing is, there nothing can come out. </p>
            <p>If it be true, (I know it is confidently Reported) that a 
great Number of English Robbers are come over, that likewise 
is a very strong Argument of our Wealth; for they would 
never quit the English Streets, and Roads, for ours, unless 
they were sure to find an Advantage by the Change. It is 
most certain we never had such a Number of Robbers, as at 
this very juncture; from whence we may conclude, that they 
could not Possibly Multiply thus, if they did not find 
Houses, and People enough to Rob, for all Professions and 
Trades encrease, according to the Encouragement they meet 
with. </p>
            <p>Are not whole Streets adding every Day to our Metropolis, 
when one would think it Large enough already? Some entire 
Streets and many Houses, I must confess, are waste, and 
unhabited. But does not this shew the Wealth and Wantonness 
of the Inhabitants, who not content with their present 
Dwellings, change them for others, more costly and 
expensive? </p>
            <p>Do not great Numbers of our Inhabitants, daily go off to 
America? Will any Man say this can be done with empty 
Pockets? Can any Man think otherwise, but that it must be 
the effect of vast superfluity, when People wantonly take 
such long Voyages, and Journeys, to go where they have no 
business? </p>
            <p>The last Argument I shall offer for the Wealth of this 
Kingdom, is the great Number of Beggars, in which it 
abounds; for it is a common Observation, that Riches are the 
parent of Idleness, Sloth, and Luxury, and are not these 
Naturally productive of Want and Beggary? </p>
            <p>I could offer many more Arguments, but that I hope you 
and your Country Men, are sufficiently convinced, by what I 
have said, that Ireland is a place of great Wealth, 
affluence, and Plenty. Therefore let me advise you, the next 
time you put Pen to Paper, not to dress up Hibernia in Rags, 
and Dirt, but cloath her in Scarlet, and fine Linen; for she 
can very well afford them. Draw the God of Riches, hovering 
over your Island, shaking Ten Thousands of Golden Feathers 
from his Wings, much more than the Inhabitants can gather, 
and thus will your Country Men, who have retrenched upon 
your last groundless Alarm, return to their former 
Hospitality, and we shall see Halcyon, that is, Irish Days 
once more.  </p>
            <p>SIR, I Have perused your Arguments, and thus I Answer 
them. You were certainly fast asleep, and Writ them all in 
your Dream, nor do I in the least doubt, when you awake from 
your Golden Slumber, but you will find your self as much 
mistaken, as the Man in [AElig ]sop, who Dreamed the Devil 
shewed him a Treasure. I wish you may not Likewise, be in 
the same pickle, and prove a Gold-Finder, between your own 
Sheets.  </p>
            <l>		Your's, </l>
            <l>			The Intelligencer.    </l>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XVIII" type="article">
            <head>Article XVIII</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q type="verse">
                  <l>Hic dies anno redeunte festus.</l>
               </q>
               <bibl>Hor:</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>My Dear Country-Men, </p>
            <p>IT has been the Custom of all wise Nations, not only to 
confer immediate honours upon their Benefactors, but 
likewise to distinguish their Birth-Days, by Anniversary 
rejoycings.  This was a most generous Institution, to 
transmit those Heroes to posterity, who gloriously 
signalized themselves, in the Defence of their Country, that 
others, being Spirited up by their Example, might endeavour 
to deserve the same Encouragement.  It is for this reason, 
that I recommend Saint Andrew's-Day unto you, to be 
Celebrated in a most Particular manner, being (as I am very 
well informed) the DRAPIER's Birth-Day. But before I shall 
make out the great Obligations, we have to him, I think it 
first necessary, to relate unto you a passage, untoucht upon 
before, by those who Writ against Wood's Half-pence, which I 
have read in an English Historian of great probity, and 
Truth. </p>
            <p>His Name is Fines Morrison.  He was Secretary of State to 
the Lord Monjoy, our chief Governour, in the Reign of Queen 
Elizabeth, and therefore had the best oportunity, of knowing 
the State of this Nation at that time.  He tells you that 
the Queen, had received an Account of the Irish being up in 
Arms (though to speak the truth it was the English, rather; 
for the Giraldies, the Tools, the Cavanaghs, and the Byrns 
who were the Ring-leaders, were all of English Extraction.)  
She called a Council, where after several Schemes had been 
proposed, for reducing the Rebels, it was at last agreed 
upon, as the best expedient, to make a base Coin current 
among them; for this it was thought would quickly Subdue 
their stuborn Spirits, by introducing Poverty, the great 
humbler of Families and Nations. </p>
            <p>Accordingly this expedient was set on Foot, and it had 
the intended Effect; for the Merchants, who generally 
Speaking, consider nothing but their own private advantage, 
imported vast Sums of this base Coin, every hundred Pounds 
of which stood them not in above Forty, for so they bought 
it from the Dutch, who thrust their cloven Foot into all 
affairs.  This being discovered, the Rates of things were 
raised to Ten times their value, the middle Rank of People 
were all ruined by it, and the Poor, through this whole 
Kingdom, reduced to Famine, in so much, that all the publick 
Roads were strowed with Dead Carcases of miserable Wretches, 
whose Mouths were Green (as the Author expresses it) with 
their last meal of Grass. </p>
            <p>He likewise gives a Relation, of a very horrible Fact; 
too horrible indeed to mention! That a poor Widow of Newry, 
having six small Children, and no food to support them, shut 
up her Doors, Died through despair, and in about three or 
four Days after, her Children were found Eating her Flesh.  
He says farther, That at the same time, a discovery being 
made of Twelve Women, who made a practice of stealing 
Children, to Eat them, they were all burned, by order of Sir 
Arthur Chichester, then Governour of the North of Ireland.  
He likewise tells us, that the poor Butchers, and other 
Trades-men, who could not afford to part with their goods, 
at such Rates as the Army would have them, were daily 
Dragooned by them.  That the poor Soldiers were also ruined, 
for not being able to Buy their Cloathing here, they were 
obliged to be supplyed from England, at double Rates. </p>
            <p>After many more Evils enumerated, the good Natured, and 
Compassionate Author, who all along deplores the miserable 
Condition of the poor Natives, tells us, their Case was 
Represented in such deplorable Circumstances, that the Queen 
quickly recalled her Grant, and put a stop to the base Coin.  
And he concludes one Paragraph thus (as well as I can 
remember.) </p>
            <p>We her Majesty's Officers, who thought to make our 
Fortunes by our Employments, lost what we had, and we lost 
our Hearts therewith. </p>
            <p>I have now finished my Melancholy extract, from whence I 
shall infer, that as like Causes ever have, and ever must 
produce like Effects, that Villainous Project of William 
Wood, might have intirely ruined this Kingdom, and have 
Converted it, into one large Poor House, had not the DRAPIER 
(whom I shall honour while I live) prevented that by his 
PEN, which perhaps Twenty thousand Swords, could not have 
done.  Some very great Men, whose Names I am loath to 
Mention, were so Angry with the DRAPIER, for saving his 
Country, and disobliging their Friend William Wood, that 
they orderd a good Sum of Mony, as a reward to any one, who 
should discover which of the Town DRAPIER's, it was, that 
durst be so Impudent, and had it been found out, it is 
highly probable, they would have Seized all the Goods in his 
Shop, and have Imprisoned, and Pillored him into the 
Bargain, to make him an example to all PATRIOTS. </p>
            <p>Consider then my dear Country Men, the hazard, which this 
Noble Spirited DRAPIER did run for your Sakes. How like the 
old Heroe Camillus, he flew in suddainly to our Rescue, when 
Wood's Half-pence were like the Brazen Bucklers, thrown into 
the opposite Scale, by our Enemies, to fill their Pockets 
more plentifully, with our Gold, and Silver.  That he has 
done his best endeavour, to save us from Poverty and 
Slavery, and consequently has the strongest Title, to our 
Gratitude. </p>
            <p>Let us not Act then, in a Christian Country, like the 
Barbarous Heathens, who frequently, when their greatest 
Deliverances were wrought, either Slighted, or banished, or 
Poisoned, or Murthered the Benefactors, or the Heroes, or 
reduced them to the Necessity, of Dying by their own Hands. </p>
            <p>So fell the great Patriots Demosthenes, Cicero, Socrates, 
Phocion, Themistocles; And Dion of Syracuse, who was most 
inhumanly given up, to be Butchered by some Zacynthian 
Ruffians, after he had recovered the ungrateful Sicilians 
their freedom. </p>
            <p>We ought likewise to consider, that we may possibly stand 
in need of a DRAPIER's Assistance another Time. </p>
            <p>And it must be an uncommon strain of Virtue in any Man, 
to serve those People, who will not at least offer him their 
thanks, or own their Obligation to him. </p>
            <p>What makes the Soldier, and Consecrates the Heroe, but 
Rewards, and Honours! </p>
            <p>Let a Prince be ever so great a Soldier himself, if he 
fails in this single point, of giving Valour its due 
Encouragement, he will find his Soldiers but very slack in 
their Duty, and full as loose in their Loyalty. </p>
            <p>It is even so in all other Professions; let Men pretend 
what they will, as to Conscience, and Duty, they are but 
Hypocrites, when they say, they Act with a View to these 
alone.  Proper Encouragements have ever been expected, by 
the best of Men, and it is very just, they should have their 
due, as well as Cæsar. </p>
            <p>I dare venture to engage for the DRAPIER, that he expects 
no more, for his great Services, but that Love, and Regard, 
that Respect and Esteem, which every Irish Man, who has any 
Virtue left, ought to have, for so great a Benefactor.  I 
have my self, one way, or other, five hundred Pounds a Year, 
and I am certain, I make the Computation in my own Favour, 
when I say, that I owe him four hundred and fifty pounds per 
Annum.  Let others in Proportion to their Fortune, make Use 
of the same Arithmetick, how much will the Nation owe him! </p>
            <p>And can any one, after this, refuse a few Complements to 
his BIRTH-DAY, when Furze, and Candles, are so cheap, and 
considering that our Houses can never be better adorned, 
than by Illuminations, in respect to those, who enable us to 
keep them? </p>
            <p>I wish, my dear Country-Men, I could cast a Veil over one 
piece of Ingratitude, which you have been Guilty of, to one 
of your Deliverers; I mean to the Great and Glorious King 
William, that for two Years past, you have laid aside his 
Anniversary-Dinner at the Tholsel, forgetting that he did 
not only, save us from Popery and Slavery, but did in a very 
Particular manner, Distinguish, and Reward the Gentlemen of 
this Kingdom, both of the Gown and the Sword, and made the 
People in general, so much his peculiar Care, that there was 
no complaining in our Streets. </p>
            <p>I would not here be understood, to approve of that 
Bumper-Loyalty, of getting Drunk to the Memory of the Dead, 
but to have an Annual meeting, to shew a decent Respect for 
those, who have been our True Friends, and Benefactors, 
either Living, or Dead, and to exclude all others, who are 
not so, even from our flattery.  </p>
            <p>POSTSCRIPT. I do make it my Request, that the Widdow, the 
PRINTER of these Papers, who did likewise Print the 
DRAPIER's Letters, may be enabled by Charitable 
Encouragements to keep a merry Christmass; for She, and her 
Family, were ruined by Iniquitous Imprisonments, and 
hardships, for Printing those Papers, which were to the 
Advantage of this Kingdom in General.    </p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div n="XIX" type="article">
            <head>Article XIX</head>
            <opener>Having on the 12th of October last, receiv'd a 
LETTER Sign'd <lb/>
Andrew Dealer, and Patrick Pennyless; I believe the 
following <lb/>
PAPER, just come to my Hands, will be a sufficient Answer 
to <lb/>
it.  <lb/>
  	        Sic vos non vobis vellera fertis oves. <lb/>
					Virg.</opener>
            <salute>SIR, </salute>
            <p>I Am a Country Gentleman, and a Member of Parliament, 
with an Estate of about 1400 l. a Year, which as a Northern 
Landlord, I receive from above two Hundred Tenants, and my 
Lands having been Let, near twenty Years ago, the Rents, 
till very lately, were esteemed to be not above half Value; 
yet by the intolerable Scarcity of Silver, I lye under the 
greatest Difficulties in receiving them, as well as in 
paying my Labourers, or buying any thing necessary for my 
Family from Tradesmen, who are not able to be long out of 
their Money. But the sufferings of me, and those of my Rank, 
are Trifles in Comparison, of what the meaner sort undergo; 
such as the Buyers and Sellers, at Fairs, and Markets; The 
Shop-keepers in every Town, the Farmers in general. All 
those who Travel with Fish, Poultry, Pedlary-Ware, and other 
Conveniencies to sell: But more especially Handy-crafts-men, 
who Work for us by the Day, and common Labourers, whom I 
have already mentioned. Both these kinds of People, I am 
forced to employ, till their Wages amount to a Double 
Pistole, or a Moydore, (for we hardly have any Gold of lower 
Value left among us) to divide it among themselves as they 
can; and this is generally done at an Ale-house or Brandy 
shop; where, besides the cost of getting Drunk, (which is 
usually the Case) they must pay ten pence or a Shilling, for 
changing their Piece into Silver, to some Huckstering-
fellow, who follows that Trade. But what is infinitely 
worse, those Poor Men for want of due Payment, are forced to 
take up their Oat-meal, and other Necessaries of Life, at 
almost double Value, and consequently are not able, to 
discharge half their score, especially under the scarceness 
of Corn, for two Years past, and the Melancholy 
disappointment of the present Crop. </p>
            <p>The Causes of this, and a thousand other Evils, are clear 
and manifest to you and all other Thinking Men, though 
hidden from the Vulgar: These indeed complain of hard Times, 
the Dearth of Corn, the want of Money, the badness of 
Seasons; that their Goods bear no Price, and the poor cannot 
find Work; but their weak reasonings never carry them to the 
Hatred, and Contempt, born us by our Neighbours, and 
Brethren, without the least grounds of Provocation, who 
rejoice at our Sufferings, although sometimes to their own 
Disadvantage; of the dead Weight upon every beneficial 
Branch of our Trade; of half our Revenues sent annually to 
England, and many other Grievances peculiar to this unhappy 
Kingdom, excepted for our Sins, which keeps us from enjoying 
the common Benefits of Mankind, as you and some other Lovers 
of their Country, have so often observed, with such good 
Inclinations, and so little Effect. </p>
            <p>It is true indeed, that under our Circumstances in 
general, this Complaint for the want of Silver, may appear 
as Ridiculous, as for a Man to be impatient, about a Cut 
Finger, when he is struck with the Plague, and yet a poor 
Fellow going to the Gallows, may be allow'd to feel the 
smart of Wasps, while he is upon Tyburn Road. This 
misfortune is too urging, and vexatious in every kind of 
small Traffick, and so hourly pressing upon all Persons in 
the Country whatsoever, that a hundred inconveniences, of 
perhaps greater Moment in themselves, have been timely 
submitted to, with far less disquietude and murmurs. And the 
Case seems yet the harder, if it be true, what many skilfull 
Men assert, that nothing is more easy, than a Remedy; and, 
that the Want of Silver, in proportion to the little Gold 
remaining among us, is altogether as unnecessary, as it is 
inconvenient. A Person of Distinction assured me very 
lately, that, in discoursing with the Lord Lieutenant, 
before his last Return to England, His Excellency said, He 
had pressed the matter often, in proper Time and Place, and 
to proper Persons; and could not see any difficulty of the 
least Moment, that could prevent us from being easy upon 
that Article. </p>
            <p>Whoever carrys to England, twenty seven English 
Shillings, and brings back one Moydore, of full Weight, is a 
gainer of nine pence Irish; In a Guinea, the Advantage is 
three pence, and two pence in a Pistole. The BANKERS, who 
are generally Masters of all our Gold, and Silver, with this 
Advantage, have sent over as much of the latter, as came 
into their Hands. The Value of one thousand Moydores in 
Silver, would thus amount in clear profit, to 37 l. 10 s. 
The Shop-keepers, and other Traders, who go to London to buy 
Goods, followed the same Practice, by which we have been 
driven into this insupportable Distress. </p>
            <p>To a common Thinker, it should seem, that nothing would 
be more easy, than for the Government to Redress this Evil, 
at any time they shall please. When the value of Guineas was 
lowred in England, from 21 s. 6 d. to only 21 s. the 
Consequences to this Kingdom, were obvious, and manifest to 
us all; and a sober Man, may be allowed at least to wonder, 
though he dare not complain, why a new Regulation of Coin 
among us, was not then made; much more, why it hath never 
been since. It would surely require no very profound skill 
in Algebra, to reduce the difference of nine Pence in thirty 
Shillings, or three Pence in a Guinea, to less than a 
Farthing; And so small a Fraction could be no Temptation, 
either to Bankers, to hazard their Silver at Sea, or 
Tradesmen to load themselves with it, in their Journeys to 
England. In my humble Opinion, it would be no unseasonable 
Condescension, if the Government would Graciously please, to 
signify to the poor loyal Protestant Subjects of Ireland, 
either that this miserable want of Silver, is not possible 
to be remedy'd in any degree, by the nicest skill in 
Arithmetick; or else, that it doth not stand with the good 
pleasure of England, to suffer any Silver at all among us. 
In the former Case, it would be madness, to expect 
Impossibilities: And in the other, we must submit: For, 
Lives, and Fortunes are, always at the Mercy of the 
CONQUEROR. </p>
            <p>The Question hath been often put in printed Papers, by 
the DRAPIER, and others, or perhaps by the same WRITER, 
under different Styles, why this Kingdom should not be 
permitted to have a Mint of its own, for the Coinage of 
Gold, Silver, and Copper, which is a Power exercised by many 
Bishops, and every petty Prince in Germany. But this 
Question hath never been answered, nor the least Application 
that I have heard of, made to the Crown from hence, for the 
grant of a Publick Mint, although it stands upon Record, 
that several Cities, and Corporations here, had the Liberty 
of Coining Silver. I can see no Reasons, why we alone of all 
Nations, are thus restrained, but such as I dare not 
mention; only thus far, I may venture, that Ireland is the 
first Imperial Kingdom, since Nimrod, which ever wanted 
Power, to Coin their own Money. </p>
            <p>I know very well, that in England it is lawful for any 
Subject, to Petition either the Prince, or the Parliament, 
provided it be done in a dutiful, and regular Manner; But 
what is lawful for a Subject of Ireland, I profess I cannot 
determine; nor will undertake, that your Printer shall not 
be prosecuted, in a Court of Justice, for publishing my 
Wishes, that a poor Shop-keeper might be able to change a 
Guinea, or a Moydore, when a Customer comes for a Crown's 
worth of Goods. I have known less Crimes punished with the 
utmost Severity, under the Title of Disaffection: And, I 
cannot but approve the Wisdom of the Antients, who, after 
Astrea had fled from the Earth, at least took care to 
provide three upright Judges for Hell. Men's Ears among us, 
are indeed grown so nice, that whoever happens to think out 
of Fashion, in what relates to the Welfare of this Kingdom, 
dare not so much as complain of the Tooth-ach, lest our weak 
and busy Dablers in politick should be ready to swear 
against him for Disaffection. </p>
            <p>There was a Method practiced by Sir Ambrose Crawley, the 
great Dealer in Iron-works, which I wonder the Gentlemen of 
our Country, under this great Exigence, have not thought fit 
to imitate. In the several Towns, and Villages, where he 
dealt, and many Miles round, he gave Notes, instead of 
Money, from two Pence, to twenty Shillings, which passed 
currant in all Shops, and Markets, as well as in Houses, 
where Meat, or Drink was Sold. I see no Reason, why the like 
Practice, may not be introduced among us, with some degree 
of Success, or at least may not serve, as a poor Expedient, 
in this, our blessed age of Paper, which, as it Dischargeth 
all our greatest Payments, may be equally useful in the 
Smaller, and may just keep us alive, till an English Act of 
Parliament shall forbid it. </p>
            <p>I have been told, that among some of our poorest American 
Colonies, upon the Continent, the People enjoy the Liberty 
of cutting the little Money among them into halves, and 
quarters, for the conveniences of small Traffick. How happy 
should we be in Comparison of our present Condition, if the 
like Priviledge, were granted to us, of employing the 
Sheers, for want of a Mint, upon our foreign Gold; by 
clipping it into half Crowns, and shillings, and even lower 
Denominations; For Beggars must be content to live upon 
scraps; And it would be our Felicity, that these scraps 
would never be exported to other Countries, while any thing 
better was left. </p>
            <p>If neither of these Projects will avail, I see nothing 
left us, but to truck and barter our Goods, like the wild 
Indians, with each other, or with our too powerful 
Neighbours; only with this disadvantage on our side, that 
the Indians enjoy the Product of their own Land, whereas the 
better half of ours is sent away without so much as a 
recompence in Bugles, or Glass, in return. </p>
            <p>It must needs be a very comfortable Circumstance, in the 
present juncture, that some thousand Families are gone, or 
going, or preparing to go, from hence, and settle themselves 
in America. The poorer Sort, for want of Work, the Farmers, 
whose beneficial Bargains are now become a Rack-rent, too 
hard to be born. And those who have any ready Money, or can 
purchase any, by the Sale of their Goods, or Leases; because 
they find their Fortunes hourly decaying; that their Goods 
will bear no Price, and that few or none, have any Money to 
buy the very necessaries of Life, are hastening to follow 
their departed Neighbours. It is true, Corn among us, 
carries a very high price; but it is for the same reason, 
that Rats, and Cats, and Dead Horses, have been often bought 
for Gold, in a Town besieged. </p>
            <p>There is a Person of Quality in my Neighbourhood, who 
twenty Years ago, when he was just come to age, being 
unexperienced, and of a generous Temper, let his lands, even 
as times went then, at a low Rate, to able Tenants, and 
consequently by the rise of Land since that time, looked 
upon his Estate, to be set at half value. But Numbers of 
these Tenants, or their Descendants are now Offering to sell 
their Leases by Cant, even those which were for Lives, some 
of them renewable for ever, and some Fee-farms, which the 
Landlord himself, hath bought in, at half the Price they 
would have yielded seven Years ago. And some Leases Let at 
the same time, for Lives, have been given up to him, without 
any Consideration at all. </p>
            <p>This is the most favourable face of things at present 
among us, I say, among us of the North, who are esteemed the 
onely thriving people of the Kingdom: And how far, and how 
soon, this Misery, and Desolation may spread, is easy to 
foresee. </p>
            <p>The vast Sums of Money daily carryed off, by our numerous 
Adventurers to America, have deprived us of our Gold in 
these Parts, almost as much as of our Silver. </p>
            <p>And the good Wives who come to our Houses, offer us their 
Pieces of Linnen, upon which their whole Dependence lyes, 
for so little profit, that it can neither half pay their 
Rents, nor half support their Families. </p>
            <p>It is remarkable, that this Enthusiasm spread among our 
Northern People, of sheltring them selves in the Continent 
of America, hath no other foundation, than their present 
insupportable Condition at home. I have made all possible 
inquiries, to learn what Encouragement our People have met 
with, by any Intelligence from those Plantations, sufficient 
to make them undertake, so tedious, and hazardous a Voyage, 
in all seasons of the Year; and so ill accommodated in their 
Ships, that many of them have Dyed miserably in their 
Passage; But, could never get one satisfactory Answer. Some 
body, they know not who, had Written a Letter to his Friend, 
or Cousin, from thence, inviting him by all means, to come 
over; that it was a fine fruitfull Country, and to be held 
for ever, at a Penny an Acre. But the Truth of the Fact is 
this, The English established in those Colonies, are in 
great want of Men to inhabit that Tract of Ground, which 
lyes between them, and the Wild Indians, who are not reduced 
under their Dominion. We Read of some barbarous People, whom 
the Romans placed in their Armies, for no other service, 
than to blunt their Enemies Swords, and afterwards to fill 
up Trenches with their dead Bodies. And thus our People who 
Transport themselves, are settled in those interjacent 
Tracts, as a screen against the Insults of the Savages and 
may have as much Land, as they can clear from the Woods, at 
a very reasonable Rate, if they can afford to pay about a 
hundred years Purchase by their Labour. Now besides the 
Fox's reasons, which inclines all those, who have already 
ventured thither, to represent every thing, in a false 
light, as well for justifying their own Conduct, as for 
getting Companions, in their misery; so, the Governing 
People in those Plantations, have Wisely provided, that no 
Letters shall be suffered to pass from thence hither, 
without being first viewed by the Council, by which our 
People here, are wholly deceived in the Opinions, they have 
of the happy condition of their Friends, gone before them. 
This was accidentally discovered some months ago, by an 
honest Man who having transported himself, and family 
thither, and finding all things directly contrary to his 
hope, had the luck to convey a private Note, by a faithful 
hand, to his Relation here, entreating him, not to think of 
such a Voyage, and to discourage all his friends from 
attempting it. Yet this, although it be a Truth well known, 
hath produced very little effects; which is no manner of 
wonder; For as it is natural to a Man in a Fever to turn 
often, although without any hope of Ease, or when he is 
pursued to leap down a Precipice, to avoid an Enemy just at 
his back; so, Men in the extremest degree of Misery, and 
Want, will naturally fly to the first apperance of Relief, 
let it be ever so vain, or visionary. </p>
            <p>You may observe, that I have very superficially touched 
the subject I began with, and with the utmost Caution: For I 
know how Criminal the least Complaint hath been thought, 
however seasonable or just, or honestly intended, which hath 
forced me to offer up my Daily Prayers, that it may never, 
at least in my time, be Interpreted by innuendo's as a 
false, scandalous, seditious, and disaffected action, for a 
Man to roar under an acute fit of the Gout, which beside the 
loss, and the danger, would be very inconvenient to one of 
my Age, so severely Afflicted with that Distemper. </p>
            <p>I wish you good success, but I can promise you little, in 
an ungrateful Office you have taken up, without the least 
view, either to Reputation, or Profit. Perhaps your Comfort 
is, that none but Villians, and Betrayers of their Country, 
can be your Enemies. Upon which, I have little to say, 
having not the honour, to be acquainted with many of that 
sort, and therefore, as you easily may believe, am compelled 
to lead a very retired Life. 
</p>
            <trailer>I am Sir, 
Your most Obedient, 
Humble Servant,</trailer>
            <signed>    A. NORTH. County of Down.   <lb/>
Dec. 2d. 1728.    </signed>
         </div>
         <div n="XX" type="article">
            <head>Article XX</head>
            <opener>DEAN SMEDLEY <lb/>
Gone to seek his <lb/>
FORTUNE.  <lb/>
Per varios casus per tot discrimina rare Rum.  <lb/>
A short HISTORY of the DEAN, <lb/>
by way of illustration. </opener>
            <p>HIS first rise in the Church was a small living in the 
Diocese of Cork, given him by the GOVERNMENT, to the 
Surprize of the whole World.  This Living he swapped soon 
after for a Chaplain's Post to a Regiment, which he Sold for 
five Hundred Pounds.  He turned his Hand with this Money, 
and in a very litle time, got a DEANERY, this he swapped 
likewise for another Living.  After this again he got 
another DEANERY, by some unacountable methods, but being 
much in Debt, he was forced to fly his Country, and disposed 
of it, in what manner no Body can tell, but himself and 
another.  He has left one living behind him, which he could 
not avoid doing, because it was sequestred for his Debts.  
When he went for England, in order to turn the Penny, he 
received Subscripsions from Numbers of Gentlemen, to carry 
on a Work, which would have taken ten Years to accomplish, 
if the most Ingenious and Learned Person had undertaken it, 
and which he himself could not have done in ten Thousand 
Years.  After all this, he run off to Fort St. George, and 
left the following Character of himself.  - FROM the 
Political State for the Month of February 1729 pag. 209.  
ABOUT the same time it was published (in the Dayly Post of 
February 13th) that a Mezzotinto is engraving from an 
Original Picture of Dean Smedley, with this remarkable 
Inscription, Written by Himself.  REVERENDUS Decanus, 
Jonathan Smedley: Theologia instructus; in Poesi 
exercitatus; Politioribus excultus Literis: Parce Pius, 
Impius minime: Veritatis Indagator; Libertatis Assertor: 
Subsannatus multis; Fastiditus Quibusdam; Exoptatus 
plurimis; Omnibus Amicus; Author hujus Sententiæ, </p>
            <p>PATRES SUNT VETUL[AElig ]. Domata Invidia; Superato Odio; per 
Laudem et Vituperium; per Famam atq; Infamiam: Utramque 
Fortunam, Variosq; expertus Casus; Mente Sana; Sano Corpore; 
Volens, Lætusq; Lustris plus quam XI numeratis; ad Rem 
Familiarem Restaurandam, augendamq; et ad Evangelium, Indos 
inter Orientales, prædicandum; Grevæ, Idibus 
Februarii, Navem ascendens, Arcemq; Sancti petens Georgii, 
Vernale per [AElig ]quinoxium; Anno [AElig ]ræ Christianæ, 
Millesimo Septingentesimo Vicesimo Octavo TRANSFRETAVIT. </p>
            <p>--Fata vocant--Revocentq; precamur.  </p>
            <p>Thus translated.  </p>
            <l>THE very Reverend Dean Smedley, </l>
            <l>Of Dullness, Pride, Conceit, a medley, </l>
            <l>Was equally allow'd to shine, </l>
            <l>As Poet, Scholar and Divine. </l>
            <l n="5">With Godliness cou'd well dispense, </l>
            <l>Wou'd be a Rake, but wanted Sense. </l>
            <l>Wou'd strictly after Truth enquire </l>
            <l>Because he dreaded to come nigh'r. </l>
            <l>For Liberty no Champion bolder, </l>
            <l n="10">He hated Bailiffs at his shoulder. </l>
            <l>To half the world a standing jest, </l>
            <l>A perfect Nuissance to the rest. </l>
            <l>From many (and we may believe him) </l>
            <l>Had the best wishes they cou'd give him. </l>
            <l n="15">To all mankind a constant friend, </l>
            <l>Provided they had Cash to lend. </l>
            <l>One thing he did before he went hence, </l>
            <l>He left us a Laconick Sentence, </l>
            <l>By cutting of his Phrase, and trimming, </l>
            <l n="20">To prove that Bishops were old Women. </l>
            <l>Poor Envy durst not shew her Phiz, </l>
            <l>She was so terrify'd at his. </l>
            <l>He waded without any shame, </l>
            <l>Thro' thick and thin, to get a name. </l>
            <l n="25">Try'd ev'ry sharping Trick for Bread, </l>
            <l>And after all he seldom Sped. </l>
            <l>When fortune favour'd, he was nice, </l>
            <l>He never once wou'd cog the Dice, </l>
            <l>But if she turn'd against his play, </l>
            <l n="30">He knew to stop a quater trois. </l>
            <l>Now sound in mind, and sound in corpus, </l>
            <l>(Says he) tho' swell'd like any porpus, </l>
            <l>He heys from hence at forty four, </l>
            <l>(But by his Leave he sinks a Score,) </l>
            <l n="35">To the East Indies, there to cheat, </l>
            <l>'Till he can purchase an Estate; </l>
            <l>Where after he has fill'd his chest, </l>
            <l>He'll mount his Tub, and preach his best, </l>
            <l>And plainly prove by dint of Text, </l>
            <l n="40">This World is his, and theirs the next. </l>
            <l>	Lest that the reader shou'd not know, </l>
            <l>The Bank where last he set his Toe, </l>
            <l>'Twas Greenwich.  There he took a Ship, </l>
            <l>And gave his Creditors the Slip. </l>
            <l n="45">But lest Chronology should vary, </l>
            <l>Upon the Ides of February, </l>
            <l>In seventeen hundred eight and twenty, </l>
            <l>To Fort St. George a Pedlar went he. </l>
            <l>Ye Fates, when all he gets is Spent, </l>
            <l n="50">RETURN HIM BEGGAR AS HE WENT.  </l>
            <p>	 ALL Gentlemen, 
who are any ways attacked by Dunces, are desired to send a 
formal Complaint to the Intelligencer, with the Names of the 
Delinquents, there shall be ample Satisfaction given, by 
Printing the Dunces Names at length, with Animadversions, 
suitable to their Crimes and Qualities.  By which means, we 
shall in time be enabled to accomplish an Irish Dunciad, in 
imitation of that incomparable Duncepick Poem, Written and 
Published, by the most Ingenious Mr. Pope against the Grub-
street Scriblers of Great-Brittain.  The Intelligencer does 
likewise for the Ease of the Publick, give Warning to all 
Dunces, of what Rank soever, forthwith to lay aside their 
Crambo, or he does in a most solemn manner declare he will 
Couple them together in their own Rhymes.  He does farther 
assure them, that if, after this his Proclamation, any Dunce 
within this Realm of Ireland, shall presume to touch Pen, 
Ink, or Paper, after the twentieth Day of this Instant, 
before which time it is to be presumed he may hear this 
Read, that then, ipso facto, he pronounces him an Out-law, 
and of Consequence every Man has a right to his Head.  And 
for every such Head, brought in, the Reward shall be the 
current Price of a Sheep's Head, be the Rate ever so High.  </p>
            <p>Dated at our Chambers. </p>
            <p>May, the 7th 1729.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

