<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Discourse of Western Planting</title>
            <title type="alternative">A particuler discourse concerning the greate necessitie and manifolde commodyties that are like to growe to this realme of Englande by the westerne discoueries lately attempted, written in the yere 1584 : known as discourse of western planting</title>
            <author>Hakluyt, Richard, 1552?-1616</author>
            <editor>University of Oxford Text Archive</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name>Triggs, Sara</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority xml:id="trije1">deposited by<name type="person">Triggs, Jeffery</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>North American Reading Project</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Press (NY)</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>c/o Bellcore</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="email">triggs@bellcore.com</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </authority>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/3115</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106001141</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106001146</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
      </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Revised version of  <relatedItem type="older" target="http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/2168"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <note>Hakluyt, Richard, 1552?-1616. - Discourse of Western Planting. - 1st e.d 1584</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notAfter="1584"/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <term type="genre">America -- Discovery and exploration -- English</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-09-27">Header normalised</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">
                  <title type="main">Discourse of Western Planting</title>
               </titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>by 
<docAuthor>Richard Hakluyt</docAuthor>
            </byline>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="main">
            <head>[Discourse of Western Planting]</head>
            <p>A particuler discourse concerninge the greate necessitie and manifolde 
comodyties that are like to growe to this Realme of Englande by the Westerne 
discoveries lately attempted, Written In the yere 1584 by Richarde Hackluyt of 
Oxforde at the requeste and direction of the righte worshipfull Mr. Walter 
Raghly [Raieigh] nowe Knight, before the comynge home of his Twoo Barkes: and 
is devlded into xxi chapiters, the Titles whereof followe in the nexte leafe. 
</p>
            <p>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item> That this westerne discoverie will be greately for 
the inlargement of the gospell of Christe whereunto the 
Princes of the refourmed relligion are chefely bounde 
amongest whome her Majestie is principall. </item>
                  <item> That all other englishe Trades are growen beggerly 
or daungerous, especially in all the kinge of Spaine his 
Domynions, where our men are dryven to flinge their 
Bibles and prayer Bokes into the sea, and to forsweare and renownce their 
 relligion and conscience and consequently theyr obedience to her Majestie. </item>
                  <item> That this westerne voyadge will yelde unto us all 
the commodities of Europe, Affrica, and Asia, as far as 
wee were wonte to travell, and supply the wantes of all 
our decayed trades. </item>
                  <item> That this enterprise will be for the manifolde imploymente of nombers 
 of idle men, and for bredinge of 
many sufficient, and for utterance of the greate quantitie 
of the commodities of our Realme. </item>
                  <item> That this voyage will be a great bridle to the 
Indies of the kinge of Spaine and a means that wee may 
arreste at our pleasure for the space of teime weekes or 
three monethes every yere, one or twoo hundred saile of 
his subjectes shippes at the fysshinge in Newfounde Iande. </item>
                  <item> That the rischesse that the Indian Threasure 
wrought in time of Charles the late Emperor father to the 
Spanishe kinge, is to be had in consideracion of the Q. 
moste excellent Majestie, leaste the contynuall commynge 
of the like threasure from thence to his sonne, worke the 
unrecoverable annoye of this Realme, whereof already wee 
have had very dangerous experience. </item>
                  <item> What speciall meanes may bringe kinge Phillippe 
from his high Throne, and make him equal to the Princes 
his neighbours, wherewithall is shewed his weakenes in 
the west Indies. </item>
                  <item> That the limites of the kinge of Spaines domynions in the west Indies 
 be nothinge so large as is generally 
imagined and surmised, neither those partes which he 
holdeth be of any such forces as is falsely geven oute by 
the popishe Clergye and others his suitors, to terrffie the 
Princes of the Relligion and to abuse and blinde them. </item>
                  <item> The Names of the riche Townes lienge alonge the 
sea coaste on the northe side from the equinoctiall of the 
mayne lande of America under the kinge of Spaine. </item>
                  <item> A Brefe declaracion of the chefe Ilands in the Bay 
of Mexico beinge under the kinge of Spaine, with their 
havens and fortes, and what commodities they yeide. </item>
                  <item> That the Spaniardes have executed most outragious and more then 
 Turkishe cruelties in all the west 
Indies, whereby they are every where there, become moste 
odious unto them, whoe woulde joyne with us or any 
other moste willingly to shake of their moste intollerable 
yoke, and have begonne to doo it already in dyvers places 
where they were Lordes heretofore. </item>
                  <item> That the passage in this voyadge is easie and 
shorte, that it cutteth not nere the trade of any other 
mightie Princes, nor nere their Contries, that it is to be 
perfourmed at all tymes of the yere, and nedeth but one 
kinde of winde, that Ireland beinge full of goodd havens 
on the southe and west sides, is the nerest parte of Europe 
to it, which by this trade shall be in more securitie, and 
the sooner drawen to more Civilitie. </item>
                  <item> That hereby the Revenewes and customes of her 
Majestie bothe outwardes and inwardes shall mightely be 
inlarged by the toll, excises, and other dueties which without oppression may be 
 raised. </item>
                  <item> That this action will be greately for the increase, 
mayneteynaunce and safetie of our Navye, and especially 
of greate shippinge which is the strengthe of our Realme, 
and for the supportation of all those occupacions that depende upon the same. </item>
                  <item> That spedie plantinge in divers fitt places is moste 
necessarie upon these luckye westerne discoveries for feare 
of the daunger of being prevented by other nations which 
have the like intentions, with the order thereof and other 
reasons therewithall alleaged. </item>
                  <item> Meanes to kepe this enterprise from overthrowe 
and the enterprisers from shame and dishonor. </item>
                  <item> That by these Colonies the Northwest passage to 
Cathaio and China may easely quickly and perfectly be 
searched oute aswell by river and overlande, as by sea, for 
proofe whereof here are quoted and alleaged divers rare 
Testymonies oute of the three volumes of voyadges gathered by Ramusius and other 
 grave authors. </item>
                  <item> That the Queene of Englande title to all the west 
Indies, or at the leaste to as moche as is from Florida to 
the Circle articke, is more lawfull and righte then the 
Spaniardes or any other Christian Princes. </item>
                  <item> An aunswer to the Bull of the Donacion of all the 
west Indies graunted to the kinges of Spaine by Pope 
Alexander the VI whoe was himselfe a Spaniarde borne. </item>
                  <item> A brefe collection of certaine reasons to induce 
her Majestie and the state to take in hande the westerne 
voyadge and the plantinge there. </item>
                  <item> A note of some thinges to be prepared for the 
voyadge which is sett downe rather to drawe the takers of 
the voyadge in hande to the presente consideracion then 
for any other reason for that divers thinges require preparation longe before 
the voyadge, without which the voyadge is maymed. </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

