<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Observator: [Selections]</title>
            <author>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Text Keyer and Proofreader</resp>
               <name>Kelly-Uhlig, Daria</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp>
               <name>Triggs, Jeffery</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority xml:id="TRIJE1">deposited by<name type="person">Triggs, Jeffery</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>North American Reading Project</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Press (NY)</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>c/o Bellcore</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="email">triggs@bellcore.com</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </authority>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/3139</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106001389</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106001382</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
      </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Revised version of  <relatedItem type="older" target="http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/2217"/>
            </bibl>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Observator : [Selections]</title>
                  <author>L'Estrange, Roger, Sir, 1616-1704</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Augustan Reprint Society]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>s.l.</pubPlace>
                  <date>s.d.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <seriesStmt>
                  <p>Augustan Reprint Society; 141</p>
               </seriesStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First published between 1681 and 1687</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="1681" notAfter="1687"/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <term type="genre">Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1660-1688</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-09-27">Header normalised</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">
                  <title type="main">Selections from The Observator</title>
               </titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>by 
<docAuthor>Roger L'Estrange</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <docImprint>Augustan Reprint Society. Publication no. 141.</docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>To the <hi>READER</hi>.</head>
            <note anchored="true">1687?</note>
            <p>MOst <hi>Prefaces</hi> are (Effectually) <hi>Apologies</hi>; and 
neither the <hi>Book</hi>, nor the <hi>Author</hi>, one Jot the 
<hi>Better</hi> for them. If the <hi>Book</hi> be <hi>Good</hi>, it 
will not <hi>Need</hi> an <hi>Apology</hi>; If <hi>Bad</hi>, it will 
not <hi>Bear</hi> One: For where a man thinks, by <hi>Calling</hi>
himself <hi>Noddy</hi>, in the <hi>Epistle</hi>, to <hi>Atone</hi>, for 
<hi>Shewing</hi> himself to be one, in the <hi>Test</hi>; He does 
(with Respect to the Dignity of an <hi>Author</hi>) but <hi>Bind up 
Two Fools</hi> in <hi>One Cover</hi>. But there's no more Trusting 
some People with <hi>Pen</hi>, <hi>Ink</hi>, <hi>and Paper</hi>, then 
the Maddest Extravagants in <hi>Bedlam</hi>, with <hi>Fire</hi>, 
<hi>Sword</hi>, or <hi>Poyson</hi>. He that <hi>Writes Ill</hi>, and 
<hi>Sees</hi> it, why does he <hi>Wrote on</hi>? And, with a kind of 
<hi>Malice Prepense</hi>, <hi>Murder</hi> the <hi>Ingenious</hi> part 
of <hi>Mankind</hi>? He that <hi>Really Believes</hi> he Writes 
<hi>Well</hi>; why does he pretend to <hi>Think</hi> Otherwise? Now 
take it which way you please, a man runs a Risque of his 
<hi>Reputation</hi>, for want, either of <hi>Skill</hi>, and 
<hi>Judgment</hi>, the <hi>One</hi> way; Or of <hi>Good Faith</hi>, and 
<hi>Candor</hi> the <hi>Other</hi>. Beside a Mighty Oversight, in 
<hi>Imagining</hi> to bring himself off, from an <hi>Ill</hi> Thing, 
<hi>Done</hi>, or <hi>Said</hi>, by Telling the World that he did it 
for <hi>This</hi> or <hi>That Reason</hi>. When a Book has once past 
the <hi>Press</hi> into the <hi>Publique</hi>; there's no more 
<hi>Recalling</hi> of it, then of a <hi>Word Spoken</hi>, out of the 
<hi>Air</hi> again. And a man may as well hope to Reverse the 
<hi>Decree</hi> of his <hi>Mortality</hi>, as the <hi>Fate</hi> of his 
<hi>Writings</hi>. In short: When the <hi>Dice</hi> are <hi>Cast</hi>, 
the <hi>Author</hi> must stand his <hi>Chance</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>Now that I may not be thought to Enterfere with my self, by 
<hi>Declaiming</hi> against <hi>One Preface</hi> in <hi>Another</hi>: I 
do here previously Renounce to All the Little Arts and Forms of 
Bespeaking the <hi>Good Will</hi> of the <hi>Reader</hi>; As a 
<hi>Practice</hi>, not only <hi>Mean</hi>, <hi>Light</hi>, and 
<hi>Unprofitable</hi>; but wholly <hi>Contrary</hi> to the 
<hi>Bent</hi> of <hi>My Inclination</hi>; as well as 
<hi>Inconsistent</hi> with the very <hi>Drift</hi>, and 
<hi>Quality</hi> of my <hi>Design</hi>. For These <hi>Papers</hi> were 
<hi>Written</hi>, Indifferently, for the <hi>Enformation</hi> of the 
<hi>Multitude</hi>; and for the <hi>Reproof</hi> of a <hi>Faction</hi>: 
<hi>Two Interests</hi> that I am not much <hi>Sollicitous</hi>, or 
<hi>Ambitious</hi>, to <hi>Oblige</hi>: And upon <hi>This 
Consideration</hi> it is, that I have <hi>Address'd</hi> them to the 
<hi>Reader</hi> in <hi>Generall</hi>; as a <hi>Calculation</hi> that 
will serve for <hi>All Meridians</hi>: But if I could have Resolved 
upon a <hi>Dedication</hi>, with any <hi>Particular Mark</hi>, or 
<hi>Epithete</hi> of <hi>Distinction</hi>; it should have been, <hi>To 
the IGNORANT</hi>, <hi>the SEDITIOUS</hi>, or <hi>the SCHISMATICAL 
Reader</hi>; for <hi>There</hi>, properly, lies <hi>my Bus'ness</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>The Reader will find in the <hi>First Number</hi> of This 
Collection, the <hi>True Intent</hi>, and <hi>Design</hi> of the 
<hi>Undertaking</hi>; And he will likewise find, in the very 
<hi>Date</hi> of it, (<hi>April</hi> 13, 1681.) the <hi>Absolute 
Necessity</hi> of some Such <hi>Application</hi>, to Encounter the 
<hi>Notorious Falshoods</hi>; the <hi>Malicious Scandals</hi>, and 
the <hi>Poysonous Doctrines</hi> of <hi>That Season</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>Whether I had Sufficient <hi>Ground</hi>, or <hi>Reason</hi>, for the 
Warmth I have Exprest in These Papers, upon Several Occasions, 
(out of an Affectionate Sense of my <hi>Duty</hi>, and a 
<hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Peace</hi>, <hi>Welfare</hi>, and 
<hi>Safety</hi> of my <hi>Country</hi>;) I <hi>Dare</hi>, and I <hi>Do 
Appeal</hi> to the <hi>King</hi>, and his <hi>Ministers</hi>; to the 
<hi>Consciences</hi> of as many of his Majesties <hi>Subjects</hi>, 
as are not <hi>Stark Blind</hi> because they <hi>WILL</hi> not 
<hi>See</hi>; and to the Justice of the Nation. I do <hi>Appeal</hi>, 
I say, to his Majesties <hi>Proclamations</hi>; to his <hi>Royal 
Declaration</hi>; Several <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>Councel</hi>; the 
<hi>Examinations</hi>, and <hi>Confessions</hi> of <hi>Unquestionable 
Witnesses</hi>; The <hi>Solemnity</hi> of so many <hi>Tryals</hi>, 
<hi>Sentences</hi>, and <hi>Executions</hi>; and the 
<hi>Criminals</hi>, Every Man of 'em, Either <hi>Acknowledging</hi>
the <hi>Crime</hi>, or <hi>Justifying</hi> the <hi>Treason</hi>: But 
the <hi>FACT</hi>, however made as <hi>Clear</hi> as the <hi>Day</hi>. 
There's the <hi>Flight</hi> of the <hi>Conspirators</hi>; Their 
<hi>Arms Seiz'd</hi>; Their <hi>Councels Laid Open</hi>; <hi>Men 
Listed</hi>; The <hi>Methods</hi> of the <hi>Confederacy 
Detected</hi>, to the very <hi>Time</hi>, and <hi>Place</hi> for the 
<hi>Perpetration</hi> of the <hi>Villany</hi>; to the very 
<hi>Circumstance</hi> of the <hi>Providential Fire</hi> at 
<hi>Newmarket</hi>, that <hi>Disappointed</hi> it. I have All These 
<hi>Demonstrative Proofs</hi>, and <hi>Convincing Evidences</hi>, to 
<hi>Warrant</hi> me in the most <hi>Violent Presumptions</hi> of a 
<hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Agitation</hi>: And the <hi>Phanatiques 
Themselves</hi> made good the <hi>Worst</hi> Things that ever I said 
of the <hi>Party</hi>: In <hi>Vindication</hi> of the 
<hi>Importunity</hi> of All my <hi>Foreboding</hi>, if not 
<hi>Prophetical Suspicions</hi>: Nay, they were come to the very 
<hi>Point</hi>, and <hi>Crisis</hi> of the <hi>Operation</hi>, of That 
<hi>Unaccountable</hi>, and <hi>Amazing Vote</hi>. [<hi>If his 
Majesty shall come by Any Violent Death (which God Forbid) it 
shall</hi> be <hi>Reveng'd to the Utmost upon the Papists</hi>.] 
The <hi>King</hi>, and the <hi>Duke</hi> were to be <hi>Murder'd</hi>
by <hi>Republican</hi>, and <hi>Fanatical Rebells</hi>: 
<hi>There's</hi> your <hi>VIOLENT DEATH</hi>, And <hi>Then</hi>
[<hi rend="bold">Reuenge it upon the Papists</hi>:] For [<hi>the 
Thing</hi> (says <hi>Keeling</hi>) <hi>was to be laid upon the 
Papists as a Branch of the Popish Plot</hi>. Walcots Tryal. 
Fol.9.] And the <hi>Next</hi> Step was, for the <hi>Traytors</hi>
to <hi>Unriddle</hi> the <hi>Mystery</hi>, and to <hi>Expound</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Who</hi> were the <hi>Papists</hi>. [<hi>The Lord Mayor</hi>, 
<hi>and the Sheriffs</hi>] <hi>were Three</hi> of 'em. 
<hi>They</hi>, were to be Kill'd; And [<hi>as many of the</hi>
Lieutenancy <hi>as they could get</hi>; <hi>And the Principal 
Ministers of State</hi>; <hi>My Lord</hi> Halifax, <hi>My Lord</hi>
Rochester, <hi>and my</hi> Lord Keeper: (<hi>They</hi> were <hi>Three 
Papists more</hi>.) <hi>My Lord</hi> Keeper <hi>was to have been</hi>
Hang'd <hi>upon the same Post that</hi> College <hi>had hung</hi>. 
<hi>Sir</hi> John Moor <hi>to be</hi> Hung-up <hi>in</hi> Guildhall, 
<hi>as a Betrayer of the Rights and Liberties of the City. And the 
Judges Lordships to be</hi> Flayed, <hi>and</hi> Stuff'd, <hi>and</hi>
Hung-up <hi>in</hi> Westminster Hall: <hi>And a great many of 
the</hi> Pensionary Parliament Hang'd-up, <hi>as Betrayers of the 
Rights of the People</hi>. Walcots Tryal, p.15.] You have 
here, <hi>a Practical Explanation of</hi> the <hi>True-Protestant 
Way</hi>, (in case of <hi>the King's Violent Death</hi>) <hi>of 
Revenging it to the Utmost upon the Papists</hi>.] And This 
Intended <hi>Assassination</hi> (says <hi>Ferguson</hi> (in the same 
Page) [<hi>Is a Glorious Action, and such an Action as</hi> I 
HOPE TO SEE PUBLIQUELY GRATIFY'D BY PARLIAMENT; <hi>And Question 
not but you will be Fam'd for it, and</hi> Statues <hi>Erected for 
you, with the Title of</hi> LIBERATORES PATRIAE. <hi>Ibid</hi>.] 
Now when Matters were come to <hi>This Pass</hi> once, I think it 
was High Time to Write <hi>Observators</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>I might Enlarge my self, upon the <hi>Inducements</hi> that Mov'd 
me to Enter upon This <hi>Province</hi>; The <hi>Needfullness</hi>, 
of some <hi>Popular Medium</hi> for the <hi>Rectifying</hi> of 
<hi>Vulgar Mistakes</hi>, and for <hi>Instilling</hi> of 
<hi>Dutyfull</hi>, and <hi>Honest Principles</hi> into the <hi>Common 
People</hi>, upon That <hi>Turbulent</hi> and <hi>Seditious 
Juncture</hi>: But I am not Willing to <hi>Clogg</hi> my 
<hi>Preface</hi>, with the <hi>Repetition</hi> of what I have spoken 
so <hi>Expressly</hi> to, in the <hi>Book</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>I am now to Advertise the <hi>Reader</hi>, in the next Place; That 
as I have not Strain'd, so much as <hi>One Syllable</hi>, in the 
<hi>Whole Course</hi> of <hi>These Papers</hi>, beyond the 
<hi>Line</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi>, Nor let fall <hi>One Word</hi>, 
<hi>Contrary</hi> to my <hi>Conscience;</hi> Nor <hi>Layd-on</hi> so 
much as <hi>One False Colour</hi>, for a <hi>Blind</hi>, or a 
<hi>Disguise</hi>: As I have not done any Thing of All This, I say; 
Nor <hi>Gratify'd</hi> so much as <hi>One Passion</hi> to the 
Prejudice, of any <hi>MAN</hi>, or <hi>THING</hi>; or of <hi>Common 
Justice it Self</hi>: So neither, on the <hi>Other</hi> hand, was I 
less <hi>Cautious</hi>, and <hi>Considerate</hi>, in the 
<hi>Undertaking</hi> of This <hi>Duty</hi>, then I have been 
<hi>Clear</hi>, and <hi>Impartial</hi>, in the <hi>Discharge</hi>, and 
<hi>Manage</hi> of it. 
</p>
            <p>I was no sooner Possess't, of the <hi>Reason</hi>, and the 
<hi>Expedience</hi> of the <hi>Thing</hi>; but I feel presently to 
<hi>Deliberate</hi> upon the <hi>Individious Difficulties</hi>; The 
<hi>Scandals</hi>, <hi>Reproaches</hi>, and a Thousand Other 
<hi>Mischiefs</hi>, and <hi>Inconveniencies</hi>, that would probably 
<hi>Attend</hi> it. I laid them All <hi>before</hi> me; And upon a 
<hi>Full Computation</hi> of the <hi>Matter</hi>, <hi>Pro</hi> and 
<hi>Con</hi>; I Resolv'd, at last, to Put <hi>pen to paper</hi>; not 
without some <hi>Vanity</hi> perhaps, in <hi>Affecting</hi> the 
<hi>Honour</hi> of being <hi>Revil'd</hi>, but the <hi>Blasphemers</hi>
of <hi>God</hi>, and the <hi>King</hi>. I shall say Nothing of the 
<hi>Traytors</hi>; The <hi>Papists</hi>; The <hi>Fidlers</hi>; The 
<hi>All-manner-of-Rogues</hi>, and <hi>Debauchees</hi> that they have 
<hi>made</hi> me: For their <hi>Cause</hi> is <hi>Founded</hi> upon a 
<hi>Sacrilegious Hypocrisy</hi>; <hi>Maintain'd</hi> by <hi>Fraud</hi>, 
<hi>Scandal</hi>, and <hi>Imposture</hi>. And when they have a mind 
to <hi>Blacken</hi> a man, 'tis not a <hi>Straw</hi> matter, for any 
<hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Fact</hi>, or <hi>History</hi>: But 
<hi>Paint</hi> him as like the <hi>Devil</hi> as they <hi>Can</hi>; and 
to make short Work on't, <hi>One Fanatique</hi> Sits to 
<hi>Another</hi>, for the <hi>Picture</hi>. But <hi>These 
Scurrilities</hi> have more of <hi>Noise</hi> in 'em, then of 
<hi>Weight</hi>: And Those People that had the face to 
<hi>Calumniate Charles the First</hi>, for a <hi>TYRANT</hi>, and a 
<hi>PAPIST</hi>; And the <hi>Confidence</hi>, at This very day, to do 
as much for <hi>Charles the Second</hi>; They that <hi>Preach 
REBELLION</hi> out of the <hi>GOSPEL</hi>; Give it the <hi>Name</hi>
of <hi>GOD'S TRUTH</hi>, <hi>GOD'S CAUSE</hi>; And offer up the 
<hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> as an <hi>Acceptable Sacrifice</hi> to 
<hi>Jesus Christ</hi>: What <hi>Christian</hi> will not <hi>Value</hi>
himself, upon the <hi>Reputation</hi> of lying under the 
<hi>Scourge</hi> of <hi>Those Tongues</hi>, and <hi>Pens</hi>, that 
Offer these <hi>Outrages</hi> to their <hi>Maker</hi>, and their 
<hi>Saviour</hi>? So that these <hi>Clamours</hi>, and 
<hi>Maledictions</hi>, I look upon, as Matter, rather of 
<hi>Advantage</hi>, then <hi>Discredit</hi>; Where <hi>Loyalty</hi> to 
the <hi>King</hi>, and to the <hi>Church</hi>, is made the 
<hi>Crime</hi>: But yet I must Confess, I had <hi>Some Other 
Mortifications</hi> in my <hi>Thought</hi>, that went a little 
<hi>Nearer</hi> me. 
</p>
            <p>As first, the <hi>Indecency</hi> of a <hi>Gentlemans</hi> Entring 
into a <hi>Street-Brawl</hi>, (and <hi>Barefac'd</hi> too) with the 
<hi>Sink</hi> of <hi>Mankind</hi>, both for <hi>Quality</hi>, and 
<hi>Wickedness</hi>. 21y. The <hi>Disproportion</hi>, and the 
<hi>Indecorum</hi> of the Thing, for an <hi>Old Fellow</hi> that now 
Writes <hi>Sixty Eight</hi>, to run about, a <hi>Masquerading</hi>, 
an <hi>Dialoguing</hi> of it, in <hi>Twenty Fantastical Shapes</hi>, 
only to furnish a <hi>Popular Entertainment</hi>, and 
<hi>Diversion</hi>. 31y. The <hi>Scandalous Appearance</hi> of it, 
for Me to take up the <hi>Profession</hi>, and <hi>Bus'ness</hi> of a 
<hi>Pamphleteer</hi>; and (almost) to Lose the <hi>Name</hi> of my 
<hi>Family</hi>, by it, in <hi>Exchange</hi> for That of the 
<hi>Observator</hi>. 41y. I had This Prospect before me too. What 
<hi>Construction</hi> would be made upon't; (If I may speak it with 
<hi>Modesty</hi>) even to the <hi>Lessening</hi> of my 
<hi>Character</hi>; And Consequently, to my Detriment, Every way, 
as well in Respect of <hi>Fortune</hi>, as <hi>Esteem</hi>: For men 
are apt, in such Cases as This, to <hi>Mistake</hi>, the 
<hi>Intent</hi>, as well as the <hi>Reason</hi> of the <hi>Office</hi>; 
and to Impute the most <hi>Sacred</hi>, and <hi>Consciencious 
Zeal</hi> of an <hi>Upright Heart</hi>, in the performance of the 
most <hi>Important</hi>, and <hi>Necessary Duty</hi>, only to a 
<hi>Levity</hi> of <hi>Mind</hi>, perchance; Or in Other Terms; to an 
Over <hi>Officious</hi>, and <hi>Pragmatical Itch of Medling</hi>: It 
makes a man to be lookt upon, as if a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> were his 
<hi>Masterpiece</hi>; and when he's once <hi>Nail'd</hi> to <hi>That 
Post</hi>, he may reckon upon't, that he' at the <hi>Top</hi> of his 
<hi>Preferment</hi>. Upon These <hi>Four Difficulties</hi>, I 
Reason'd with my self, after This Manner. To the <hi>First</hi>; 
What do I care, for having so much <hi>Dirt</hi> Thrown at me, that 
will <hi>Wash off</hi> again? And at the worst, the Engaging with 
such a <hi>Rabble</hi> of <hi>Contaminated Varlets</hi>, is no more 
than <hi>Leaping</hi> into the <hi>Mud</hi> to help my <hi>Father</hi>. 
<hi>Secondly</hi>. <hi>'Tis not for a man in years</hi>, to do so and 
so. Well! And here's a <hi>Reputative Circumstance</hi>, on the 
<hi>One</hi> hand, against an <hi>Indispensable Duty</hi>, on the 
<hi>Other</hi>. The <hi>Common people</hi> are <hi>Poyson'd</hi>, and 
will run <hi>Stark Mad</hi>, if they be not <hi>Cur'd</hi>: Offer 
them <hi>Reason</hi>, without <hi>Fooling</hi>, and it will never 
<hi>Down</hi> with them: And give them <hi>Fooling</hi>, without 
<hi>Argument</hi>, they're never the <hi>Better</hi> for't. Let 'em 
<hi>Alone</hi>, and All's <hi>Lost</hi>. So that the <hi>Mixture</hi>
is become as <hi>Necessary</hi>, as the <hi>Office</hi>; And it has 
been <hi>My Part</hi>, only to <hi>Season</hi> the <hi>One</hi> with 
the <hi>Other</hi>. <hi>Thirdly</hi>, I must Set the 
<hi>Conscience</hi> of the Action, against the <hi>Reproch</hi>. And 
<hi>Lastly</hi>; <hi>'Tis nothing to me what Other People</hi> Think, 
<hi>so long as I am Conscious to my Self that I Do what I</hi>
Ought. 
</p>
            <p>All This I Computed upon, <hi>before-hand</hi>; And thus far, I 
have not been <hi>Deceiv'd</hi> in my <hi>Account</hi>. I have been 
<hi>Baited</hi> with <hi>Thousands</hi> upon <hi>Thousands</hi> of 
<hi>Libells</hi>. I have Created <hi>Enemies</hi> that do me the 
<hi>Honour</hi> to <hi>Hate</hi> me, perhaps, next to the <hi>King 
Himself</hi> (God Bless him) and the <hi>Royal Family</hi>. Their 
<hi>Scandals</hi> are <hi>Blown over</hi>: Their <hi>Malice</hi>, 
<hi>Defeated</hi>, And whenever <hi>my Hour comes</hi>, I am ready to 
Deliver up my <hi>Soul</hi>, which the <hi>Conscience</hi> of an 
<hi>Honest Man</hi>, as to what I have done, in <hi>This 
Particular</hi>: And I do here Declare, in the <hi>Presence</hi> of 
an <hi>All-Seeing</hi>, and an <hi>All-Knowing God</hi>, That as I 
have never yet receiv'd any <hi>Answer</hi>, more then 
<hi>Cavil</hi>, and <hi>Shuffling</hi>, to the <hi>Doctrine</hi>, and 
<hi>Reasoning</hi> of <hi>These Papers</hi>: So I never <hi>made 
use</hi> of Any <hi>Sophism</hi>, or <hi>Double Meaning</hi>, in 
Defence of the <hi>Cause</hi> that I have here taken upon me to 
<hi>Assert</hi>: but have dealt <hi>Plainly</hi>, and <hi>Above-Bord</hi>, 
without either <hi>Fallacy</hi>, or <hi>Collusion</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>After This <hi>View</hi> of the <hi>Worst side</hi> of my 
<hi>Case</hi>; (And (in truth) a kind of <hi>Abstract</hi> of it, in 
<hi>Minutes</hi>) I should be Extremely wanting, both to <hi>God</hi>
and <hi>Man</hi>, in not taking <hi>This Occasion</hi>, of making 
<hi>known</hi> to the <hi>world</hi>, the <hi>Many Generous 
Instances</hi> of <hi>Affection</hi>, and <hi>Respect</hi>, which I 
have received, not only from the most <hi>Considerable</hi> Part of 
his Majesties <hi>Loyal Subjects</hi> of <hi>All qualities</hi>, and 
<hi>Degrees</hi>; but <hi>Particularly</hi> from the <hi>Two Famous 
Universities themselves</hi>: And, in short, from the most 
<hi>Eminent Persons</hi> of the <hi>Long Robe</hi>, in their 
<hi>Several Professions</hi>: In <hi>Testimony</hi> of their 
<hi>Favourable Acceptance</hi> of my <hi>Honest Endeavours</hi>
toward the Service, both of the <hi>Church</hi>, &amp; the 
<hi>State</hi>. And this I am Obliged to leave behind me, upon 
<hi>Record</hi>; out of a <hi>Double Right</hi>, &amp; <hi>Regard</hi>, 
as well to my <hi>Friends</hi>, as to my <hi>Self</hi>: For I reckon 
upon it, as an <hi>Accumulation</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi>, to 
<hi>Me</hi>, to be <hi>Rescu'd</hi> out of the hands of <hi>Publique 
Enemies</hi>, and <hi>Apostates</hi>, by Men of the Clear 
<hi>Contrary Character</hi>; That is to say; by Men of 
<hi>Unquestionable Integrity</hi>, and of <hi>Unspotted Faith</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>My <hi>Back Friends</hi> are as <hi>Merry</hi>, now, as <hi>a Laugh on 
One side of the Mouth</hi> can Make 'em; at the <hi>Conceit</hi> of 
calling the several <hi>Presents</hi> which have been made me (and 
they are very <hi>Considerable</hi>) by the name of a 
<hi>Gathering</hi>; and they do not Stick to put it about, That I 
was my <hi>Own Sollicitor</hi> for the <hi>Begging</hi> of it. I have 
been Told of One, that <hi>said</hi> as much; <hi>for whose 
sake</hi>, I would Advise <hi>All Parents</hi> to take it for a 
<hi>Warning</hi>, not to <hi>Stuff</hi> their <hi>Childrens heads</hi>
so Damnably, with <hi>Greek and Latin</hi> as to leave no 
<hi>Room</hi> for <hi>Brains</hi>, and <hi>Good Manners</hi>. But what 
if it <hi>be a Gathering</hi>? Are not All <hi>Publique 
Benevolences</hi>; <hi>Publique Works</hi>; <hi>Publique 
Acknowledgments</hi>; the <hi>same Thing</hi>? Neither do I find any 
more <hi>Scandal</hi>, in receiving a <hi>Reward</hi> for a 
<hi>Service</hi> in a <hi>Common Cause</hi>, then in a <hi>Lawyers</hi>
taking a <hi>Fee</hi>, in a <hi>Private</hi> One: But be it what it 
<hi>will</hi>: I shall Transmit the <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> of it, 
with This Paper, as the <hi>Glory of my Life</hi>: And Value my 
self Incomparably more upon so <hi>Eminent</hi> a <hi>Mark</hi> of a 
<hi>General Esteem</hi>; then upon the <hi>Advantage</hi> of <hi>Ten 
times a Greater sum</hi>, by <hi>Any Other way</hi>. But 
<hi>Gatherings</hi>, with some People, are only <hi>Honourable</hi>, 
when they are Apply'd to the <hi>Maintaining</hi> of 
<hi>Conspirators</hi>, and <hi>Affidavit-Men</hi>: And they Account 
<hi>Money</hi> much better <hi>Bestow'd</hi> upon the 
<hi>Subversion</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi>, then toward the 
<hi>Defending</hi> of it: but <hi>That Orange is Squeez'd a far as 
'twill Drop, already</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>Now to the <hi>Calumny</hi> of <hi>My Setting This Bus'ness 
afoot</hi>; <hi>First</hi>, I thank God, that neither my 
<hi>Mind</hi>, nor my <hi>Condition</hi> were ever Sunk <hi>so</hi>
Low, yet, as to <hi>Descend</hi> to <hi>That way of Application</hi>. 
21<hi>y</hi>, As I hope to be Sav'd, the Matter was Proceeded upon, 
in <hi>Several Places</hi>, and a <hi>Long time</hi>, before ever I 
had the Least <hi>Inkling</hi>, or <hi>Imagination</hi> of it; and 
when it was so far <hi>Advanc'd</hi>, <hi>without my Privity</hi>, I 
must Certainly have been both a Great <hi>Fool</hi>, and a Great 
<hi>Clown</hi>, either to have <hi>Oppos'd</hi>, or <hi>Refus'd</hi>, a 
token of so <hi>Obliging</hi>, and so <hi>Generous</hi> a 
<hi>Respect</hi>. To Conclude; If any man has been so 
<hi>Misled</hi>, as to <hi>Intend</hi> That for a <hi>Personal 
Charity</hi>; which I cannot <hi>Honourably</hi> Own the 
<hi>Receiving</hi> of, under <hi>That Notion</hi>; I am ready to 
Return him his Proportion, with a Thousand Acknowledgments: But 
This shall not Hinder me yet, from <hi>Cherishing</hi> in my 
<hi>Thoughts</hi>, the <hi>Remembrance</hi> of what <hi>Honour</hi>
soever has been done me for the sake of the <hi>Publique</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>The Reflexions that have been Pass'd upon my <hi>Quality</hi>, and 
<hi>Conversation</hi>, need no Further Answer, then to Appeal to my 
very <hi>Name</hi>, and my <hi>Acquaintance</hi>: but for the 
<hi>Charge</hi> of being a <hi>Papist</hi>, it is as <hi>False</hi>, as 
it is <hi>Malicious</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>I am to say One Word more now, concerning my <hi>L. 
Shaftsbury</hi>; whose <hi>Name</hi>, and <hi>Title</hi>, I have often 
Occasion to make mention of, in This Book. The <hi>Reader</hi> is 
to take Notice, that it is Intended of the <hi>Late Earl of 
Shaftsbury</hi>, who Dy'd at <hi>Amsterdam</hi>, <hi>Jan</hi>. 1682/3. 
<hi>The Surviving Heir of That Honour, and Family, having ever 
Demean'd himself with a Remarkable Loyalty, and Respect, toward 
the King, and his Government</hi>. 
</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a1" type="Article">
            <head>Numb. 110</head>
            <head>THE OBSERVATOR. In <hi>DIALOGUE</hi>.</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">SATURDAY</hi>, March 11. 1681. <note type="ed" anchored="true">sic</note>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHIG</hi>.     COme; I'le shew ye my <hi>study,</hi> Tory. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TORY</hi>.     Why you have got a Brave <hi>Library</hi> here. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     For a <hi>Choice Collection,</hi> let me tell ye, as 
any is in <hi>Christendom</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     You have all the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin 
Fathers,</hi> I suppose; the <hi>Councells,</hi> the 
<hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and those People. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     I had'em all; but there's a great deal of 
<hi>Trash;</hi> and so I e'en rid my hands of'em; though some of'em 
did pretty well too; considering those <hi>Dark Times</hi>. Now 
here can I sit as <hi>Snug</hi> as a <hi>Hare</hi> in her 
<hi>Form,</hi> and Chat away a Winters Evening with a <hi>Good 
Fire,</hi> a <hi>Pipe,</hi> and a <hi>Friend,</hi> and never feel how 
the time spends. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Well! Andy why should not You and I keep our 
<hi>Conferences</hi> here too? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Best of all: There's no body within hearing; and 
then we have our <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Papers</hi> about us, and all 
in such Order, that I'le lay my Finger, Blindfold, upon any book 
you'le call for. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     But what Subject are they mostly of? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Matters of <hi>State, History, Travells,</hi> The 
Rights and Power of the <hi>People, Reformation, Religion, 
Discipline, Admonitions, Remonstrances, Petitions, Appeals;</hi>
as ye see'em mark'd upon the Shelves. But all this is nothing, 
you'l say, when y'ave seen my <hi>Gallery</hi>. Open that same Door 
before ye. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Bless me! What a Treasure's here? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Look ye now. That side is all <hi>News-Books,</hi>
and <hi>Political Divinity</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     You mean <hi>Polemical</hi> Divinity I suppose. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Ay Ay; 'Tis all one for that. Now all to'ther side 
is <hi>Dissenting Protestants;</hi> as <hi>Cartwright, Brown, 
Barrow, Robinson, Hetherington, Trask, Naylor, Best, Biddle, 
Muggleton</hi>. And here are your <hi>Muncerians, Apostoliques, 
Separatists, Libertines, Georgites, Familists, Ranters Seekers, 
Sweet-Singers, Antinomians, Arrians, Socinians, Millenayres, 
Quakers:</hi> And in Two words; all the <hi>Godly Party</hi>. They 
make Fourteen Folio's of Catalogue. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.      But ha'ye no <hi>Manuscripts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Yes I have Three cases there beyond the Chimny, 
that I wou'd not change for <hi>Bodlies Library</hi> three times 
over. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     What do they treat of? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Two of 'em are altogether upon the <hi>Art of 
Government,</hi> and the <hi>Third</hi> is Cramm'd with 
<hi>Lampoon</hi> and <hi>Satyr</hi>. You sha'not name me any one Copy 
that has scap'd me; nor any Exigent of State; but I'le furnish ye 
out of these Papers with an Expedient for't. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     And wherein does this <hi>Art of Government</hi>
Consist? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.    In <hi>Foresight, Experience, Presence of Thought, 
Prudence of Direction,</hi> and <hi>Vigour of Execution</hi>. To be 
short; Every Motion of the <hi>Head,</hi> the <hi>Eye,</hi> the 
<hi>Hand,</hi> the <hi>Foot,</hi> the <hi>Body,</hi> Contributes a part 
to this Great Work. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Is it a Science that may be Convey'd by 
<hi>Instruction</hi>? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     With as much Ease as <hi>Fencing,</hi> or 
<hi>Dancing</hi>. There are Three or Four <hi>Dissenting 
Academies</hi> here about the Town, where People are taught to 
<hi>Nod, Wink, Gape, Cough, Spit;</hi> Nay the very <hi>Turning</hi>
of their <hi>Hum's</hi> and <hi>Haw's,</hi> by <hi>Rule and 
Method;</hi> when to <hi>Smite the Breast,</hi> and when to <hi>Dust 
the Cushion;</hi> when to <hi>Leap</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and 
when <hi>to Swim;</hi> when to be <hi>Serene,</hi> and when to 
<hi>Thunder:</hi> Nay the <hi>Faces</hi> they are to make at every 
<hi>Period;</hi> and the very <hi>Measure</hi> of their 
<hi>pauses;</hi> that the <hi>Parenthesis</hi> may be large enough 
for the <hi>Groans,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ejaculations</hi> of the <hi>Secret 
ones</hi> to <hi>Play</hi> in; they are taught to Pray for the 
<hi>King</hi> with <hi>One Tone</hi> and <hi>Countenance,</hi> and for 
the <hi>Parliament</hi> with <hi>another</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     I have Observ'd them indeed to Cry with a Loud 
Voice, <hi>Lord! strengthen the Hands of the One,</hi> &amp; then 
to drop the Note into a kinde of a Piping whisper, with a 
<hi>Lord! Turn the Heart of the Other;</hi> which is as much as to 
say, <hi>Alas! the Poor Gentleman is out of his way, and we must 
set all hands at work to bring him to comply with his</hi>
Parliament, <hi>though that</hi> Handy work, <hi>at last, bring 
his</hi> Royall Head <hi>to the</hi> Scaffold. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     If you wou'd not be a <hi>Rogue</hi> now and tell 
tales, I could let ye in to the whole <hi>Popular Mystery;</hi> and 
shew ye the <hi>Folly,</hi> and the <hi>Vanity</hi> of any other 
Claim to <hi>Sovereign Power</hi>. And then <hi>I</hi> have all the 
<hi>Prints</hi> brought me as soon as ever they come out. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Pre'thee let's fall to work then. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Come, I'le give you a sight of one of my 
<hi>Boxes</hi> first; but I must be gone in a quarter of an hour 
upon absolute Necessity. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Well<hi>!</hi> And whether in such hast? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     There's One at <hi>Newington</hi> has promis'd me an 
<hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>Dissenters Sayings;</hi> and then I am 
told of a <hi>Godly Divine</hi> at <hi>Clapham,</hi> that has a 
<hi>Reply</hi> ready to the <hi>Notes upon College</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Let's make the best of our time then. Stay a 
little; what have we here? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Every thing is <hi>Titled,</hi> ye see, ready to 
your hand; so that you may Pick and Chuse. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Let me see then. <hi>Pious Frauds; Mentall 
Reservations; Infallibility of the Assembly; Baxters Saints; 
Cases of Conscience; Dispensations, Contributions, Maxims, 
Intelligence, Orders, Committees, Juryes, Caballs, Religion, 
Property, Demands, Proposals, Grievances, Pretenses, Salvo's, 
Distinctions, Explanations, Projects, Directions, Advices, 
Resolutions, Invectives, Fictions, Forms of Reproaches,</hi>
suited to <hi>All Persons, Orders,</hi> and <hi>Qualities; True-Protestant 
Privileges;</hi> The <hi>Doctrine</hi> of 
<hi>Probabilityes,</hi> and <hi>Implicit Obedience</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Now upon all these Heads, ye have <hi>Authoritys, 
Precedents;</hi> and all the <hi>Colours, Arguments,</hi> and 
<hi>Elucidatons</hi> that the matter will bear. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     But your <hi>Pious Frauds, Mentall Reservations, 
Infallibility, Dispensations, Salvo's, Distinctions, 
Probabilityes, Implicit Faith;</hi> These are all <hi>Popish 
Points</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     They are so, when they are apply'd to the service 
of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> but the <hi>True Protestant-Cause 
Sanctifies</hi> the <hi>Principle</hi>. As there's a great 
difference betwixt the <hi>Popes Excommunicating</hi> of an 
<hi>Hereticall Prince;</hi> and the <hi>Generall Assemblys 
Excommunicating</hi> of an <hi>Antichristian, Episcopall 
Prince;</hi> betwixt a <hi>Popish Gunpowder-Treason,</hi> in the 
<hi>Cellers, under the Parliament-House;</hi> and a <hi>Gunpowder 
Commission</hi> to <hi>Kill</hi> and <hi>Slay</hi> within the 
<hi>walls</hi> of the <hi>Same House, above ground;</hi> though to 
Carnal Eyes they may both appear to <hi>Center</hi> in the same 
<hi>Point:</hi> And so in like manner, betwixt a <hi>Conspiracy</hi>
of <hi>Papists</hi> to <hi>cut off the King,</hi> and <hi>Subvert the 
Government;</hi> and a <hi>True-Protestant-Association,</hi> to the 
very <hi>same Effect:</hi> Nay with this Advantage too; that the 
Latter Propounds the Accomplishing of that, in a matter of a 
<hi>month</hi> or <hi>six weeks,</hi> which the Zeal of their Fore-fathers 
was at least <hi>Ten,</hi> or a <hi>dozen years a doing</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     'Tis a Great Ease for a man to have all these 
subjects <hi>Common-Plac'd</hi> to his hand. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Right. And where you may turn to any thing you 
have a mind to see, with a <hi>wet Finger</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     But Pray'e How do you approve (in many of our 
<hi>Seisures</hi>) of the <hi>Application</hi> of <hi>Popish 
Trinkets</hi> to <hi>Prophane Uses,</hi> which were by them 
Dedicated to the service of a <hi>Superstitious Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     You cannot Imagine, though an <hi>Embroder'd 
Cope</hi> may be an <hi>Abomination,</hi> what a <hi>Cordial the 
Pearl</hi> of it is to a <hi>True-Protestant Professor</hi>. 
<hi>Lambs-Wool</hi> drinks no way better than out of a 
<hi>Chalice</hi>. Or in other Cases; 'Tis but Destroying the 
<hi>Popish Form</hi> of an <hi>Idolatrous Vessell,</hi> and the 
<hi>Intrinsick Value</hi> is never the less <hi>Current</hi>
according to the <hi>Standard</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi>. The 
<hi>Picture</hi> of the <hi>Blessed Virgin,</hi> with our 
<hi>Saviour</hi> in her Arms, is never a jot the worse for 
<hi>sale</hi> to a <hi>Painter,</hi> for being an object of 
<hi>Idolatry</hi> about the <hi>Altar</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     And yet I have seen it Committed to the 
<hi>Flames,</hi> but it has been an Oversight, betwixt the 
<hi>Zeal</hi> and the <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the <hi>Magistrate</hi>. 
How many <hi>Curious Crucifixes,</hi> and <hi>Reliques,</hi> with 
<hi>Delicate Inlayings,</hi> and <hi>Carvings</hi> have I seen 
Expos'd at <hi>Gill</hi> the <hi>Constables</hi> in 
<hi>Westminster;</hi> truly, at very <hi>Reasonable Rates?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Not likely; but then ye must know, they were 
<hi>Seiz'd</hi> in <hi>One Capacity,</hi> and <hi>sold</hi> in 
<hi>Another;</hi> for they were <hi>vended</hi> in the Contemplation 
of the <hi>Workmanship,</hi> though they were <hi>taken</hi> as the 
<hi>Fooleries</hi> of a <hi>False Religion</hi>. We have in our days 
seen the <hi>Representation</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> Demolish'd 
in a <hi>Church-Window,</hi> with Extraordinary <hi>Zeal</hi> and 
<hi>Approbation</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     Why truly I am as much against the making of any 
<hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>God the Father</hi> under the 
<hi>Form</hi> of a <hi>Man,</hi> as any body; for <hi>Twenty 
Mistakes</hi> and <hi>Inconveniences</hi> that may arise upon the 
consideration of such an <hi>Object;</hi> but I know no hurt in the 
world in the Representing of our <hi>Saviour</hi> under a <hi>Human 
shape;</hi> or of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> under the shadow of a 
<hi>Dove:</hi> beside that the thing is presum'd to have been done 
by <hi>Authority;</hi> for otherwise, the same <hi>Zeal</hi> that 
Destroys but the <hi>Window</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> would not 
stick at the Destroying perhaps of every thing else that belongs 
to't. But prethee tell me One thing, suppose the <hi>Blessed 
Trinity,</hi> so Represented, should be the <hi>Seal</hi> of an 
<hi>Ancient</hi> Community, or <hi>Society</hi> of men, what's the 
difference betwixt that <hi>Figure,</hi> in <hi>Graving,</hi> or in 
<hi>Nealing;</hi> in <hi>Silver,</hi> or in <hi>Glass?</hi> Would not 
you as much <hi>scruple</hi> that putting of that <hi>Seal</hi> to a 
<hi>Lease,</hi> as the <hi>seeing</hi> of that <hi>Figure</hi> in a 
<hi>Church-Window?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     No; by no means; for the <hi>One</hi> is Purely a 
<hi>Civil Act;</hi> and the <hi>Other</hi> has a Regard to 
<hi>Religious Worship</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     And yet this <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>Pretended 
Resemblance,</hi> is the <hi>same thing</hi> in the <hi>One,</hi> as 
it is in the <hi>Other</hi>. Well! I am Extremly pleas'd with this 
Private Corner for Liberty of Discourse. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Here you may have all the <hi>Papers</hi> as they 
come out, <hi>Fresh and Fresh:</hi> All the <hi>Arguments,</hi> and 
<hi>Politiques</hi> of the <hi>Dissenting Party;</hi> Chuse <hi>your 
own Theme,</hi> Take <hi>your own time,</hi> and Treat upon <hi>your 
own Conditions</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     That's as fair as any Mortall can wish; So that 
when the day does not afford other matter to work upon, we may 
Look a little more narrowly into the <hi>Merits</hi> of the 
<hi>Cause</hi>. And so much for that. But here let me ask ye a 
Question: Do you know a <hi>Little Cause-Jobber</hi> yonder 
somewhere about <hi>Kings-street, in Covent Garden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Does he not use the <hi>Christian Coffee-House?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     The very same. He was saying t'other day that 
[<hi>L'Estrange</hi> was a <hi>Pensioner of Cromwels;</hi> a 
<hi>Papist;</hi> and that he durst not bring his <hi>Action</hi>
against any man for <hi>Calling</hi> him so: That he was a 
<hi>Rogue;</hi> a <hi>Fidler;</hi> Liv'd in <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> a 
good while, and got his <hi>Living</hi> by his <hi>Trade;</hi> And 
that a <hi>Magistrate,</hi> not far from that place, would 
<hi>Justify</hi> it. The Two first Points, I suppose, will be 
Disputed in another place: And for the <hi>Fidler:</hi> 'Tis well 
known that <hi>L'Estrange</hi> liv'd Eight or Nine years in one of 
the <hi>Piazza-Houses</hi> there; and kept <hi>Servants</hi> that 
would have Scorn'd to have Sorted themselves with any thing so 
mean as this <hi>Paltry Varlet</hi>. But to the Business. How far 
will the <hi>Privilege</hi> of a <hi>True-Protestant-Whig</hi>
Justify a <hi>Villain</hi> in so many <hi>Scandalous Lyes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     So far as the <hi>Common Good</hi> of the 
<hi>Cause</hi> is more Valuable then the <hi>single Credit</hi> of a 
<hi>Private Person</hi>. But say ye now to <hi>Curtis's 
Advertisement</hi> (in his Last <hi>Mercury</hi>) of <hi>Tong's 
Narrative,</hi> and <hi>Case;</hi> concerning <hi>L'Estrange,</hi>
printed for C W? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>.     I say, 'tis <hi>first,</hi> a <hi>Cheat;</hi> for 'tis 
none of <hi>Tong's Writing;</hi> 2<hi>1y,</hi> 'Tis <hi>Another 
Cheat;</hi> for 'twas Printed for <hi>Langley Curtis,</hi> with his 
Name to <hi>Tongs Appointment</hi> for the Printing of it: Only he 
has Fobb'd a <hi>New,</hi> and a <hi>False Title-Page</hi> to't. But 
what says Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> all this while, to <hi>L'Estranges 
Enformation</hi> against <hi>Tonge,</hi> in the <hi>Shammer 
Shamm'd?</hi> where that young Fellow has the Impudence to declare 
under his hand, the very <hi>Foundations</hi> of <hi>Oates's</hi>
Plot to be a <hi>Cheat:</hi> And <hi>I appeal to all Good 
Protestants for Justice upon that Scandalous Wretch</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wh</hi>.     Nay, 'tis a horrible Abuse, and really the man 
stands in's own light: What was't? 500 or a 1000 Pound that he 
recover'd of One that did not say the Hundredth part of what this 
comes to? The Lord Deliver me! I knew the Time when 'twas <hi>half 
a Hanging-matter</hi> to have made the least doubt of any Branch 
of the Hellish Plot: But for this Audacious Fool to say in 
Expresse Terms, that [<hi>the</hi> Four Jesuites Letters, 
<hi>wherein</hi> Oates <hi>pretended was the whole Discovery, 
were</hi> counterfeits] is utterly Intolerable. I'le e'en go 
my ways immediately, and talk with the Doctor about it. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi>, Printed for <hi>Joanna Brome</hi>, at the Gun in S. 
<hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 
</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a2" type="Article">
            <head>Numb. 1.</head>
            <head>THE OBSERVATOR. In <hi>QUESTION</hi> and <hi>ANSWER</hi>.</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">WEDNESDAY</hi>, April 13, 1681.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>WELL! They are so. But do you think now to 
bring'um to their Wits again with a</hi> Pamphlet? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Come, Come; 'Tis the <hi>Press</hi> that has made'um 
<hi>Mad</hi>, and the <hi>Press</hi> must set'um <hi>Right</hi> again. 
The Distemper is <hi>Epidemical;</hi> and there's no way in the 
world, but by <hi>Printing</hi>, to convey the <hi>Remedy</hi> to the 
<hi>Disease</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But what is it that you call a</hi> Remedy? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>. The <hi>Removing</hi> of the <hi>Cause</hi>. That is to 
say, the <hi>Undeceiving</hi> of the <hi>People:</hi> for they are 
well enough Disposed, of themselves, to be Orderly, and Obedient; 
if they were not misled by <hi>Ill Principles</hi>, and Hair'd and 
Juggled out of their Senses with so many Frightful <hi>Stories</hi>
and <hi>Impostures</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well! to be Plain and Short; You call your self 
the</hi> Observator: <hi>What is it now that you intend for the 
Subject of your</hi> Observations&gt;
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Take it in few words then. My business is, to 
encounter the <hi>Faction</hi>, and to Vindicate the 
<hi>Government;</hi> to detect their <hi>Forgeries;</hi> to lay open 
the Rankness of their <hi>Calumnies</hi> and <hi>Malice;</hi> to 
Refute their <hi>Seditious Doctrines;</hi> to expose their 
<hi>Hypocrisy</hi>, and the <hi>bloudy Design</hi> that is carry'd 
on, under the Name, and Semblance, of <hi>Religion</hi>; And, in 
short, to lift up the Cloke of the <hi>True Protestant</hi> (as he 
Christens himself) and to shew the People, the <hi>Jesuite</hi>
that lies skulking under it. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Shall the</hi> Observator <hi>be a</hi> Weekly 
Paper, <hi>or How?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     No, No; but oftner, or seldomer, as I see Occasion. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Pray favour me a word; When you speak of a</hi>
True Protestant, <hi>don't you mean a</hi> Dissenting Protestant? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Yes, I do: For your <hi>Assenting</hi> and 
<hi>Consenting Protestant</hi> (you must know) is a 
<hi>Christian</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>And is not a</hi> Dissenting Protestant <hi>a</hi>
Christian too? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Peradventure, he <hi>is</hi> one; peradventure, 
<hi>not:</hi> For a <hi>Dissenter</hi> has his Name from his 
<hi>Disagreement</hi>, not from his <hi>Perswasion</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>What is a Dissenter then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Tis Impossible to say either what a <hi>Dissenter 
IS</hi>, or what he is <hi>NOT</hi>. For he's a <hi>NOTHING;</hi> that 
may yet come to be <hi>ANY thing</hi>. He may be a 
<hi>Christian;</hi> or he may be a <hi>Turk;</hi> But you'l find the 
best account of him in his <hi>Name</hi>. <hi>A DISSENTER, is one 
that thinks OTHERWISE</hi>. That is to say, let the 
<hi>Magistrate</hi> think what he pleases, the <hi>Dissenter</hi>
will be sure to be of <hi>another Opinion</hi>. A <hi>Dissenter</hi>
is not of <hi>This</hi>, or of <hi>That</hi>, or of <hi>Any 
Religion;</hi> but <hi>A Member Politique of an Incorporate 
Faction</hi>: or Otherwise; A <hi>Protestant-Fault-Finder</hi> in a 
<hi>Christian Commonwealth</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well! but tho' a</hi> Dissenter <hi>may be</hi> any 
thing; <hi>A</hi> Dissenting Protestant <hi>yet tells ye</hi> what 
<hi>he</hi> Is. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     He does so, he tells ye that he <hi>is</hi> a 
<hi>Negative</hi>: an <hi>Anti-Protester;</hi> One that <hi>Protests 
AGAINST</hi>, but not <hi>FOR</hi> any thing. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Ay; but so long as he opposes the</hi>
Corruptions <hi>of the Church of</hi> Rome. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Well: And so he does the <hi>Rites</hi>, and 
<hi>Constitutions</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> too. As a 
<hi>Protestant</hi>, he does the <hi>former;</hi> and the 
<hi>Other</hi> as a <hi>Dissenter</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But there is no</hi> Uniting <hi>of These</hi>
Dissenters? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     You shall as soon make the Winds blow the same way, 
from all the Poynts of the Compass. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>There are</hi> Good <hi>and</hi> Bad, <hi>of</hi> all 
Opinions, <hi>there's no doubt on't: But do you think it fayr, to 
Condemn a</hi> whole Party <hi>for some</hi> Ill men <hi>in't?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     No, by no means: The <hi>Party</hi> is neither the 
<hi>Worse,</hi> for having <hi>Ill</hi> men in it, nor the 
<hi>Better,</hi> for <hi>Good</hi>. For whatever the 
<hi>Members</hi>are, the <hi>Party</hi> is a <hi>Confederacy;</hi> as 
being a <hi>Combination</hi> against the <hi>Law</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     But <hi>a man may</hi> Mean honestly, <hi>and yet 
perhaps ly under some</hi> Mistake. <hi>Can any man help his 
Opinion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     A man may <hi>Mean well,</hi> and <hi>Do Ill</hi>; he 
may shed <hi>Innocent Bloud,</hi> and <hi>think he does God good 
Service</hi>. 'Tis True: A man cannot help <hi>Thinking'</hi> but he 
may help <hi>Doing:</hi> He is <hi>Excusable</hi> for a 
<hi>Private</hi> Mistake, for <hi>That's</hi> an Error only to 
<hi>himself;</hi> but when it comes once to an <hi>Overt Act</hi>, 
'tis an <hi>Usurpation</hi> upon the <hi>Magistrate</hi>, and there's 
no Plea for't. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>You have no kindnesse, I perceive, for a</hi>
Dissenting Protestant; <hi>but what do you think of a bare</hi>
Protestant <hi>without any</hi> Adjunct? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     I do look upon <hi>Such</hi> a <hi>Protestant</hi> to 
be a kind of an <hi>Adjective Noun-Substantive; It requires 
something to be joyn'd with it, to shew its Signification</hi>. By 
<hi>Protestancy</hi> in <hi>General</hi> is commonly understood a 
<hi>Separation</hi> of Christians from the Communion of the Church 
of <hi>Rome:</hi> But to <hi>Oppose Errors,</hi> on the <hi>One 
hand</hi>, is not Sufficient, without keeping our selves 
<hi>Clear</hi> of Corruptions, on the <hi>Other</hi>. Now it was the 
<hi>Reformation</hi>, not the <hi>Protestation</hi>, that Settled us 
upon a <hi>true Medium</hi> betwixt the two <hi>Extremes</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>So that you look upon the</hi> Protestation, 
<hi>and the</hi> Reformation, <hi>it seems, as two several 
things</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Very right; But in such a manner only, that the 
<hi>Former,</hi> by Gods Providence, made way for the <hi>Other</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But are not all</hi> Protestants <hi>Members of 
the</hi> Reformed Religion? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Take notice, <hi>First,</hi> that the <hi>Name</hi>
came Originally from the <hi>Protestation</hi> in 1529. against the 
<hi>Decree of Spires;</hi> and that the <hi>Lutheran Protestants</hi>
and <hi>Ours</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are not of the 
<hi>Sam Communion</hi>. Now <hi>Secondly;</hi> If you take 
<hi>Protestants</hi> in the <hi>Latitude</hi> with our 
<hi>Dissenters,</hi> they are not so much a <hi>Religion,</hi> as a 
<hi>Party;</hi> and whoever takes this Body of <hi>Dissenters</hi>
for <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> sets up a 
<hi>Reformation</hi> of a <hi>hundred and fifty Colours</hi> and as 
may [sic] <hi>Heresies</hi>. The <hi>Anabaptists, Brownists, 
Antinomians, Familists, &amp;c</hi>. do all of the set up for 
<hi>Dissenting Protestants;</hi> but God forbid we should ever 
enter these <hi>People</hi> upon the Roll of the 
<hi>Reformation</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     Well! <hi>but what do you think of</hi> Protestant 
Smith <hi>and</hi> Protestant Harris? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Just as I do of <hi>Protestant Muncer,</hi> and 
<hi>Protestant Phifer;</hi> a Brace of <hi>Protestants</hi> that cost 
the Empire 150000 Lives: and our own <hi>Pretended Protestants</hi>
too, of Later Date, have cost <hi>This Nation little lesse</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Ay: But these are men of quite another Temper: 
Do not you see how zealous they are for the Preservation of 
the</hi> King's Person, <hi>the</hi> Government, <hi>and the</hi>
Protestant Religion? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     I <hi>See</hi> well enough what they <hi>Say,</hi> and 
I <hi>know</hi> what they <hi>do</hi>. Consider, <hi>First,</hi> that 
they are Profess'd <hi>Anabaptists: Smith</hi> no less than a 
<hi>pretended Prophet;</hi> and the <hi>Other,</hi> a kind of a 
<hi>Wet Enthusiast</hi>. <hi>Secondly;</hi> 'tis the very 
<hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Sect</hi> to root out <hi>Magistracy,</hi>
Cancel <hi>Humane Laws; Kill,</hi> and take <hi>Possession;</hi> and 
<hi>wash their Feet with the Bloud of the Ungodly;</hi> and where 
ever they have set Footing, they have <hi>Practic'd</hi> what they 
<hi>Taught</hi>. Are not these likely men now, to help out a 
<hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>Religion,</hi> at a dead lift? If you would 
be further satisfy'd in the Truth of things, reade <hi>Sleidan, 
Spanhemius, Gastius, Hortensius, Bullinger, Pontanus,</hi> The 
<hi>Dipper dipp'd, Bayly's Disswasive, Pagets Heresiography,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>Hortensius</hi> tells ye, how <hi>Jack of Leydens 
Successor</hi> murthered his Wife, to make way to his Daughter, 
<hi>P</hi>. 74. and after that, cut a girls throat, for fear she 
should tell Tales. <hi>Gastius</hi> tells us of a Fellow that cut 
off his brothers Head, as by Impulse, and then cry'd, <hi>The Will 
of God is fulfilled, lib</hi>. I. <hi>Pa</hi>. 12. <hi>Jack of 
Leyden</hi> started up from Supper, <hi>to do some business</hi> (he 
said) <hi>which the Father had commanded him,</hi> and cut off a 
Soldiers Head; and afterwards cut off his Wives head in the 
<hi>Market-place</hi>. <hi>Sleydans Comment. Lib</hi>. 10. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>You will not make the</hi> Protestant-Mercury 
<hi>to be an</hi> Anabaptist <hi>too, will ye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     If you do make him <hi>any thing,</hi> I'le make him 
<hi>That</hi>. But in one word, they are <hi>Factious</hi> and 
<hi>Necessitous;</hi> and consequently, the fittest Instruments in 
the world, for the promoting of a <hi>Sedition</hi>. First, as they 
are <hi>Principled</hi> for't; and then, in respect of their 
<hi>Condition;</hi> for they are every man of them under the Lash 
of the Law, and Retainers to Prisons; So that in their 
<hi>Fortunes</hi> they can hardly be <hi>worse</hi>. Insomuch, that 
it is a common thing for them to lend a Name to the countenancing 
of a Libel which no body else dares own. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well! but let them be as</hi> poor, <hi>and</hi>
malicious <hi>as</hi> Devils, <hi>so long as they have neither</hi>
Brains, <hi>nor</hi> Interest, <hi>what hurt can their Papers 
do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     The Intelligences, you must know, that bear their 
<hi>Names,</hi> are not of <hi>their Composing,</hi> but the Dictates 
of a <hi>Faction,</hi> and the Venom of a <hi>Club of Common-wealths-men</hi>
instill'd into those Papers. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>These are</hi> Words, <hi>all this while, 
without</hi> Proofs; <hi>Can you shew us particularly where the 
Venom lies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     It is the business of every Sheet they Publish, to 
Affront the <hi>Government</hi> the <hi>Kings Authority,</hi> and 
<hi>Administration;</hi> the <hi>Privy-Council;</hi> the <hi>Church, 
Bench, Juries, Witnesses;</hi> All <hi>Officers, Ecclesiastical, 
Military,</hi> and <hi>Civil:</hi> and no matter for <hi>Truth</hi> or 
<hi>Honesty,</hi> when a <hi>Forg'd Relation</hi> will serve their 
turn. 'Tis a common thing with them, to get half a dozen 
<hi>Schismaticall</hi> Hands to a <hi>Petition,</hi> or 
<hi>Address</hi> in a corner, and then call it, the sense of the 
Nation: and when all's done, they are not above twenty Persons, 
that make all this clutter in the Kingdom. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But to what End do they all this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     To make the Government <hi>Odious,</hi> and 
<hi>Contemptible;</hi> to magnifie their own Party; and fright the 
People out of their <hi>Allegeance,</hi> by <hi>Counterfeit Letters, 
Reports,</hi> and <hi>false Musters,</hi> as if the sober and 
considerable part of the Nation were all on their side. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>We are in Common Charity</hi> to allow, 
<hi>for</hi> Errors, <hi>and</hi> Mis-reports, <hi>and not presently 
to make an Act of</hi> Malice, <hi>and</hi> Design, <hi>out of 
every</hi> Mistake. <hi>Can you shew me any of these</hi>
Counterfeits, <hi>and</hi> Impostures <hi>that you speak of? 
These</hi> Cheats <hi>upon the</hi> People, <hi>and</hi> Affronts 
<hi>upon the</hi> Government? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Yes, yes; Abundantly. And Il'e give you Instances 
immediately upon every poynt you'l ask me: Only This note, by the 
way; That let them be <hi>mistakes,</hi> or <hi>Contrivances,</hi> or 
what you will, they all run Unanimously <hi>against</hi> the 
Government, without so much as one Syllable in <hi>favour</hi> of 
it: Which makes the matter desperately suspitious. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Let me see then, in the First place, where 
any</hi> Affront <hi>is put upon the</hi> Government. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     <hi>Some Persons</hi> (Says Smiths Prot. Int. N. 7.) 
<hi>in</hi> Norwich, <hi>&amp;c. who have a greater stock of</hi>
Confidence, <hi>and</hi> Malice, <hi>then</hi> Wisdom, <hi>and</hi>
Honesty, <hi>are so far transported with</hi> Zeal <hi>to serve 
the</hi> Devil, <hi>or his</hi> Emissaryes <hi>the</hi> Papists, 
<hi>that they are now Prosecuting several</hi> Dissenting 
Protestants <hi>upon</hi> Stat. 35. Eliz. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (And so 
the Protestant-Mercury, <hi>N.</hi> 15.) <hi>Some People at</hi>
Norwich, <hi>are playing the</hi> Devil <hi>for</hi> Godsake: 
<hi>several honest, peaceable,</hi> Protestant Dissenters, 
<hi>having been troubled for not coming to</hi> Church, <hi>or 
having been Present at</hi> Religious Meetings &amp;c.] Now 
what greater <hi>Affront</hi> can there be to <hi>Government,</hi>
then This language, <hi>First,</hi> from an <hi>Anabaptist</hi> that 
is a <hi>Professed Enemy</hi> to <hi>all Government;</hi> and 
<hi>Secondly,</hi> from a <hi>Private Person,</hi> Bare-fac'd, to 
arraign a <hi>Solemn Law:</hi> A <hi>Law</hi> of this 
<hi>Antiquity;</hi> a <hi>Law of Queen Elizabeth's,</hi> (a Princesse 
so much Celebrated by our <hi>Dissenters themselves</hi> for her 
<hi>Piety, Good Government,</hi> and <hi>Moderation;</hi>) a 
<hi>Law</hi> which, upon Experience, has been found so 
<hi>Necessary,</hi> that the bare <hi>Relaxing</hi> of it, cost the 
<hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>two or 
three hundred thousand</hi> of his <hi>Subjects</hi>, and a 
<hi>Twenty-years-Rebellion?</hi> To say nothing of the dangerous 
Consequence of making it <hi>Unsafe</hi> for <hi>Magistrates</hi> to 
discharge their Dutyes, for fear of <hi>Outrages,</hi> and 
<hi>Libells</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well! but what have you to say now to the</hi>
Kings Authority, <hi>his</hi> Administration, <hi>and his</hi> Privy 
Council. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     <hi>Smith</hi> (in his <hi>Vox Populi, P.</hi> 13.) 
saith, that <hi>the King is oblig'd to pass or Confirm those Laws 
his People shall Chuse</hi>.] at which rate, if they shall 
tender him a Bill for the <hi>Deposing</hi> of himself, he is bound 
to <hi>agree</hi> to't. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in the same Page, <hi>he 
Denies the Kings Power of Proroguing, or Dissolving 
Parliaments;</hi> which is an <hi>Essential</hi> of 
<hi>Government</hi> it self, under what Forms so-ever, and he's no 
longer a <hi>King, without it</hi>. And then for his 
<hi>Administration, P</hi>. 1. the <hi>Anabaptist</hi> charges upon 
his Majesty [<hi>those many surprizing and astonishing 
Prorogations, and Dissolutions</hi> (as he has worded his Meaning) 
<hi>to be procur'd by the Papists</hi>.] And then, <hi>P</hi> 15. 
he wounds both the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Council,</hi> at a 
Blow; in falling upon <hi>those that make the King break his 
Coronation-Oath;</hi> arraigning his <hi>Council</hi> in the 
<hi>First</hi> place, and the <hi>King himself</hi> in the 
<hi>Second'</hi> and that for no less than the breach of 
<hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi>.Wee'l talk out the Rest at our 
next Meeting. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Brome,</hi>, at the Gun in <hi>S. 
Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 
</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a3" type="Article">
            <head>Numb. 13.</head>
            <head>THE OBSERVATOR In QUESTION and ANSWER.</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">SATURDAY</hi>, May 14, 1681.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>u.     <hi>But which way lies</hi> your <hi>Humour</hi> then? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     My way (and you must know) lies more to <hi>History,</hi> and 
<hi>Books,</hi> and <hi>Politicks,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>such as 
That,</hi> But take this along with you too; that I am for turning over of 
<hi>Men,</hi> as well as <hi>Books;</hi> for that's the Profitable Study when 
all's done. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Pre'thee commend me to the</hi> Common Hangman 
<hi>then, If He that</hi> turns over <hi>the most</hi> men <hi>be the</hi>
Greatest Philosopher. <hi>But how</hi> turning over <hi>of</hi> Men? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     That is to say, I <hi>Read</hi> Them; I <hi>Study</hi> them; I 
speak of <hi>turning over</hi> their <hi>Actions,</hi> not their <hi>Body s</hi>. 
And Pray observe my <hi>Simile</hi>. <hi>Every</hi> Action <hi>of a man s</hi>
Life <hi>resembles</hi> a Page <hi>in a</hi> Book. D'ye Mark me? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>I were to Blame else, But what are the Authors that you 
would recommend to a body s Reading?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Why thereafter as the Subject is, As for <hi>History;</hi> ye 
have <hi>Clarks Lives,</hi> and <hi>Examples; Lloyd's Memoirs;</hi> the 
<hi>Popes Warehouse,</hi> &amp;c. For <hi>Politicks;</hi> There's Mr. 
<hi>Baxters Holy Commonwealth,</hi> the <hi>Assemblys Catechism,</hi>
The Letter about the <hi>Black Box,</hi> &amp;c. For <hi>Law,</hi> ye have 
Mr. <hi>Prinn's Soveraign Power of Parliaments; Smiths Vox Populi,</hi>
&amp;c. For <hi>Morals,</hi> There's <hi>Youth's Behaviour;</hi> And then 
For <hi>Deep Knowledge,</hi> ye have <hi>Brightman's Revelations 
Reveal'd; Lilly's Hieroglyphicks;</hi> the <hi>Northern Star, Jones of the 
Heart:</hi> All Excellent Pieces in their Kinds, and not Inferior (perhaps) to 
any of the Ancients. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>I was never so happy as to meet with any of these 
Authors. But what d'ye think of</hi> Cornelius Tacitus? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     A <hi>Talking, Tedious, Empty Fellow</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well but is not</hi> Titus Livius <hi>a pretty Good</hi>
Historian? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Ha Ha Ha. That Same <hi>Titus</hi> is an Errant <hi>Puppy,</hi>
a <hi>Damn'd, Insipid, Lying Coxcomb</hi>. <hi>Titus Livius</hi> a good 
<hi>Historian</hi> sayst thou? Why if I had a <hi>Schoolboy</hi> that writ 
such <hi>Latin</hi> I'de tickle his <hi>Toby</hi> for him. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But what's your Opinion of</hi> Caesars Commentaries 
<hi>then? I mean, for a</hi> Narrative? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     A <hi>Narrative</hi> d'ye say? Deliver me from such 
<hi>Narratives!</hi> Why 'tis no more to be compar'd to the 
<hi>Narratives</hi> that are written <hi>now aday s,</hi> then an <hi>Apple</hi>
is to an <hi>Oyster</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But however He was a very</hi> Brave Fellow, <hi>was he 
not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     He was an <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> Oppressing, Tyrannical 
<hi>Fellow</hi>. And then for his <hi>Bravery,</hi> he did pretty well at the 
Battel of <hi>Leipsick,</hi> and after that, at <hi>Lepanto;</hi> and when you 
have said that, you have said all. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>You have read all these Authors, have you not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Why verily I <hi>have,</hi> and I have <hi>not</hi>. They are a 
company of <hi>Lying, Ridiculing Rascals;</hi> They do not <hi>AFFECT</hi>
me at all: they are below me, they are not worth my notice. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>What would I give to be as well vers'd in</hi> History, <hi>as 
you are?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     And that's Impossible, let me tell ye; Utterly Impossible: For I 
reade just six times as much as any other Man. I have Read more 
<hi>Folio's</hi> then ever <hi>Tostatus</hi> read <hi>Pages</hi>. In one Word; I 
reade as much in <hi>one hour,</hi> as any other man reads in <hi>six</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why how can that be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Why you must know I have a notable Faculty that way. I read 
ye <hi>two Pages</hi> at a <hi>view:</hi> the <hi>Right-hand</hi> Page with 
<hi>one eye,</hi> and the <hi>Left</hi> with <hi>t'other,</hi> and then I carry 
<hi>three Lines</hi> before me at a time with <hi>each eye</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But can ye</hi> Keep <hi>what ye</hi> Reade, <hi>at this 
rate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     I <hi>remember</hi> six times more than I <hi>reade;</hi> for I 
supply all that was left out, and yet 'tis a wonderfull thing, I cannot for my 
heart's blood remember <hi>Faces</hi>. I dare swear I have taken one man 
for another twenty times; but I am altogether for <hi>Things,</hi> and 
<hi>Notions,</hi> d'ye see, and such like; <hi>Countenances,</hi> let me tell 
ye, don't <hi>AFFECT</hi> me; And yet I have a strange aversion for the two 
Faces I saw with you t'other day. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>What D'ye mean,</hi> Kings-man <hi>and</hi> Church-man? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     <hi>Devil's-man</hi> and <hi>Damms-man:</hi> A couple of 
<hi>Canary-Birds,</hi> I'le warrant 'em: But <hi>Kings-man</hi> is better yet 
then <hi>Duke's-man</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why do ye talk thus of men of Quality, and Considerable 
Families?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Well! but I may live to see their Honours laid in the dust tho' 
for all that. Prethee why is not <hi>Circingle-man, Lawn-sleeve-man, Mitre-man,</hi>
as good a name as <hi>Church-man?</hi> Pray what Family is the 
same <hi>Church-man</hi> of, for I know a world of the <hi>Name?</hi> He's 
of the <hi>Prelatical House,</hi> I suppose, Is he not? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well, and is he ever the worse for that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Only <hi>Antichrist</hi> is the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Family</hi>. 
Come let me talk a little roundly to ye. How many sound <hi>Protestant 
Divines</hi> may there be of that House now, d'ye think, in <hi>England,</hi>
and <hi>Wales,</hi> and the Town of <hi>Berwick upon Tweed?</hi> not 
above <hi>Six,</hi> if I be a <hi>Christian,</hi> and all the rest are 
<hi>Tantivy's,</hi> and worshippers of the Beast: But I may live yet to have 
the scowring of some of their Frocks for 'em. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Prethee when didst thou see Mr.</hi> Sancroft? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Not a good while; but <hi>Harry</hi> and I had a Crash t'other 
day yonder at <hi>Greenwich</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>What's become of</hi> L'Estrange <hi>I wonder?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Who! <hi>Towzer?</hi> that <hi>Impudent Dog;</hi> That 
<hi>Tory-Rascal;</hi> That <hi>Fidling Curr</hi>. He's in the Plot with 
<hi>Celiers,</hi> and young <hi>Tong,</hi> as sure as thou'rt alive, and as 
Rank a <hi>Papist</hi> (let him swear what he will) as ever Piss't. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But has he not taken the</hi> Sacrament <hi>to the</hi>
contrary? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     A <hi>Popish Proselyte</hi> is no more to be believ'd, upon his 
<hi>Oath,</hi> than the <hi>Devil himself</hi> if he were to Expound upon the 
<hi>Gospel</hi>. Why they have Dispensations to swear any thing. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>What and continue Papists still?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Yes: And go on still with the Hellish Popish Plot, as heartily as 
ever they did before. Why don't you see how the Toad Brazens it out still 
that he was not at <hi>Somerset-House?</hi> tho' <hi>Prance</hi> and 
<hi>Mowbray</hi> swear they saw him there? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Well, But who knows best? He</hi> Himself, <hi>or the</hi>
Witnesses? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Not a fart matter; For whether 'twas so or not; It were better 
Forty such Rogues were Hang'd then one Kings-Evidence Disparag'd. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But did they not swear a little short, think ye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Nay, they might have sworn <hi>homer,</hi> I must confess. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But now you mind me of</hi> Somerset-House; <hi>Do'nt 
you remember a young Fellow of</hi> Cambridge <hi>that Refus'd to 
receive the Sacrament, because (as he told his Master) he was reconcil'd 
to the Church, of</hi> Rome, <hi>and Converted ,and Baptiz'd at</hi>
Somerset-House? <hi>This is an old story ye must know. Why might not 
this be</hi> Towzer? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Nay as like as not, for the <hi>Universitys</hi> are the very 
<hi>Seminarys</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> and it will never be well with 
<hi>England</hi> till <hi>those Calves</hi> be turn'd a <hi>grazing</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But is there no believing of a</hi> Converted Papist 
<hi>upon his</hi> Oath? <hi>Why does the Law receive 'em then (upon such 
and such Certain Tests) for</hi> statutable Protestants? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     The <hi>Law</hi> never was among 'em as I have been. There's 
no such thing (I tell ye) as a <hi>Converted Papist,</hi> and he shall sooner 
change his <hi>shape,</hi> then his <hi>Nature: Kiss a Book, Kiss mine 
Arse</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why d'ye talk thus at random?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Come, come, the <hi>Outlandish Doctor</hi> for my money: that 
told one of the <hi>Macks</hi> t'other day in the face of the <hi>Bench,</hi>
that <hi>he would let down his Breeches and shite upon him. Plain-dealing's a Jewell</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Thou'rt e'en as busy with a</hi> Backside <hi>as a</hi>
Glyster-Pipe. <hi>But (sluttery a part) Pray have a care what ye say; for if 
a</hi> Proselyted Papist <hi>be not to be trusted upon his</hi> Oath, <hi>what 
becomes of the</hi> Kings Evidence <hi>that</hi> swear <hi>under the</hi>
same Circumstances? <hi>But here's enough of this; and Pre'thee tell us 
now, how go squares in the</hi> State <hi>all this while?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Oh very bad, very bad, nothing but <hi>Tory-Rorys,</hi> from 
the top to bottom. <hi>Tory-Judges; Tory-Jurys; Tory-Justices; Tory-officers; 
Tory-Crackfarts; Tory-Pamphlets</hi>. All, <hi>Certiorari-men,</hi>
and <hi>Yorkists</hi>. But I rattled up some of 'em there at the  <hi>What 
d'ye call't-House</hi>  Oh they'r grown strangely Insolent since these 
Bawling Addresses. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why what do they do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Why they set ever <hi>Rascally Squire</hi> and <hi>Doctor 
above</hi> me: Nay, they'l scarce put off their hats to me unless I begin; 
and then they stand grinning at Me and my Train. Would you think now 
that a fellow should have the Impudence to call Me to an account, for 
nothing in the world, but saying, that <hi>he had</hi> a Bitch <hi>to his</hi>
Wife, <hi>and</hi> she <hi>a</hi> Rogue <hi>to her</hi> Husband. And then to 
be call'd <hi>Sirrah</hi> for my pains, only for telling a <hi>Court-Kinsman</hi>
of his that <hi>I should Lace the Rogue, his Cozens Coat for 
him</hi>. Well If I had not sent a Fool o'my errant I had had the Rascal in 
<hi>Lob's</hi> Pound before this time. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>And how came ye to miss?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Why the Agent that I employ'd was so set upon his Guts, that 
he never minded the discourse at the Table. We had had him else. Or if 
he could but have got him to ha' me, we'd ha' done his business. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But d'ye take this to be fair dealing now; to set any man at 
work to betray his Host; or give such language to people of Condition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     What not when the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> lies at 
<hi>stake?</hi> Why Pre'thee I tell the Proudest of 'em all to their Teeth, 
that they are <hi>Villains</hi> and <hi>Scoundrells</hi>. What do I care for 
their <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Reverences</hi>. they <hi>Pimp</hi> for 
<hi>Preferment,</hi> and some of 'em shall hear on't too <hi>next 
Parliament</hi>. But Hark ye I have a great deal of work upon my hands, 
and I want an <hi>Ammanuensis</hi> out of all Cry. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why ye had a Pretty Fellow to'ther day, what's become of 
him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     I'l tell ye then. A <hi>Taylor</hi> had made him a 
<hi>Garment:</hi> and afterwards coming to him for the <hi>mony,</hi> he 
deny'd the Receit on't and being prest upon it, he offer'd to purge himself 
upon <hi>Oath,</hi> that he never had any such Garment. Upon this, the 
matter rested for a while; but any length, it was prov'd where he had 
<hi>Sold</hi> it, and so the Taylor had satisfaction. In short, I turn'd him 
away apon't, for he is no servant for me that's <hi>taken</hi> in a false Oath. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>How is it possible for you to go through with all your 
Writing-work?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Nay that's true; considering what a deal of other business I 
have; for really there would be no Justice done, if I did not look after 
<hi>Witnesses, Jury's,</hi> Choice of <hi>City-Officers,</hi> Election of 
<hi>Members</hi> to serve in <hi>Parliament,</hi> both for <hi>Town,</hi> and 
<hi>Country;</hi> the disposing of <hi>Ecclesiastical Dignitys;</hi> the 
<hi>Jurisdictions</hi> of <hi>Courts;</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> of 
<hi>Prisons;</hi> the <hi>Regulation</hi> of <hi>Messengers Fees:</hi> In one 
word, the stress of the whole Government lyes in a manner upon my 
shoulders; And I am so <hi>Harrass'd</hi> with it, that I profess I was e'en 
thinking, a little before the Meeting of the last Parliament, to lay out a 
smatter of <hi>Twenty</hi> or <hi>Thirty Thousand Pound</hi> upon some 
Pretty Seat in the Country, and Retire. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why truly for a man that has seen the world as you have 
done, what can he do better?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     Yes, I have seen the world to my Cost. 'Twas a sad thing for 
me, you must think, that never went to bed in my Mothers House without 
four or five Servants to wait upon me, (and if I had a mind to a <hi>Tart,</hi>
a <hi>Custard,</hi> or a <hi>Cheesecake</hi> at any time, I had 'em all at 
command:) to be <hi>Hackny'd,</hi> and <hi>Jolted</hi> up and down in a 
Forreign Country like a <hi>Common Body</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But what was it that put you upon</hi> Travel? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     The Desire I had to see <hi>Religions,</hi> and 
<hi>Fashions:</hi> And now it comes in my head. Did you ever see my 
<hi>Grounds and Occasions of the Contempt of the Clergy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Was That Yours Then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     <hi>Mum;</hi> betwixt friends. But I shall have a touch ere long 
at the <hi>Creed-making</hi> Rascal there. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Who's that?</hi> Athanasius? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     The very same. What a <hi>Declaration</hi> is there? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>But how d'ye like the Kings Declaration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     <hi>Not at all. Not at all</hi>. It runs so much upon the 
<hi>Arbitrary,</hi> and the <hi>Prelatick?</hi> Yes, and upon something else 
too. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Come, 'Faith we should not part with dry lips, What d'ye 
think of one</hi> Roomer <hi>now to the Health of? (Hark, and I'le tell 
ye.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     I'le drink no <hi>Traitors</hi> Health. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>Why prethee what is</hi> Civilly-Drinking <hi>his Health, 
more then</hi> Dutifully Praying <hi>for't?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>.     No: I am of the mans mind that said, [I <hi>hope the Devil 
will have him; and if there be any punishment in Hell greater then 
another,</hi> I <hi>hope the Devil will tear his soul to pieces</hi>. So 
Farewell. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi>.     <hi>What a Blessed sort of</hi> Subjects <hi>and</hi> Christians 
<hi>are these, that value themselves in the</hi> One Capacity, <hi>for 
their</hi> Contempt <hi>of</hi> Authority: <hi>And in the</hi> other, <hi>for the 
Zeal of Flying out into</hi> Blasphemys, <hi>and</hi> Execrations, <hi>instead 
of</hi> Prayers? <hi>But what shall</hi> I <hi>call this at last?</hi> A 
Romantique, or <hi>an</hi> Historical Observator? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Johanna Brome,</hi> at the Gun in S. 
<hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 
</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a4" type="Article">
            <head>Vol. 3, Numb. 88</head>
            <head>THE OBSERVATOR</head>
            <head>A Schism <hi>a Greater Judgment then a</hi> Pestilence. <hi>The</hi> Natural Rhetorique <hi>of the</hi> Non-Cons. <hi>The</hi> Danger <hi>of them</hi>. <hi>Several</hi> Sorts <hi>and</hi> Degrees <hi>of Danger</hi>. <hi>Of Coming</hi> About, <hi>or Coming</hi> Over. <hi>The</hi> Cause <hi>Transferr'd from</hi> Government <hi>to</hi> Religion.</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">Munday</hi>, September 28, 1685.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>OBSERVATOR</hi>.     If I were the <hi>Master</hi> of a <hi>Territory,</hi> I would as soon 
<hi>Trust</hi> so many <hi>Spirits</hi> in my <hi>Pulpits, to Blow a Pestilence thorough my 
Dominions,</hi> as so many of our <hi>Non-Conforming Divines;</hi> and reckon my 
<hi>People</hi> much <hi>Safer</hi> too, under the Danger of a <hi>Plague,</hi> then under the 
<hi>Consequences of a Schism:</hi> For the <hi>One Taints</hi> but the <hi rend="bold">Bodies</hi> of 
Men; the <hi>Other Destroys</hi> their very <hi rend="bold">Souls</hi>; the <hi>One</hi> takes them 
<hi>Promiscuously,</hi> the <hi>Good,</hi> and the <hi>Bad, One</hi> with <hi>Another:</hi> But 
the <hi>'Tother Marks,</hi> and <hi>Singles-out</hi> the <hi>Best Men</hi> for <hi>Ruine,</hi> with 
a <hi>Privilege</hi> of <hi>Exemption,</hi> to those that neither fear <hi>God,</hi> nor 
<hi>Man</hi>. The <hi>One</hi> Sweeps away a number of Single <hi>Persons;</hi> the 
<hi>Other</hi> Tears to pieces the <hi>Sinews</hi> of a <hi>Community</hi>. The <hi>One</hi>
does, in <hi>some Degree,</hi> Conduce to the <hi>Purging</hi> of a <hi>Wicked Nation,</hi>
when the <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> is <hi>Appeas'd</hi> by the <hi>Discharge</hi> of 
some <hi>Dreadfull Judgment</hi> upon't; (as the <hi>Air</hi> is Clear'd by <hi>Thunder</hi>) 
The <hi>Other</hi> does All that is <hi>Possible</hi> to the <hi>Filling-up</hi> of the 
<hi>Measure</hi> of a <hi>Publique Iniquity;</hi> and the making of a Land <hi rend="bold">Ripe</hi> for 
<hi>Vengeance</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TRIMMER</hi>.     Prethee what <hi>Danger?</hi> Or what needs this <hi>Lashing,</hi>
when they are All <hi rend="bold">Tongue-Ty'd</hi>; and Driven into <hi>Holes,</hi> and <hi>Hiding-Places,</hi>
to keep out of the way of <hi>Messengers,</hi> and <hi>Constables,</hi> and out of 
the <hi>Clutches</hi> of the <hi>Corporation-Act,</hi> and <hi>Other Penal Laws</hi> against 
their <hi>Private Meetings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     What dost thou Talk of <hi rend="bold">Tongue-Ty'd</hi>? Why I will undertake it; (and 
in <hi>Serious Good Earnest</hi> too) <hi>Gagg</hi> the Whole <hi rend="bold">Set</hi> of'em Give Every 
man his <hi>Pulpit,</hi> or his <hi>Chair,</hi> and only a Bare <hi rend="bold">Standing</hi> in't; and if they 
do not <hi>Wink,</hi> and a <hi>Nod,</hi> and <hi>Cuff</hi> any Prince in <hi>Christendom</hi>
out of his <hi>Dominions,</hi> without a <hi>Word Speaking,</hi> I'le be thy <hi>Bond-slave</hi>. 
Why they do not do their Bus'ness, man, by the Force of <hi>Logique, Grammar,</hi> or by 
the <hi>Dint of Theology:</hi> But by <hi>Groans, Pangs, Tragical Ululations, Silent 
Interjections, Whining Apostrophes, Melting Epiphonemas;</hi> and in a word; by the Helps 
of <hi>Natural Rhetorick,</hi> without <hi>Need,</hi> of either <hi>Sense,</hi> or 
<hi>Syllables</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     They <hi>Preach,</hi> and <hi>Pray,</hi> without <hi>Speaking</hi> then. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     No No. They do <hi rend="bold">Talk</hi> for <hi>Fashion</hi>-sake: But Observe it while 
you will; They move the <hi>Passions</hi> of their <hi>Auditory,</hi> in the <hi>Belfry,</hi> or the 
<hi>Church-Porch, Forty times more</hi> then Directly under the <hi>Pulpit:</hi> For the 
<hi>Emphasis</hi> of an <hi>Action; a Motion, Tone,</hi> or <hi>Countenance,</hi> makes a 
much Deeper <hi>Impression,</hi> than that of a <hi>Naked, Empty, Sound:</hi> And for 
<hi>My Part,</hi> I fancy, it might do as well for 'em to <hi rend="bold">Whistle</hi> their 
<hi>Preachments</hi> as to <hi rend="bold">Articulate</hi> them: For the <hi>Master-piece,</hi> or the 
<hi rend="bold">All in All</hi> of it, lies Mainly, in <hi>Hitting</hi> the <hi>Tune</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Dy'e call this <hi rend="bold">Reasoning</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">Ridiculing</hi>? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     'Tis <hi>Both</hi> in <hi>One:</hi> For it is the <hi>Ridiculous Truth,</hi> and the 
<hi>Just Reason, Method,</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Matter:</hi> And when People are 
once <hi>Juggled</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Out</hi>
               <hi>of their Wits,</hi> they must be <hi>Fool'd</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Into</hi>
               <hi>'em again</hi>. Now there needs no more to the doing of <hi>That Work,</hi>
then the bare <hi>Drawing</hi> of the <hi>Curtain,</hi> and letting People into the <hi>Tyring-Room</hi>. 
For the <hi>Cause,</hi> is all over, <hi>Theatrical:</hi> The <hi>Actors</hi> are 
<hi>Hypocrites,</hi> in their <hi>Manners,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Etymon;</hi> and the whole 
<hi>Manage,</hi> fitter for a <hi>Stage,</hi> then a <hi>Pulpit</hi>. So that the most <hi>Certain 
Way</hi> in <hi>Nature,</hi> for the making of the <hi>Practice, Odious;</hi> and the 
<hi>Disabusing</hi> of the <hi>Undiscerning Multitude,</hi> is to <hi>lay Open</hi> their 
<hi>False Colours, Shapes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Disguises;</hi> and <hi>Expose</hi> Every thing in 
its <hi>Naked Simplicity</hi> to the <hi>Light</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     And what if a man should <hi rend="bold">Allow</hi> This sort of People now, to be the 
most <hi>Uncouth, Hideous Monsters</hi> of the <hi>Creation?</hi> To have the <hi>Teeth,</hi>
the <hi>Nails,</hi> the <hi>Fierceness,</hi> the <hi>Strength,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Appetite</hi> of 
the most <hi>Ravenous</hi> of <hi>Wild Beasts?</hi> This Discourse, of <hi>Caution,</hi> and 
<hi>Description,</hi> might do well enough in the <hi>Countrys</hi> of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and 
<hi>Tygers:</hi> But what's All This, to <hi>his Majesties Dominions,</hi> where there are 
either <hi>None</hi> of These Creatures, <hi>at all,</hi> or No <hi>Other,</hi> at least, then such 
as have their <hi>Nails Par'd,</hi> and their <hi>Chops Muzzled:</hi> And no more 
<hi>Danger</hi> of them, at present, then of our <hi>Beeves,</hi> and <hi>Muttons</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     Dost not thou know that there are <hi>Several</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Sorts</hi>, &amp; 
<hi rend="bold">Degrees</hi> of <hi>Danger?</hi> A man may be <hi rend="bold">Wheedled</hi> into a 
<hi>Precipice,</hi> as well as <hi rend="bold">Thrown</hi> into't: A man may be <hi rend="bold">Hugg'd</hi> or 
<hi rend="bold">Suck'd</hi> to <hi>Death,</hi> without any <hi rend="bold">Biting</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">Scratching</hi> in the 
Case: A man may be <hi rend="bold">Poyson'd</hi> in his <hi>Porridge,</hi> as well as <hi rend="bold">Strangl'd</hi>
in his <hi>Bed:</hi> A man may have <hi rend="bold">False Opinions</hi>
               <hi>Impos'd</hi> upon him by a 
<hi>Fallacy,</hi> or <hi>Fraud</hi> in <hi>Argument,</hi> as well as <hi rend="bold">Extorted</hi> from him, 
by the Force of <hi>Menace,</hi> and <hi>Torment</hi>. And his Bus'ness, at last, is 
<hi>done,</hi> as <hi rend="bold">Dead</hi>, <hi>One way</hi> as <hi>T'other:</hi> And so for the Degrees 
of <hi>Danger;</hi> There's <hi>Danger at Hand;</hi> there's <hi>Danger</hi> at a <hi>Distance; 
Danger</hi> in <hi>Design,</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> in <hi>Practice;</hi> And <hi>Danger,</hi> in 
fine, through All the <hi>Preparatory,</hi> and <hi>Mediate Tendencies</hi> to <hi>Mischief,</hi>
to the <hi>Last Effect</hi> that <hi>Pushes</hi> it self forth to <hi>Execution</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Very Good! And what are All These <hi>Sorts,</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> of 
<hi>Danger</hi> to the <hi>Instances</hi> we have now <hi>Before</hi> us? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     'Tis true; The <hi>Faction</hi> is not in Condition to <hi>Attacque</hi> the 
<hi>Government</hi> by <hi>Force:</hi> Their <hi>Armies</hi> are <hi>Scatter'd,</hi> and their 
<hi>Squadrons Defeated;</hi> the <hi>Whole Party</hi> put to their <hi>Shifts;</hi> and the very 
<hi>Best</hi> of 'em, has enough to do to <hi>save his Own Bacon</hi>. Their <hi>Teeth</hi> are 
<hi>Drawn,</hi> I'le Allow ye, All but here and there a <hi>Stump;</hi> And yet they'l <hi>Pinch, 
Plaguily,</hi> though they cannot <hi>Worry,</hi> and <hi>Tear:</hi> And with <hi>Time,</hi> and 
<hi>Good Discipline,</hi> they'l come to <hi>Grow again</hi>. They have the <hi>Same 
Principles</hi> to friend, that <hi>ever</hi> they had: Only they must be <hi>Manag'd Another 
Way:</hi> And there can never Want <hi>Matter,</hi> for <hi>Artificial Flattery, Wheedling, 
Imposture</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> to <hi>Work</hi> upon. They are not in Condition to 
<hi>Advance,</hi> at this time of Day, in the face of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and of the 
<hi>Government,</hi> with their <hi>Petticoats Flying,</hi> under the <hi>Auspicious 
Direction</hi> of their <hi>Tutelary Angel, Ferguson;</hi> and [<hi rend="bold">Fear Nothing but 
God</hi>] for their <hi>Motto</hi>. But they must Supply want of <hi>Strength,</hi> by 
<hi>Stratagem;</hi> and <hi>Carry-on</hi> their <hi>Approaches,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">out of sight</hi>. 'Tis 
only a little more <hi>Patience,</hi> and the <hi>Work</hi> will be brought about, as sure at the 
<hi>Long-Run,</hi> by a <hi>Mine,</hi> as by a <hi>Battery:</hi> And the <hi>Certifying</hi> of 
<hi>a Hundred and Fifty Perrots</hi> into the <hi>Service,</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Of</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> will be of Greater <hi>Effect,</hi> then the <hi>Drawing-up</hi>
of <hi>Ten Thousand men in Arms,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Against</hi> it. Now <hi>These 
Methods</hi> lye All <hi>Open</hi> still, only they are somewhat more <hi>About</hi>. Now as to 
<hi>Dangers Remote,</hi> or <hi>Nearer hand; Dangers of Design,</hi> or <hi>Dangers of 
Practice:</hi> All the <hi>Preparatories, &amp; Dispositions to Mischief,</hi> in their <hi>Secret 
Impulses,</hi> and <hi>Causes,</hi> are as <hi>Vigorous</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Now</hi>, as <hi rend="bold">Ever</hi>
they were, that is to say, within Two or Three Motions of a <hi>Publique Violence:</hi> Only 
This Difference in the Case, that we have <hi>Hitherto,</hi> been in the <hi>Greatest 
Danger</hi> of our <hi>Profess'd,</hi> &amp; <hi>Open Enemies:</hi> And <hi>Now,</hi> God 
bless us from our <hi>Pretending Friends:</hi> For all on a Sudden, the <hi>Trimmers</hi> are 
come-up to be <hi>Stark Church-of-England-men;</hi> And the <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> gotten a 
<hi>Form Higher,</hi> into the <hi>Seat</hi> or <hi>Classes</hi> of the <hi>Trimmers</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Thou art <hi>Well, neither Full nor Fasting</hi>. Neither <hi>Fanatique,</hi> nor 
<hi>Trimmer,</hi> nor <hi>Church-of-England-man</hi> I perceive, will please ye; The 
<hi>Controversy</hi> of a <hi rend="bold">New King</hi>; or a <hi rend="bold">Common-Wealth</hi>, is <hi>Out of 
Doors;</hi> The Question of <hi rend="bold">Liberty of Conscience</hi>; The <hi>Privilege</hi> of 
<hi>Private Meetings</hi> for <hi rend="bold">Religious Worship</hi>; And a <hi>Challenge</hi> of 
<hi>Dispensation</hi> from the <hi>Rites, Ceremonies, and</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Discipline</hi>
               <hi>of the 
Church, are</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">All layd aside</hi>. And All This will not serve the <hi>Turn</hi> yet. Now 
if Men go to <hi>Church;</hi> Take <hi>Tests,</hi> make <hi>Declarations;</hi> And <hi>Do</hi>
and <hi>Perform</hi> All that the <hi>Law Requires</hi> of'em; where's the <hi>Danger</hi> of 
These People I beseech ye? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     Not in their <hi>coming over</hi> with their <hi>Bodies,</hi> but in <hi>Staying 
behind,</hi> in their <hi>Good Wills,</hi> and <hi>Affections:</hi> Nay, and in their 
<hi>Communicating</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Morning,</hi> and in the 
<hi>Afternoon,</hi> with the <hi>Schism:</hi> And pray will you Note in them, One Thing 
<hi>More</hi> too. 'Tis worth the while, when they <hi>Ramble</hi> from their <hi>Own 
Parish,</hi> to <hi>Observe</hi> whither they go: For I have known the very <hi>Streets 
Throng'd,</hi> out of Distance of <hi>Hearing One Word</hi> that the <hi>Minister says,</hi>
with the <hi>Same Superstition,</hi> that the <hi>Quakers Flock</hi> to the <hi>Door,</hi> when 
they are <hi>Lock'd-out</hi> of the <hi>Meeting-House:</hi> In which Case, It has yet the 
<hi>Semblance</hi> of a <hi>Private Meeting;</hi> And in Truth, looks liker a <hi>Political 
Muster,</hi> then a <hi>Religious Exercise:</hi> But Heark ye for One Word, before we go any 
further; Suppose a Man should have sayd about the <hi>Beginning</hi> of <hi>July Last,</hi> in 
a <hi>Brisk Reply</hi> to a <hi>Reflexion</hi> made upon the <hi>Western-Rebells;</hi> (at that 
time in their <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi>) [<hi rend="bold">The King has as Loyal Subjects in 
That Army as Any are in T'other</hi>.] Wouldst thou have me, in Construction of 
<hi>Common Sense,</hi> and <hi>Honesty,</hi> look upon <hi>That Person,</hi> to be, 
Effectually <hi rend="bold">Come over</hi>, and in the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>a True Church-of-England-man;</hi>
only for <hi>Keeping</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> with his <hi>Heels,</hi> when he 
<hi>Breaks</hi> it, with his <hi>Tongue,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine?</hi> Now this is more then I Owe 
ye, upon the Matter in hand: For you have Carry'd the <hi>Question</hi> quite <hi>back</hi>
again, from the <hi>Non-Con-Ministers,</hi> to the <hi>Generality,</hi> and the 
<hi>Multitude</hi> of the <hi>Dissenters:</hi> which is a Point Wholly <hi>Excepted,</hi> and out 
of the <hi>Limits</hi> of <hi>Our Debate:</hi> For All their <hi>Conventicles</hi> without a 
<hi>Mouth,</hi> are <hi>Monsters;</hi> Meer <hi>Nullities,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bilks,</hi> without a 
<hi>Teacher:</hi> So that I have <hi>Restrain'd</hi> my <hi>Applications,</hi> Singly, to the 
<hi>Rabbi's</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> as <hi>Including,</hi> and <hi>Implying</hi> the 
<hi>Sense,</hi> and the <hi>Intent</hi> of their <hi>Disciples:</hi> Nay and <hi>so far 
Including</hi> it, that they are <hi>Barely,</hi> the <hi>Passive Instruments</hi> of their 
<hi>Leaders</hi>. Now These <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Divided Parties,</hi> are a sort of 
People, that do not, by any Means, fall within the <hi>Charitable Prospect</hi> of <hi>Your 
Qualifications:</hi> For they <hi>Stand-off,</hi> in <hi>Contempt,</hi> and <hi>Defyance</hi> of 
the <hi>Orders,</hi> &amp; <hi>Censures</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and of the <hi>Law,</hi> as 
much at <hi>This Instant,</hi> as <hi>ever</hi> they did. Their <hi>Followers Maintain,</hi> and 
<hi>Support</hi> them in That <hi>Stubbornness</hi> of <hi>Disobedience;</hi> And so the 
<hi>Opposition</hi> stands yet <hi>Firm,</hi> in <hi>Effect,</hi> though with <hi>Less Noise</hi>
of <hi>Menace,</hi> and <hi>Tumult</hi>. The <hi>Branches,</hi> 'tis True, are <hi>Lopt;</hi> but 
the <hi>Root,</hi> not so much as <hi>Touch'd;</hi> Nay, and in such a Condition of 
<hi>Vegetative Virtue,</hi> and <hi>Vigour,</hi> that it wants nothing but <hi>Time,</hi> and a 
<hi>Favourable Season</hi> to make it <hi>Sprout</hi> again. And This you may Assure your 
self of, that Nothing less than an <hi>Utter,</hi> an <hi>Open,</hi> a <hi>Solemn,</hi> and an 
<hi>Irrevocable Divorce,</hi> betwixt <hi>These Libertine-Seducers,</hi> and Those that have 
been <hi>Trepann'd,</hi> and <hi>Inveigled,</hi> out of the <hi>Bosom</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi>
into the <hi>Arms</hi> of the <hi>Schism:</hi> Nothing I say, less then Some such 
<hi>Unalterable Act,</hi> or <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Separation,</hi> can ever <hi>Secure,</hi>
either the <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>State</hi> from the <hi>Pernicious Consequences</hi> of 
this <hi>Intelligence:</hi> For betwixt <hi>Blind Pity,</hi> and <hi>Foolish Zeal,</hi> on the 
<hi>One</hi> hand, and all the <hi>Arts,</hi> of <hi>Moving,</hi> and <hi>Provoking</hi> Those 
<hi>Passions,</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi> on the <hi>Other,</hi> there is <hi>kept-up,</hi> and 
<hi>Cherish'd,</hi> a <hi>Communication</hi> of <hi>Reciprocal Kindness,</hi> between them 
that keeps the <hi>Fire alive</hi> still in the <hi>Embers,</hi> 'till by <hi>Degrees,</hi> it 
<hi>Blows-up</hi> All at last into a <hi>Common Flame</hi>. Now take away <hi>These 
Bellows,</hi> and <hi>T'other Sparks,</hi> and a man may <hi>Sleep</hi> in his <hi>Bed,</hi>
without <hi>Dreaming</hi> of <hi>Conflagrations,</hi> or the <hi>Dread</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Rising with 
his Throat Cut</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     I will not Excuse some <hi>Hot-Headed Blades,</hi> that let their 
<hi>Tongues</hi> run before their <hi>Wits;</hi> And make it a Point of <hi>Honour,</hi> to 
<hi>Brave</hi> All the <hi>Terrors</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Dungeons,</hi> in defence of 
the <hi>Cause</hi> that they have <hi>Undertaken</hi>. The <hi>Less said,</hi> the 
<hi>Better;</hi> Though a Body cannot, in <hi>Generosity,</hi> but have some sort of 
<hi>Compassion,</hi> for a Man that Suffers <hi>Death,</hi> with <hi>Constancy of Mind,</hi>
Even in a <hi rend="bold">Mistaken Cause</hi>, if it be according to his <hi>Conscience</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     If these <hi>Impressions</hi> were <hi>Inbred,</hi> and the <hi>Errors</hi> purely 
their <hi>Own,</hi> it would be a <hi>Point,</hi> not only of <hi>Good Nature,</hi> but of 
<hi>Common Justice,</hi> and <hi>Humanity,</hi> to have a <hi>Tenderness</hi> for 
<hi>People</hi> under an <hi>Invincible Mistake:</hi> But you have Started the <hi>Strongest 
Argument</hi> in the World, against your <hi>self</hi> here, by <hi>Enforcing</hi> the 
<hi>Necessity</hi> of Clearing the <hi>Stage</hi> of the <hi>Seditious Oracles,</hi> that 
<hi>Inspire These Desperate Resolutions</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Why All matter of <hi>Violence, Heat</hi> of <hi>Dispute,</hi> and 
<hi>Clamour</hi> of <hi>Argument,</hi> is at an <hi>End</hi>. You hear no more of your 
<hi>Scottish,</hi> and <hi>Western Declarations;</hi> No more <hi>Competitors</hi> for the 
<hi>Crown;</hi> or <hi>Confederates</hi> for a <hi>Republique:</hi> And therefore prethee, 
<hi>let</hi> us be at <hi>Peace</hi> while we <hi>May</hi> be at <hi>Peace;</hi> and do not stand 
<hi>Puzzling</hi> the <hi>People</hi> with <hi>Danger,</hi> where <hi>No Danger is</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     Soft, and Fair, <hi>Trimmer;</hi> those <hi>Declarations, Practices,</hi> and 
<hi>Attempts,</hi> are not to be <hi>Repeated</hi> again in the <hi>same Age:</hi> But there are 
<hi>more ways to the Wood then One:</hi> And 'tis All a case, to a man that's <hi>Robb'd,</hi>
whether the <hi>Thieves</hi> came in at the <hi>Door,</hi> or at the <hi>Window</hi>. 'Tis very 
Right, That, since the Breaking of the <hi>Rebellion,</hi> the <hi>Non-Cons</hi> lay their 
<hi>Fingers</hi> upon their <hi>Mouths;</hi> and not <hi>One Word</hi> of <hi>Late,</hi> upon 
the Subject of <hi>Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Properties;</hi> or of the Danger of <hi>Tyranny,</hi>
and of <hi>Arbitrary Power:</hi> But All other <hi>Grievances</hi> are <hi rend="bold">Now</hi>
               <hi>Swallow'd-up</hi> in <hi>One:</hi> They are All in <hi>Tears</hi> for fear of the 
<hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> and <hi>That's the Topique that's now Carry'd-on, through All 
Shapes, Figures, and Disguises</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     <hi rend="bold">We shall have fine Work, Next Bout!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi>, Printed for <hi>Charles Brome,</hi> at the Gun in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard. 
</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a5" type="Article">
            <head>Vol. 3, Numb. 202</head>
            <head>THE OBSERVATOR.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>The way of Promoting</hi> Fears, <hi>and</hi> Jealousies.  <hi>The</hi> People <hi>meerly</hi> Passive <hi>in the Bus'ness</hi>.  <hi>Both Parts seem to</hi> Contend <hi>for the</hi> Same Common Principles. <hi>The</hi> Rise of Jelousies.</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">Saturday</hi>, August 21. 1686.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TRIMMER</hi>.     The <hi>Accommodating</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Words</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Phrases</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Texts</hi> to the Matter in hand, with the 
Interjecting, here and there, of Certain <hi>Emphatical Winks,</hi> and 
<hi>Innuendo's,</hi> to the <hi>Common People,</hi> will do the 
Bus'ness of <hi>Fears and Jelousies,</hi> you need never <hi>Doubt</hi>
it, without any more Ceremony. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OBSERVATOR</hi>.     I do no more <hi>Doubt</hi> it, then I do, that a 
<hi rend="bold">Proper Remedy</hi>; <hi rend="bold">Rightly Prepar'd</hi>; and 
<hi rend="bold">Administer'd</hi> in the <hi>Due</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Time</hi> and 
<hi rend="bold">Proportion</hi>, will <hi>Work</hi> such or such an <hi>Effect</hi>. 
But the <hi>Skill</hi> lyes, in the <hi rend="bold">Judgment</hi> of the 
<hi rend="bold">Distemper</hi>; The <hi rend="bold">Constitution</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Patient</hi>; 
The <hi rend="bold">Choice</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Physick</hi>; The Prescription of the 
<hi rend="bold">Composition</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Preparation</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Dos</hi>. 
Now <hi>Your</hi> way of <hi>Operating,</hi> is only the 
<hi rend="bold">Mechanicall</hi>
               <hi>Part of the Bus'ness;</hi> and no more, then 
the giving of a <hi>Box,</hi> a <hi>Gally-pot,</hi> or a <hi>Glass,</hi> with a 
Note of <hi>Directions,</hi> out of <hi>One</hi> hand into <hi>Another:</hi>
which Any <hi>Porter</hi> that Plyes at the <hi>Next Corner,</hi> would 
do as <hi>Dext'rously,</hi> as ever a <hi>Doctor</hi> of the 
<hi>College</hi>. The <hi>Difficulty,</hi> and the <hi>Mystery,</hi> is 
<hi rend="bold">Over</hi>, before <hi>You</hi> have any thing to <hi>Do</hi> with it: 
The <hi>Poysonous,</hi> and <hi>Intoxicating Draught,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Prepar'd</hi>; The <hi>Multitude</hi> set a-<hi rend="bold">Gaping</hi> for't, and 
<hi rend="bold">Your</hi>
               <hi>Office,</hi> is only at last, to <hi>Pour it down their 
Throats</hi>. There's Matter of <hi>History,</hi> and <hi>Fact,</hi>
enough, 'this true, to <hi>Satisfy any man,</hi> that People may be 
made as <hi>Mad</hi> with <hi>Cant,</hi> and <hi>Gibberish,</hi> as if they 
had taken <hi>Henbane;</hi> and that <hi>the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Sting</hi>
               <hi>of</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Jelousy</hi>, will put them out of their <hi>Wits</hi> as soon as 
<hi>the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Biting</hi>
               <hi>of a</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Mad-Dog</hi>: But we are in 
the <hi>Dark</hi> all this while, for the <hi rend="bold">Rise</hi>, the 
<hi rend="bold">Progress</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Methods</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Enflaming</hi>
               <hi>Jelousies,</hi> to bring'em up to that <hi>Pitch</hi>. Prethee let me 
Understand a little of their <hi rend="bold">Birth</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Growth</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Discipline</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Education</hi>; How they are <hi rend="bold">Fed</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Nourish'd</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Entertain'd</hi>? What's the <hi rend="bold">End</hi>, 
and <hi rend="bold">Use</hi> of them? What <hi rend="bold">Language</hi> do they 
<hi>Speak;</hi> or how comes it to pass, that the <hi>Same</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Words</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Phrases</hi>, without <hi>Any Intelligence</hi>
with <hi>Grammar, Logique, Common Usage,</hi> or <hi>Propriety,</hi>
should <hi>Transport</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Some</hi>
               <hi>Men</hi> into <hi>Outrages, 
Palpitations of the Heart, Horrors,</hi> and <hi>Tremblings,</hi> both of 
<hi>Mind,</hi> and of <hi>Body;</hi> and yet Work no more upon 
<hi rend="bold">Others</hi>, then they <hi>did,</hi> before the very <hi rend="bold">Letters</hi>
of'em were taken out of the <hi>Alphabet?</hi> I do not call ye to a 
<hi>Strict Shrift</hi> upon <hi>Every Point,</hi> but I Expect you shall say 
something to the <hi>Whole Matter;</hi> for a <hi>Few Words,</hi> in 
<hi rend="bold">Order</hi>, will give a man more <hi>Light</hi> to the <hi>Reason</hi>
of a thing, then as many <hi>Volumes,</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Confusion</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     You are in the <hi>Right;</hi> that the <hi>Craft</hi> lies in 
the <hi rend="bold">Project</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Preparatory</hi>
               <hi>Manage</hi> of 
this Affair, and that the <hi>Danger</hi> is gone too <hi>Far,</hi> when 
the <hi>Mine</hi> is already <hi>Wrought;</hi> the <hi>Powder 
Dispos'd,</hi> and nothing wanting to the <hi>Final Execution</hi> of 
the <hi>Mischief,</hi> but the <hi>Lighting</hi> of the <hi>Match,</hi> and 
the Applying of the <hi>Coal</hi> to the <hi>Train</hi>. You have 
<hi>Well</hi> and <hi>Truly</hi> enough <hi>Observed,</hi> the 
<hi>Wonderfull Force,</hi> that <hi>Some Certain</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Words</hi>, 
and <hi rend="bold">Phrases</hi> have; upon the <hi>Affections</hi> of the 
<hi>Multitude;</hi> without the Least <hi>Shadow</hi> of any 
<hi rend="bold">Logical</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Grammatical</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">Philosophical</hi>
               <hi>Reason</hi> for the <hi>Operation</hi> of them. Now you must know, 
that <hi>These</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Words</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Phrases</hi>, are made 
<hi>Use</hi> of, and <hi>Understood,</hi> in the way of a <hi rend="bold">Cypher</hi>, 
or a <hi rend="bold">Jargon</hi>, and not according to the <hi>Ordinary 
Acceptation</hi> of them, in a <hi>Regular</hi> way of <hi>Writing,</hi> or 
of <hi>Speaking;</hi> So that, Effectually, the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of such 
<hi>Words,</hi> and <hi>Phrases,</hi> is given for <hi>Granted;</hi> and 
how they come to <hi>Obtain that Force,</hi> remains the <hi>Single 
Question</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>Now towards the <hi>Understanding</hi> of this Matter, you must 
Consider, that no <hi>State</hi> can be <hi>Supplanted,</hi> but by 
<hi>Turning</hi> the <hi>Peoples Hearts,</hi> against the <hi>Persons,</hi>
&amp; the <hi>Actions</hi> of their <hi>Superiors:</hi> So that in <hi>All 
Conspiracies</hi> to <hi>Destroy</hi> a <hi>Government,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Fears 
&amp; Jelousies</hi>, are <hi>the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Corner Stone</hi>
               <hi>of the 
Babel</hi>. Their <hi rend="bold">Hearts</hi> are no sooner <hi>Lost,</hi> but they 
withdraw their <hi rend="bold">Bodies</hi> too, and so, by <hi>Degrees, Erect</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Laws</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Religions</hi> of their <hi rend="bold">Own</hi>; and look 
upon themselves, by This time, as in <hi>Another Common-wealth</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     'Tis most <hi>Certainly True;</hi> and that in this 
<hi>Separation,</hi> they set-up an <hi>Interest</hi> of <hi>Direct</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Spite</hi>, as well as <hi rend="bold">Opposition</hi>, to That of the 
<hi>Church,</hi> and of the <hi>State</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     This is the very <hi rend="bold">Course</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Progress</hi>
of a <hi>Popular Jelousy:</hi> But pray take Notice as we go, that the 
<hi>People,</hi> are thus far, <hi>Meerly</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Passive</hi>; and 
<hi>Contribute No Otherwise,</hi> to the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the 
<hi>Publique,</hi> then <hi>a</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Snapping Sea</hi> does, to the 
<hi>Sinking</hi> of a <hi>Vessell,</hi> when the <hi>Billows</hi> are 
<hi>Hurry'd-on</hi> by the <hi>Violence</hi> of an <hi rend="bold">Irresistible 
Tempest</hi>: if the <hi>Winds</hi> would but let the <hi>Waves 
alone,</hi> they'd be <hi>Quiet</hi>. When they come once to Gather 
into [<hi rend="bold">Private Meetings</hi>,] (or as you call them, 
<hi rend="bold">Conventicles</hi>) you may <hi>Then</hi> accompt upon it, that 
they are as good as put to <hi>School,</hi> to <hi>Learn</hi> the 
<hi rend="bold">Mystery</hi> of their <hi>Profession</hi>. For there are 
<hi rend="bold">Canting-Schools</hi>, as well as <hi rend="bold">Reading-Schools</hi>; and under This 
<hi>Discipline,</hi> they come by <hi>Insensible Degrees,</hi> to part 
with their <hi>English</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Tongue</hi>, as well as with their 
<hi>English</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Principles</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Manners</hi>. Nay, and 
Effectually, to take up such <hi>Uncouth, Novel,</hi> and 
<hi>Strange</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Thoughts</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Opinions</hi>, and 
<hi rend="bold">Practices</hi>, that it looks, as if the <hi rend="bold">English-Man</hi>, the 
<hi rend="bold">Christian</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Subject</hi>, were <hi rend="bold">all lost in a 
Disguise</hi>. They are now, you must know, under <hi rend="bold">New 
Lords</hi>, and Consequently, under <hi rend="bold">New Laws</hi>; where they 
are <hi>Train'd-up</hi> to <hi>New Ways</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Understanding</hi>
Things, and to a <hi>New Idiome</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Expressing</hi> them. 
<hi rend="bold">Religion</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Law</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Government</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Conscience</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Good Manners</hi>, are so <hi>Sacred</hi> in 
<hi rend="bold">Themselves</hi>, that the <hi>Worst</hi> of Men cannot but 
<hi>Pretend</hi> a <hi>Veneration</hi> for them; but how to <hi>Baffle,</hi>
or to <hi>Elude</hi> the <hi>Force,</hi> the <hi>Obligation,</hi> and the 
<hi>Authority</hi> of them; and, at the Same Time, to set-up for the 
<hi>Asserters,</hi> and <hi>Supporters</hi> of <hi>These Publique Rights, 
Privileges,</hi> and <hi>Duties, There</hi> lies the <hi>Difficulty</hi> of the 
<hi>Understanding</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     That is to say, how to <hi>Resolve</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Religion</hi>, 
into an <hi>Empty</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Notion</hi>: To <hi rend="bold">Talk Christianity</hi> into 
a <hi rend="bold">Paradox</hi>; and, with <hi rend="bold">Christ</hi> in our <hi>Mouths,</hi> at 
<hi>London,</hi> to <hi>fall down,</hi> and <hi>Worship</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Mahomet</hi>, in <hi>Buda:</hi> How to <hi>Confound</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Gods</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Governments Friends</hi> and 
<hi rend="bold">Enemies</hi>, so as to make the <hi>Common People</hi> take 
<hi>One</hi> for <hi>T'other</hi>. Now This can be no way done, but by 
setting-up the <hi rend="bold">Counterfeit</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Religion</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Law</hi>, 
and <hi rend="bold">Conscience</hi>, against the <hi>Genuine,</hi> and 
<hi>Authentique</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Original</hi>; and by making <hi rend="bold">Evil</hi>, to 
be <hi rend="bold">Good</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Good</hi>, to be <hi rend="bold">Evil</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     You must <hi>Note,</hi> further, that in This 
<hi>Opposition,</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Main Cause</hi> appears to be the <hi>very 
Same,</hi> on <hi>Both sides;</hi> and <hi>Both Parts</hi> seem to 
<hi>Contend,</hi> for <hi>the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Same Common Principles</hi>, of 
<hi>Divine Worship,</hi> and of <hi>Civil Obedience</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     Only the <hi>One</hi> Flies to the <hi>Invisible Lights</hi>
and <hi>Dictates</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in Matter of <hi rend="bold">Religion</hi>; 
(taking <hi rend="bold">Fancy</hi> for <hi rend="bold">Revelation</hi>) and, in the Matter of 
<hi rend="bold">Government</hi>, has Recourse to Certain <hi>Unaccountable 
Whimsies,</hi> of [<hi rend="bold">Powers Reserv'd</hi>,] where there 
<hi>never was any Power at all; &amp; These Fooleries,</hi> they 
<hi>Trump</hi> upon the <hi>Little People,</hi> under the <hi>Pompous 
Name</hi> of [<hi>FUNDAMENTALS;</hi>] while the 
<hi>Rulers,</hi> on the <hi>Other</hi> hand, Stick to the <hi rend="bold">Law</hi>, to 
the <hi rend="bold">Text</hi>, and to the <hi>Approved Senses</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Best 
Interpreters</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Both</hi>, for their <hi>Guide</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Very Good! And after they have <hi>Departed</hi> from 
the <hi rend="bold">Common Rule</hi>, and <hi>Divided</hi> themselves from the 
<hi rend="bold">Common Interest</hi>; it is but Reasonable to <hi>Expect,</hi> that 
they will Set-up <hi rend="bold">Another Interest</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Another Rule</hi> to 
<hi>Themselves</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     Well<hi>!</hi> But how do they <hi>Manage That 
Province</hi> all this while, as to the <hi>Subject,</hi> I mean, that we 
were <hi>Speaking</hi> of? 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Why their way is, only to put <hi>Religion,</hi> and 
<hi>Government</hi> in <hi>Another Dress;</hi> but under the 
<hi rend="bold">Name</hi>, of [<hi rend="bold">Religion</hi>,] and 
[<hi>Government,</hi>] <hi>Still;</hi> and then to lay on a 
<hi>Superstructure,</hi> Answerable to the <hi>Foundation;</hi> I speak 
of the <hi rend="bold">Leaders</hi> only; for their <hi rend="bold">Disciples</hi> are <hi>Blanck 
Paper;</hi> and ready for <hi>any Impression</hi>. They <hi>Talk,</hi> to 
the <hi rend="bold">Ears</hi>, and to the <hi rend="bold">Passions</hi> of their <hi>Hearers,</hi>
not to their <hi rend="bold">Understandings</hi>: and their <hi>Auditors</hi> gather 
more of their <hi>Meaning,</hi> from their <hi>Gestures, Actions, 
Countenances,</hi> and from <hi>Pathetical Tones,</hi> then from the 
<hi>Words Themselves</hi>. As for <hi>Sense,</hi> or <hi>No Sense,</hi>
'tis <hi>all a Case;</hi> for 'tis the <hi>Jingle,</hi> not the <hi>Matter,</hi>
that does <hi>Their Bus'ness</hi>. The <hi>Less</hi> the People 
<hi rend="bold">Understand</hi>, the <hi>More</hi> they are <hi rend="bold">Edify'd</hi>; for they 
take the <hi>Congruities</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Carnal Reason</hi>, for <hi rend="bold">Vain 
Philosophy</hi>; and <hi rend="bold">Incomprehensible Nonsense</hi>, passes 
for <hi>the Work of the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Light Within</hi>. Their <hi>Religion</hi>
lies alltogther in <hi rend="bold">Groan</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Rapture</hi>: <hi>They 
Sacrifice to the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Unknown God</hi>; and in One Word; They 
<hi>Supply</hi> the <hi>Want</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Knowledge</hi>, with an 
<hi>Excess</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Zeal</hi>; and when they cannot 
<hi>Understand</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Plain English</hi> of a <hi>Discourse,</hi>
they Wrap Themselves up in the <hi rend="bold">Mystery</hi>. The making of a 
<hi>Party,</hi> &amp; the Saving of their own <hi>Skins,</hi> are the 
<hi>Two Main Points</hi> of the <hi>Leaders;</hi> and therefore, they 
<hi>Cover</hi> themselves under <hi rend="bold">Ambiguity</hi>, &amp; 
<hi rend="bold">Riddle</hi>; &amp; Compass those Matters, by <hi>Theatrical 
Gesticulations,</hi> &amp; <hi>Actions,</hi> which they dare not 
<hi>Venture</hi> upon, in <hi>Words</hi> at <hi>Length,</hi> or by the 
<hi>Dint</hi> of <hi>Argument;</hi> for there is no <hi>Law</hi> against 
<hi>making of</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Faces</hi>, <hi>and Dusting of</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Cushions</hi>, They are told <hi>Mightily,</hi> and <hi>Plainly,</hi> or 
<hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> but in such a <hi>Manner,</hi> that they 
will <hi>Never Allow</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">God</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Government</hi> to 
be <hi>Both of a side</hi>. <hi>Schism</hi> is Dignified with the 
<hi>Name</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Conscience</hi>; the Story of their 
<hi>Grievances,</hi> is the <hi>Bitterest</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Satyrs</hi>; Their very 
<hi rend="bold">Petitions</hi> have the force of <hi>Invectives;</hi> and the 
<hi>Smoother,</hi> the <hi>Softer,</hi> you find the <hi>Surface</hi> of 
them, the <hi>Falser,</hi> and the more <hi>Dangerous</hi> they are at 
the <hi>Bottom:</hi> For betwixt the <hi rend="bold">Persecution</hi> that is 
<hi>Insinuated,</hi> on the part of the <hi>Government,</hi> &amp; the 
<hi rend="bold">Innocence</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Piety</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Modesty</hi>, on 
that of the <hi rend="bold">Sufferers</hi>, Nothing can more Provoke, a 
<hi>Horror,</hi> and <hi>Indignation</hi> for the <hi>One,</hi> or a 
<hi>Tenderness,</hi> &amp; <hi>Compassion,</hi> for the <hi>Other</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     That is to say, among Those that are not <hi>Well 
Enform'd,</hi> in the <hi>Reason,</hi> and the <hi>Equity of the Cause in 
Question</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     Come Come. I tell ye <hi>Nakedly</hi> how things 
<hi rend="bold">Are</hi>, and not how they <hi rend="bold">Ought</hi> to be: and I speak of 
<hi>Those Men</hi> too, that neither <hi rend="bold">Do</hi>, nor <hi rend="bold">Will</hi>, nor 
<hi rend="bold">Can</hi> make a <hi>Right Judgment</hi> upon the Matter in 
<hi>Issue</hi>. They do not take down <hi>Reasons</hi> in 
<hi rend="bold">Connexion</hi>; neither do their <hi>Teachers</hi> so much as 
<hi rend="bold">Offer</hi> at'em; But <hi>their Work</hi> is, only to <hi>Feed</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Itching Ears</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Humours</hi>, with <hi>New-Quoyn'd 
Words. Affectate Phrases:</hi> And briefly, to <hi>Instruct</hi> their 
<hi>Disciples,</hi> by <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Tokens,</hi> like so many 
<hi>Dancing Horses</hi> to fall <hi rend="bold">Lame upon all Four</hi>, for the 
<hi>Pope;</hi> to <hi rend="bold">come-over</hi>, for the <hi>Grand Vizier;</hi> and at 
the very <hi>Sound</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Babylon</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Anti-Christ</hi>, or 
<hi rend="bold">Absolute Power</hi>, to <hi rend="bold">Snort</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Boggle</hi>, as if 
they <hi>Smelt Fire</hi>. If I may tell ye the <hi>Arrant Truth,</hi> and 
<hi>Simplicity</hi> of my <hi>Heart;</hi> This is the very <hi rend="bold">Train</hi> of 
a <hi rend="bold">Popular Institution</hi>. They are <hi rend="bold">Tutor'd</hi>, and 
<hi rend="bold">Inur'd</hi>, to the <hi rend="bold">Assuming</hi> of such and such 
<hi>Passions,</hi> upon such and such <hi>Occasions;</hi> and they do 
All their <hi>Ayres,</hi> and <hi>Tricks,</hi> by the Direction of the 
<hi>Hand,</hi> or <hi>Eye</hi>. <hi>They Dance</hi> to <hi>Sounds, Hints, 
Nodds, Forms,</hi> and <hi>Syllables;</hi> not to the force of <hi>Fair 
Reasonings,</hi> and <hi>Natural Conclusion;</hi> Nay, they are 
<hi rend="bold">Taught</hi>, when to be <hi>Angry;</hi> when to be <hi>Pleas'd;</hi>
and their very <hi>Inclinations,</hi> and <hi>Aversions,</hi> are none of 
their <hi>Own, Neither:</hi> The <hi>Whole Bus'ness,</hi> in short, is 
<hi rend="bold">Artifice</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Manage</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Practice</hi>; for <hi>All 
their</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Mistakes</hi>, <hi>and</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Mis-understandings</hi>, 
<hi>take the</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Same Biass</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs</hi>.     I do <hi>Observe,</hi> indeed, that they Shelter 
themselves under the <hi>Dark Prophets,</hi> and the 
<hi>Revelation</hi>. The <hi>Number of the Beast,</hi> they have all at 
their <hi>Fingers Ends;</hi> the <hi>Geneva-bibles</hi> are 
<hi>Thumm'd</hi> over and over, at the <hi>Same Texts:</hi> As upon the 
Subject of the <hi>Groves,</hi> &amp; the <hi>High Places, Christian 
Liberty, Will-Worship, Humane Inventions, Idolatry, Superstition,</hi>
&amp;c. There's not a <hi>Verse</hi> in the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> against 
<hi>Persecution,</hi> but makes them Shake their Heads at the 
<hi>Government</hi>. <hi rend="bold">Popery</hi> by <hi>Interpretation,</hi> is 
<hi rend="bold">Episcopacy</hi>: The <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Subject</hi>, has an 
<hi>Aking Tooth</hi> at the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Prince</hi>: 
but finally; such and such <hi rend="bold">Terms</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Forms</hi> of 
<hi rend="bold">Speaking</hi>, are by Common Consent, to pass for 
<hi>Current,</hi> under such or such a <hi rend="bold">Sense</hi>, and 
<hi rend="bold">Meaning</hi>, how <hi>Contrary</hi> soever, to their <hi>Proper,</hi>
and <hi>Genuine Signification,</hi> or <hi>Import</hi>. But this speaks 
only to the <hi rend="bold">Propagating</hi> of <hi>Jelousies,</hi> not to the 
<hi rend="bold">Rise</hi> of them. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trim</hi>.     If you Ask me the [<hi rend="bold">Rise</hi>] of 
<hi>Jelousies,</hi> I must <hi>Answer</hi> ye, that they are 
<hi>Begotten</hi> betwixt <hi rend="bold">Ambition</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Avarice</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Hypocrisy</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Craft</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Malice</hi>, and 
<hi rend="bold">Disloyalty</hi>, on the <hi>One</hi> side; and <hi rend="bold">Ignorance</hi>, 
<hi rend="bold">Obstinacy</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Blind Zeal</hi>, and an <hi rend="bold">Impetuous 
Temerity</hi>, on the <hi>Other</hi>. 
</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Brome,</hi> at the Gun in St. 
<hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 
</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

