<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Seven Seas</title>
            <author>Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/3297</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106002962</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106002969</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
      </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>TEI XML version of  
	<relatedItem type="other"
                            target="http://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/k/kipling/rudyard/seven/"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notAfter="1896"/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <figure>
            <graphic url="http://www.ota.ox.ac.uk/Graphics/3297/001.png"
                     width="153px"
                     height="115px"/>
         </figure>
         <div>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://www.ota.ox.ac.uk/Graphics/3297/002.png"
                        width="367px"
                        height="189px"/>
            </figure>
            <lg>
               <l>The Cities are full of pride,</l>
               <l>  Challenging each to each —</l>
               <l>This from her mountain-side,</l>
               <l>  That from her burthened beach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They count their ships full tale —</l>
               <l>  Their corn and oil and wine,</l>
               <l>Derrick and loom and bale,</l>
               <l>  And rampart’s gun-flecked line;</l>
               <l>City by city they hail:</l>
               <l>  “Hast aught to match with mine?”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And the men that breed from them</l>
               <l>  They traffic up and down,</l>
               <l>But cling to their cities’ hem</l>
               <l>  As a child to the mother’s gown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they talk with the stranger bands,</l>
               <l>  Dazed and newly alone;</l>
               <l>When they walk in the stranger lands,</l>
               <l>  By roaring streets unknown;</l>
               <l>Blessing her where she stands</l>
               <l>  For strength above their own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(On high to hold her fame</l>
               <l>  That stands all fame beyond,</l>
               <l>By oath to back the same,</l>
               <l>  Most faithful-foolish-fond;</l>
               <l>Making her mere-breathed name</l>
               <l>  Their bond upon their bond.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So thank I God my birth</l>
               <l>  Fell not in isles aside —</l>
               <l>Waste headlands of the earth,</l>
               <l>  Or warring tribes untried —</l>
               <l>But that she lent me worth</l>
               <l>  And gave me right to pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Surely in toil or fray</l>
               <l>  Under an alien sky,</l>
               <l>Comfort it is to say:</l>
               <l>  “Of no mean city am I.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(Neither by service nor fee</l>
               <l>  Come I to mine estate —</l>
               <l>Mother of Cities to me,</l>
               <l>  For I was born in her gate,</l>
               <l>Between the palms and the sea,</l>
               <l>  Where the world-end steamers wait.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now for this debt I owe,</l>
               <l>  And for her far-borne cheer</l>
               <l>Must I make haste and go</l>
               <l>  With tribute to her pier.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And she shall touch and remit</l>
               <l>  After the use of kings</l>
               <l>(Orderly, ancient, fit)</l>
               <l>  My deep-sea plunderings,</l>
               <l>And purchase in all lands.</l>
               <l>  And this we do for a sign</l>
               <l>  Her power is over mine,</l>
               <l>And mine I hold at her hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <div xml:id="section2">
               <head>A Song of the English.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Fair is our lot — O goodly is our heritage!<lb/>
(Humble ye, my people, and be fearful in your mirth!)<lb/>
  For the Lord our God Most High<lb/>
  He hath made the deep as dry,<lb/>
He hath smote for us a pathway to the ends of all the Earth!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Yea, though we sinned — and our rulers went from righteousness —<lb/>
Deep in all dishonour though we stained our garments’ hem.<lb/>
  Oh be ye not dismayed,<lb/>
  Though we stumbled and we strayed,<lb/>
We were led by evil counsellors — the Lord shall deal with them.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Hold ye the Faith — the Faith our Fathers sealèd us;<lb/>
Whoring not with visions — overwise and overstale.<lb/>
  Except ye pay the Lord<lb/>
  Single heart and single sword,<lb/>
Of your children in their bondage shall He ask them treble-tale.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Keep ye the Law — be swift in all obedience.<lb/>
Clear the land of evil, drive the road and bridge the ford.<lb/>
  Make ye sure to each his own<lb/>
  That he reap what he hath sown;<lb/>
By the peace among Our peoples let men know we serve the Lord.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <p>* * * * *</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Hear now a song — a song of broken interludes —<lb/>
A song of little cunning; of a singer nothing worth.<lb/>
  Through the naked words and mean<lb/>
  May ye see the truth between<lb/>
As the singer knew and touched it in the ends of all the Earth!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <p>The Coastwise Lights.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Our brows are wreathed with spindrift and the weed is on our knees;<lb/>
Our loins are battered ‘neath us by the swinging, smoking seas.<lb/>
From reef and rock and skerry — over headland, ness and voe —<lb/>
The Coastwise Lights of England watch the ships of England go!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Through the endless summer evenings, on the lineless, level floors;<lb/>
Through the yelling Channel tempest when the syren hoots and roars —<lb/>
By day the dipping house-flag and by night the rocket’s trail —<lb/>
As the sheep that graze behind us so we know them where they hail.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>We bridge across the dark, and bid the helmsman have a care,<lb/>
The flash that wheeling inland wakes his sleeping wife to prayer;<lb/>
From our vexed eyries, head to gale, we bind in burning chains<lb/>
The lover from the sea-rim drawn — his love in English lanes.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>We greet the clippers wing-and-wing that race the Southern wool;<lb/>
We warn the crawling cargo-tanks of Bremen, Leith and Hull;<lb/>
To each and all our equal lamp at peril of the sea —<lb/>
The white wall-sided warships or the whalers of Dundee!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Come up, come in from Eastward, from the guard-ports of the Morn!<lb/>
Beat up, beat in from Southerly, O gipsies of the Horn!<lb/>
Swift shuttles of an Empire’s loom that weave us main to main,<lb/>
The Coastwise Lights of England give you welcome back again!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Go, get you gone up-Channel with the sea-crust on your plates;<lb/>
Go, get you into London with the burden of your freights!<lb/>
Haste, for they talk of Empire there, and say, if any seek,<lb/>
The Lights of England sent you and by silence shall ye speak.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>The Song of the Dead.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Hear now the Song of the Dead — in the North by the torn berg-edges —<lb/>
They that look still to the Pole, asleep by their hide-stripped<lb/>
          sledges.<lb/>
Song of the Dead in the South — in the sun by their skeleton horses,<lb/>
Where the warrigal whimpers and bays through the dust of the sere<lb/>
          river-courses.</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Song of the Dead in the East — in the heat-rotted jungle hollows,<lb/>
Where the dog-ape barks in the kloof — in the brake of the<lb/>
          buffalo-wallows.<lb/>
Song of the Dead in the West — in the Barrens, the snow that betrayed<lb/>
          them,<lb/>
Where the wolverine tumbles their packs from the camp and the<lb/>
          grave-mound they made them;<lb/>
        Hear now the Song of the Dead!</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <p rend="head">I.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>We were dreamers, dreaming greatly, in the man-stifled town;<lb/>
We yearned beyond the skyline where the strange roads go down.<lb/>
Came the Whisper, came the Vision, came the Power with the Need.<lb/>
Till the Soul that is not man’s soul was lent us to lead.<lb/>
As the deer breaks — as the steer breaks — from the herd where they<lb/>
          graze,<lb/>
In the faith of little children we went on our ways.<lb/>
Then the wood failed — then the food failed — then the last water dried —<lb/>
In the faith of little children we lay down and died.<lb/>
On the sand-drift — on the veldt-side — in the fern-scrub we lay,<lb/>
That our sons might follow after by the bones on the way.<lb/>
Follow after — follow after! We have watered the root,<lb/>
And the bud has come to blossom that ripens for fruit!<lb/>
Follow after — we are waiting by the trails that we lost<lb/>
For the sound of many footsteps, for the tread of a host.<lb/>
Follow after — follow after — for the harvest is sown:<lb/>
By the bones about the wayside ye shall come to your own!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>* * * * *</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">When Drake went down to the Horn<lb/>
  And England was crowned thereby,<lb/>
‘Twixt seas unsailed and shores unhailed<lb/>
  Our Lodge — our Lodge was born<lb/>
  (And England was crowned thereby).</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Which never shall close again<lb/>
  By day nor yet by night,<lb/>
While man shall take his life to stake<lb/>
  At risk of shoal or main<lb/>
  (By day nor yet by night),</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">But standeth even so<lb/>
  As now we witness here,<lb/>
While men depart, of joyful heart,<lb/>
  Adventure for to know.<lb/>
  (As now bear witness here).</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <p rend="head">II.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>We have fed our sea for a thousand years<lb/>
  And she calls us, still unfed,<lb/>
Though there’s never a wave of all her waves<lb/>
  But marks our English dead:<lb/>
We have strawed our best to the weed’s unrest<lb/>
  To the shark and the sheering gull.<lb/>
If blood be the price of admiralty,<lb/>
  Lord God, we ha’ paid in full!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>There’s never a flood goes shoreward now<lb/>
  But lifts a keel we manned;<lb/>
There’s never an ebb goes seaward now<lb/>
  But drops our dead on the sand —<lb/>
But slinks our dead on the sands forlore,<lb/>
  From The Ducies to the Swin.<lb/>
If blood be the price of admiralty,<lb/>
If blood be the price of admiralty,<lb/>
  Lord God, we ha’ paid it in!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>We must feed our sea for a thousand years,<lb/>
  For that is our doom and pride,<lb/>
As it was when they sailed with the <hi rend="italic">Golden Hind</hi>
                     <lb/>
  Or the wreck that struck last tide —<lb/>
Or the wreck that lies on the spouting reef<lb/>
  Where the ghastly blue-lights flare.<lb/>
If blood be the price of admiralty,<lb/>
If blood be the price of admiralty,<lb/>
If blood be the price of admiralty,<lb/>
  Lord God, we ha’ bought it fair!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>The Deep-sea Cables.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>The wrecks dissolve above us; their dust drops down from afar —<lb/>
Down to the dark, to the utter dark, where the blind white sea-snakes are.<lb/>
There is no sound, no echo of sound, in the deserts of the deep,<lb/>
Or the great gray level plains of ooze where the shell-burred cables creep.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Here in the womb of the world — here on the tie-ribs of earth<lb/>
  Words, and the words of men, flicker and flutter and beat —<lb/>
Warning, sorrow and gain, salutation and mirth —<lb/>
  For a Power troubles the Still that has neither voice nor feet.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>They have wakened the timeless Things; they have killed their father Time;<lb/>
  Joining hands in the gloom, a league from the last of the sun.<lb/>
Hush! Men talk today o’er the waste of the ultimate slime,<lb/>
  And a new Word runs between: whispering, “Let us be one!”</p>
               </quote>
               <p>The Song of the Sons.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>One from the ends of the earth — gifts at an open door —<lb/>
Treason has much, but we, Mother, thy sons have more!<lb/>
From the whine of a dying man, from the snarl of a wolf-pack freed,<lb/>
Turn, for the world is thine. Mother, be proud of thy seed!<lb/>
Count, are we feeble or few? Hear, is our speech so rude?<lb/>
Look, are we poor in the land? Judge, are we men of The Blood?</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Those that have stayed at thy knees, Mother, go call them in-<lb/>
We that were bred overseas wait and would speak with our kin.<lb/>
Not in the dark do we fight — haggle and flout and gibe;<lb/>
Selling our love for a price, loaning our hearts for a bribe.<lb/>
Gifts have we only today — Love without promise or fee —<lb/>
Hear, for thy children speak, from the uttermost parts of the sea:</p>
               </quote>
               <p>The Song of the Cities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Bombay.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Royal and Dower-royal, I the Queen<lb/>
  Fronting thy richest sea with richer hands —<lb/>
A thousand mills roar through me where I glean<lb/>
  All races from all lands.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Calcutta.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Me the Sea-captain loved, the River built,<lb/>
  Wealth sought and Kings adventured life to hold.<lb/>
Hail, England! I am Asia — Power on silt,<lb/>
  Death in my hands, but Gold!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Madras.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Clive kissed me on the mouth and eyes and brow,<lb/>
  Wonderful kisses, so that I became<lb/>
Crowned above Queens — a withered beldame now,<lb/>
  Brooding on ancient fame.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rangoon.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Hail, Mother! Do they call me rich in trade?<lb/>
  Little care I, but hear the shorn priest drone,<lb/>
And watch my silk-clad lovers, man by maid,<lb/>
  Laugh ‘neath my Shwe Dagon.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Singapore.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Hail, Mother! East and West must seek my aid<lb/>
  Ere the spent gear shall dare the ports afar.<lb/>
The second doorway of the wide world’s trade<lb/>
  Is mine to loose or bar.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Hong–Kong.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Hail, Mother! Hold me fast; my Praya sleeps<lb/>
  Under innumerable keels today.<lb/>
Yet guard (and landward) or tomorrow sweeps<lb/>
  Thy warships down the bay.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Halifax.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Into the mist my guardian prows put forth,<lb/>
  Behind the mist my virgin ramparts lie,<lb/>
The Warden of the Honour of the North,<lb/>
  Sleepless and veiled am I!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Quebec and Montreal.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Peace is our portion. Yet a whisper rose,<lb/>
  Foolish and causeless, half in jest, half hate.<lb/>
Now wake we and remember mighty blows,<lb/>
  And, fearing no man, wait!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Victoria.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>From East to West the circling word has passed,<lb/>
  Till West is East beside our land-locked blue;<lb/>
From East to West the tested chain holds fast,<lb/>
  The well-forged link rings true!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Capetown.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Hail! Snatched and bartered oft from hand to hand,<lb/>
  I dream my dream, by rock and heath and pine,<lb/>
Of Empire to the northward. Ay, one land<lb/>
  From Lion’s Head to Line!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Melbourne.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Greeting! Nor fear nor favour won us place,<lb/>
  Got between greed of gold and dread of drouth,<lb/>
Loud-voiced and reckless as the wild tide-race<lb/>
  That whips our harbour-mouth!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sydney.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Greeting! My birth-stain have I turned to good;<lb/>
  Forcing strong wills perverse to steadfastness;<lb/>
The first flush of the tropics in my blood,<lb/>
  And at my feet Success!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Brisbane.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>The northern stirp beneath the southern skies —<lb/>
  I build a nation for an Empire’s need,<lb/>
Suffer a little, and my land shall rise,<lb/>
  Queen over lands indeed!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Hobart.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Man’s love first found me; man’s hate made me Hell;<lb/>
  For my babes’ sake I cleansed those infamies.<lb/>
Earnest for leave to live and labour well<lb/>
  God flung me peace and ease.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Auckland.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Last, loneliest, loveliest, exquisite, apart —<lb/>
  On us, on us the unswerving season smiles,<lb/>
Who wonder ‘mid our fern why men depart<lb/>
  To seek the Happy Isles!</p>
               </quote>
               <p>England’s Answer.</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Truly ye come of The Blood; slower to bless than to ban;<lb/>
Little used to lie down at the bidding of any man.<lb/>
Flesh of the flesh that I bred, bone of the bone that I bare;<lb/>
Stark as your sons shall be — stern as your fathers were.<lb/>
Deeper than speech our love, stronger than life our tether,<lb/>
But we do not fall on the neck nor kiss when we come together.<lb/>
My arm is nothing weak, my strength is not gone by;<lb/>
Sons, I have borne many sons but my dugs are not dry.<lb/>
Look, I have made ye a place and opened wide the doors,<lb/>
That ye may talk together, your Barons and Councillors —<lb/>
Wards of the Outer March, Lords of the Lower Seas,<lb/>
Ay, talk to your gray mother that bore you on her knees!—<lb/>
That ye may talk together, brother to brother’s face —<lb/>
Thus for the good of your peoples — thus for the Pride of the Race.<lb/>
Also, we will make promise. So long as The Blood endures,<lb/>
I shall know that your good is mine: ye shall feel that my strength is yours:<lb/>
In the day of Armageddon, at the last great fight of all,<lb/>
That Our House stand together and the pillars do not fall.<lb/>
Draw now the three-fold knot firm on the nine-fold bands,<lb/>
And the Law that ye make shall be law after the rule of your lands.<lb/>
This for the waxen Heath, and that for the Wattle-bloom,<lb/>
This for the Maple-leaf, and that for the southern Broom.<lb/>
The Law that ye make shall be law and I do not press my will,<lb/>
Because ye are Sons of The Blood and call me Mother still.<lb/>
Now must ye speak to your kinsmen and they must speak to you,<lb/>
After the use of the English, in straight-flung words and few.<lb/>
Go to your work and be strong, halting not in your ways,<lb/>
Baulking the end half-won for an instant dole of praise.<lb/>
Stand to your work and be wise — certain of sword and pen,<lb/>
Who are neither children nor Gods, but men in a world of men!</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section5">
               <head>The First Chantey.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>Mine was the woman to me, darkling I found her;</l>
                  <l>Haling her dumb from the camp, held her and bound her.</l>
                  <l>Hot rose her tribe on our track ere I had proved her;</l>
                  <l>Hearing her laugh in the gloom, greatly I loved her.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>Swift through the forest we ran; none stood to guard us,</l>
                  <l>Few were my people and far; then the flood barred us —</l>
                  <l>Him we call Son of the Sea, sullen and swollen;</l>
                  <l>Panting we waited the death, stealer and stolen,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ere they came to my lance laid for the slaughter,</l>
                  <l>Lightly she leaped to a log lapped in the water;</l>
                  <l>Holding on high and apart skins that arrayed her,</l>
                  <l>Called she the God of the Wind that he should aid her.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Life had the tree at that word, (Praise we the Giver!)</l>
                  <l>Otter-like left he the bank for the full river.</l>
                  <l>Far fell their axes behind, flashing and ringing,</l>
                  <l>Wonder was on me and fear, yet she was singing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Low lay the land we had left. Now the blue bound us,</l>
                  <l>Even the Floor of the Gods level around us.</l>
                  <l>Whisper there was not, nor word, shadow nor showing,</l>
                  <l>Still the light stirred on the deep, glowing and growing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then did He leap to His place flaring from under,</l>
                  <l>He the Compeller, the Sun, bared to our wonder.</l>
                  <l>Nay, not a league from our eyes blinded with gazing,</l>
                  <l>Cleared He the womb of the world, huge and amazing!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This we beheld (and we live)— the Pit of the Burning,</l>
                  <l>Then the God spoke to the tree for our returning;</l>
                  <l>Back to the beach of our flight, fearless and slowly,</l>
                  <l>Back to our slayers he went: but we were holy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Men that were hot in that hunt, women that followed,</l>
                  <l>Babes that were promised our bones, trembled and wallowed:</l>
                  <l>Over the necks of the tribe crouching and fawning —</l>
                  <l>Prophet and priestess we came back from the dawning!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section6">
               <head>The Last Chantey.</head>
               <p>“And there was no more sea.”</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Thus said The Lord in the Vault above the Cherubim,<lb/>
  Calling to the angels and the souls in their degree:<lb/>
    “Lo! Earth has passed away<lb/>
    On the smoke of Judgment Day.<lb/>
  That Our word may be established shall We gather up the sea?”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Loud sang the souls of the jolly, jolly mariners:<lb/>
  “Plague upon the hurricane that made us furl and flee!<lb/>
    But the war is done between us,<lb/>
    In the deep the Lord hath seen us —<lb/>
  Our bones we’ll leave the barracout’, and God may sink the sea!”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Then said the soul of Judas that betrayèd Him:<lb/>
  “Lord, hast Thou forgotten Thy covenant with me?<lb/>
    How once a year I go<lb/>
    To cool me on the floe,<lb/>
  And Ye take my day of mercy if Ye take away the sea!”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Then said the soul of the Angel of the Off-shore Wind:<lb/>
  (He that bits the thunder when the bull-mouthed breakers flee):<lb/>
    “I have watch and ward to keep<lb/>
    O’er Thy wonders on the deep,<lb/>
  And Ye take mine honour from me if Ye take away the sea!”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Loud sang the souls of the jolly, jolly mariners:<lb/>
  “Nay, but we were angry, and a hasty folk are we!<lb/>
    If we worked the ship together<lb/>
    Till she foundered in foul weather,<lb/>
  Are we babes that we should clamour for a vengeance on the sea?”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Then said the souls of the slaves that men threw overboard:<lb/>
  “Kennelled in the picaroon a weary band were we;<lb/>
    But Thy arm was strong to save,<lb/>
    And it touched us on the wave,<lb/>
  And we drowsed the long tides idle till Thy Trumpets tore the sea.”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Then cried the soul of the stout Apostle Paul to God:<lb/>
  “Once we frapped a ship, and she laboured woundily.<lb/>
    There were fourteen score of these,<lb/>
    And they blessed Thee on their knees,<lb/>
  When they learned Thy Grace and Glory under Malta by the sea.”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Loud sang the souls of the jolly, jolly mariners,<lb/>
  Plucking at their harps, and they plucked unhandily:<lb/>
    “Our thumbs are rough and tarred,<lb/>
    And the tune is something hard —<lb/>
  May we lift a Deep-sea Chantey such as seamen use at sea?”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Then said the souls of the gentlemen-adventurers —<lb/>
  Fettered wrist to bar all for red iniquity:<lb/>
    “Ho, we revel in our chains<lb/>
    O’er the sorrow that was Spain’s;<lb/>
  Heave or sink it, leave or drink it, we were masters of the sea!”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Up spake the soul of a gray Gothavn ‘speckshioner —<lb/>
  (He that led the flinching in the fleets of fair Dundee):<lb/>
    “Ho, the ringer and right whale,<lb/>
    And the fish we struck for sale,<lb/>
  Will Ye whelm them all for wantonness that wallow in the sea?”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Loud sang the souls of the jolly, jolly mariners,<lb/>
  Crying: “Under Heaven, here is neither lead nor lea!<lb/>
    Must we sing for evermore<lb/>
    On the windless, glassy floor?<lb/>
  Take back your golden fiddles and we’ll beat to open sea!”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Then stooped the Lord, and He called the good sea up to Him,<lb/>
  And ‘stablished his borders unto all eternity,<lb/>
    That such as have no pleasure<lb/>
    For to praise the Lord by measure,<lb/>
  They may enter into galleons and serve Him on the sea.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sun, wind, and cloud shall fail not from the face of it,<lb/>
  Stinging, ringing spindrift, nor the fulmar flying free;<lb/>
    And the ships shall go abroad<lb/>
    To the glory of the Lord<lb/>
  Who heard the silly sailor-folk and gave them back their sea!</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section7">
               <head>The Merchantmen.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>King Solomon drew merchantmen,</l>
                  <l>  Because of his desire</l>
                  <l>For peacocks, apes, and ivory,</l>
                  <l>  From Tarshish unto Tyre:</l>
                  <l>With cedars out of Lebanon</l>
                  <l>  Which Hiram rafted down,</l>
                  <l>But we be only sailormen</l>
                  <l>  That use in London town.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Coastwise — cross-seas — round the world and back again —<lb/>
  Where the flaw shall head us or the full Trade suits —<lb/>
Plain-sail — storm-sail — lay your board and tack again —<lb/>
  And that’s the way we’ll pay Paddy Doyle for his boots!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We bring no store of ingots,</l>
                  <l>  Of spice or precious stones,</l>
                  <l>But that we have we gathered</l>
                  <l>  With sweat and aching bones:</l>
                  <l>In flame beneath the tropics,</l>
                  <l>  In frost upon the floe,</l>
                  <l>And jeopardy of every wind</l>
                  <l>  That does between them go.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And some we got by purchase,</l>
                  <l>  And some we had by trade,</l>
                  <l>And some we found by courtesy</l>
                  <l>  Of pike and carronade,</l>
                  <l>At midnight, ‘mid-sea meetings,</l>
                  <l>  For charity to keep,</l>
                  <l>And light the rolling homeward-bound</l>
                  <l>  That rode a foot too deep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By sport of bitter weather</l>
                  <l>  We’re walty, strained, and scarred</l>
                  <l>From the kentledge on the kelson</l>
                  <l>  To the slings upon the yard.</l>
                  <l>Six oceans had their will of us</l>
                  <l>  To carry all away —</l>
                  <l>Our galley ‘s in the Baltic,</l>
                  <l>  And our boom ‘s in Mossel Bay!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’ve floundered off the Texel,</l>
                  <l>  Awash with sodden deals,</l>
                  <l>We’ve slipped from Valparaiso</l>
                  <l>  With the Norther at our heels:</l>
                  <l>We’ve ratched beyond the Crossets</l>
                  <l>  That tusk the Southern Pole,</l>
                  <l>And dipped our gunnels under</l>
                  <l>  To the dread Agulhas roll.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beyond all outer charting</l>
                  <l>  We sailed where none have sailed,</l>
                  <l>And saw the land-lights burning</l>
                  <l>  On islands none have hailed;</l>
                  <l>Our hair stood up for wonder,</l>
                  <l>  But, when the night was done,</l>
                  <l>There danced the deep to windward</l>
                  <l>  Blue-empty ‘neath the sun!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Strange consorts rode beside us</l>
                  <l>  And brought us evil luck;</l>
                  <l>The witch-fire climbed our channels,</l>
                  <l>  And danced on vane and truck:</l>
                  <l>Till, through the red tornado,</l>
                  <l>  That lashed us nigh to blind,</l>
                  <l>We saw The Dutchman plunging,</l>
                  <l>  Full canvas, head to wind!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’ve heard the Midnight Leadsman</l>
                  <l>  That calls the black deep down —</l>
                  <l>Ay, thrice we’ve heard The Swimmer,</l>
                  <l>  The Thing that may not drown.</l>
                  <l>On frozen bunt and gasket</l>
                  <l>  The sleet-cloud drave her hosts,</l>
                  <l>When, manned by more than signed with us,</l>
                  <l>  We passed the Isle o’ Ghosts!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And north, amid the hummocks,</l>
                  <l>  A biscuit-toss below,</l>
                  <l>We met the silent shallop</l>
                  <l>  That frighted whalers know;</l>
                  <l>For, down a cruel ice-lane,</l>
                  <l>  That opened as he sped,</l>
                  <l>We saw dead Henry Hudson</l>
                  <l>  Steer, North by West, his dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So dealt God’s waters with us</l>
                  <l>  Beneath the roaring skies,</l>
                  <l>So walked His signs and marvels</l>
                  <l>  All naked to our eyes:</l>
                  <l>But we were heading homeward</l>
                  <l>  With trade to lose or make —</l>
                  <l>Good Lord, they slipped behind us</l>
                  <l>  In the tailing of our wake!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let go, let go the anchors;</l>
                  <l>  Now shamed at heart are we</l>
                  <l>To bring so poor a cargo home</l>
                  <l>  That had for gift the sea!</l>
                  <l>Let go the great bow-anchors —</l>
                  <l>  Ah, fools were we and blind —</l>
                  <l>The worst we baled with utter toil,</l>
                  <l>  The best we left behind!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Coastwise — cross-seas — round the world and back again,<lb/>
  Whither the flaw shall fail us or the Trades drive down:<lb/>
Plain-sail — storm-sail — lay your board and tack again —<lb/>
  And all to bring a cargo up to London Town!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section8">
               <head>McAndrews’ Hymn.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>Lord, Thou hast made this world below the shadow of a dream,</l>
                  <l>An’, taught by time, I tak’ it so — exceptin’ always Steam.</l>
                  <l>From coupler-flange to spindle-guide I see Thy Hand, O God —</l>
                  <l>Predestination in the stride o’ yon connectin’-rod.</l>
                  <l>John Calvin might ha’ forged the same — enorrmous, certain, slow —</l>
                  <l>Ay, wrought it in the furnace-flame — <hi rend="italic">my</hi> “Institutio.”</l>
                  <l>I cannot get my sleep to-night; old bones are hard to please;</l>
                  <l>I’ll stand the middle watch up here — alone wi’ God an’ these</l>
                  <l>My engines, after ninety days o’ race an’ rack an’ strain</l>
                  <l>Through all the seas of all Thy world, slam-bangin’ home again.</l>
                  <l>Slam-bang too much — they knock a wee — the crosshead-gibs are loose;</l>
                  <l>But thirty thousand mile o’ sea has gied them fair excuse....</l>
                  <l>Fine, clear an’ dark — a full-draught breeze, wi’ Ushant out o’ sight,</l>
                  <l>An’ Ferguson relievin’ Hay. Old girl, ye’ll walk to-night!</l>
                  <l>His wife’s at Plymouth.... Seventy — One — Two — Three since he began —</l>
                  <l>Three turns for Mistress Ferguson ... an’ who’s to blame the man?</l>
                  <l>There’s none at any port for me, by drivin’ fast or slow,</l>
                  <l>Since Elsie Campbell went to Thee, Lord, thirty years ago.</l>
                  <l>(The year the <hi rend="italic">Sarah Sands</hi> was burned. Oh roads we used to tread,</l>
                  <l>Fra’ Maryhill to Pollokshaws — fra’ Govan to Parkhead!)</l>
                  <l>Not but they’re ceevil on the Board. Ye’ll hear Sir Kenneth say:</l>
                  <l>“Good morrn, McAndrews! Back again? An’ how’s your bilge today?”</l>
                  <l>Miscallin’ technicalities but handin’ me my chair</l>
                  <l>To drink Madeira wi’ three Earls — the auld Fleet Engineer,</l>
                  <l>That started as a boiler-whelp — when steam and he were low.</l>
                  <l>I mind the time we used to serve a broken pipe wi’ tow.</l>
                  <l>Ten pound was all the pressure then — Eh! Eh!— a man wad drive;</l>
                  <l>An’ here, our workin’ gauges give one hunder’ fifty-five!</l>
                  <l>We’re creepin’ on wi’ each new rig — less weight an’ larger power:</l>
                  <l>There’ll be the loco-boiler next an’ thirty knots an hour!</l>
                  <l>Thirty an’ more. What I ha’ seen since ocean-steam began</l>
                  <l>Leaves me no doot for the machine: but what about the man?</l>
                  <l>The man that counts, wi’ all his runs, one million mile o’ sea:</l>
                  <l>Four time the span from earth to moon.... How far, O Lord, from Thee?</l>
                  <l>That wast beside him night an’ day. Ye mind my first typhoon?</l>
                  <l>It scoughed the skipper on his way to jock wi’ the saloon.</l>
                  <l>Three feet were on the stokehold floor — just slappin’ to an’ fro —</l>
                  <l>An’ cast me on a furnace-door. I have the marks to show.</l>
                  <l>Marks! I ha’ marks o’ more than burns — deep in my soul an’ black,</l>
                  <l>An’ times like this, when things go smooth, my wickudness comes back.</l>
                  <l>The sins o’ four and forty years, all up an’ down the seas,</l>
                  <l>Clack an’ repeat like valves half-fed.... Forgie’s our trespasses.</l>
                  <l>Nights when I’d come on deck to mark, wi’ envy in my gaze,</l>
                  <l>The couples kittlin’ in the dark between the funnel stays;</l>
                  <l>Years when I raked the ports wi’ pride to fill my cup o’ wrong —</l>
                  <l>Judge not, O Lord, my steps aside at Gay Street in Hong–Kong!</l>
                  <l>Blot out the wastrel hours of mine in sin when I abode —</l>
                  <l>Jane Harrigan’s an’ Number Nine, The Reddick an’ Grant Road!</l>
                  <l>An’ waur than all — my crownin’ sin — rank blasphemy an’ wild.</l>
                  <l>I was not four and twenty then — Ye wadna’ judge a child?</l>
                  <l>I’d seen the Tropics first that run — new fruit, new smells, new air —</l>
                  <l>How could I tell — blind-fou wi’ sun — the Deil was lurkin’ there?</l>
                  <l>By day like playhouse-scenes the shore slid past our sleepy eyes;</l>
                  <l>By night those soft, lasceevious stars leered from those velvet skies,</l>
                  <l>In port (we used no cargo-steam) I’d daunder down the streets —</l>
                  <l>An ijjit grinnin’ in a dream — for shells an’ parrakeets,</l>
                  <l>An’ walkin’-sticks o’ carved bamboo an’ blowfish stuffed an’ dried —</l>
                  <l>Fillin’ my bunk wi’ rubbishry the Chief put overside.</l>
                  <l>Till, off Sumbawa Head, Ye mind, I heard a land-breeze ca’</l>
                  <l>Milk-warm wi’ breath o’ spice an’ bloom: “McAndrews, come awa’!”</l>
                  <l>Firm, clear an’ low — no haste, no hate — the ghostly whisper went,</l>
                  <l>Just statin’ eevidential facts beyon’ all argument:</l>
                  <l>“Your mither’s God’s a graspin’ deil, the shadow o’ yoursel’,</l>
                  <l>Got out o’ books by meenisters clean daft on Heaven an’ Hell.</l>
                  <l>They mak’ him in the Broomielaw, o’ Glasgie cold an’ dirt,</l>
                  <l>A jealous, pridefu’ fetich, lad, that’s only strong to hurt,</l>
                  <l>Ye’ll not go back to Him again an’ kiss His red-hot rod,</l>
                  <l>But come wi’ Us” (Now, who were <hi rend="italic">They</hi>?) “an’ know the Leevin’ God,</l>
                  <l>That does not kipper souls for sport or break a life in jest,</l>
                  <l>But swells the ripenin’ cocoanuts an’ ripes the woman’s breast.”</l>
                  <l>An’ there it stopped: cut off: no more; that quiet, certain voice —</l>
                  <l>For me, six months o’ twenty-four, to leave or take at choice.</l>
                  <l>’Twas on me like a thunderclap — it racked me through an’ through —</l>
                  <l>Temptation past the show o’ speech, unnamable an’ new —</l>
                  <l>The Sin against the Holy Ghost?... An’ under all, our screw.</l>
                  <l>That storm blew by but left behind her anchor-shiftin’ swell,</l>
                  <l>Thou knowest all my heart an’ mind, Thou knowest, Lord, I fell.</l>
                  <l>Third on the <hi rend="italic">Mary Gloster</hi> then, and first that night in Hell!</l>
                  <l>Yet was Thy hand beneath my head: about my feet Thy care —</l>
                  <l>Fra’ Deli clear to Torres Strait, the trial o’ despair,</l>
                  <l>But when we touched the Barrier Reef Thy answer to my prayer!</l>
                  <l>We dared na run that sea by night but lay an’ held our fire,</l>
                  <l>An’ I was drowzin’ on the hatch — sick — sick wi’ doubt an’ tire:</l>
                  <l>“<hi rend="italic">Better the sight of eyes that see than wanderin’ o’ desire!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>Ye mind that word? Clear as our gongs — again, an’ once again,</l>
                  <l>When rippin’ down through coral-trash ran out our moorin’-chain;</l>
                  <l>An’ by Thy Grace I had the Light to see my duty plain.</l>
                  <l>Light on the engine-room — no more — clear as our carbons burn.</l>
                  <l>I’ve lost it since a thousand times, but never past return.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <p>* * * * *</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Obsairve! Per annum we’ll have here two thousand souls aboard —</l>
                  <l>Think not I dare to justify myself before the Lord,</l>
                  <l>But — average fifteen hunder’ souls safe-borne fra’ port to port —</l>
                  <l>I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> o’ service to my kind. Ye wadna’ blame the thought?</l>
                  <l>Maybe they steam from grace to wrath — to sin by folly led,—</l>
                  <l>It isna mine to judge their path — their lives are on my head.</l>
                  <l>Mine at the last — when all is done it all comes back to me,</l>
                  <l>The fault that leaves six thousand ton a log upon the sea.</l>
                  <l>We’ll tak’ one stretch — three weeks an’ odd by any road ye steer —</l>
                  <l>Fra’ Cape Town east to Wellington — ye need an engineer.</l>
                  <l>Fail there — ye’ve time to weld your shaft — ay, eat it, ere ye’re spoke,</l>
                  <l>Or make Kerguelen under sail — three jiggers burned wi’ smoke!</l>
                  <l>An’ home again, the Rio run: it’s no child’s play to go</l>
                  <l>Steamin’ to bell for fourteen days o’ snow an’ floe an’ blow —</l>
                  <l>The bergs like kelpies overside that girn an’ turn an’ shift</l>
                  <l>Whaur, grindin’ like the Mills o’ God, goes by the big South drift.</l>
                  <l>(Hail, snow an’ ice that praise the Lord: I’ve met them at their work,</l>
                  <l>An’ wished we had anither route or they anither kirk.)</l>
                  <l>Yon’s strain, hard strain, o’ head an’ hand, for though Thy Power brings</l>
                  <l>All skill to naught, Ye’ll understand a man must think o’ things.</l>
                  <l>Then, at the last, we’ll get to port an’ hoist their baggage clear —</l>
                  <l>The passengers, wi’ gloves an’ canes — an’ this is what I’ll hear:</l>
                  <l>“Well, thank ye for a pleasant voyage. The tender’s comin’ now.”</l>
                  <l>While I go testin’ follower-bolts an’ watch the skipper bow.</l>
                  <l>They’ve words for everyone but me — shake hands wi’ half the crew,</l>
                  <l>Except the dour Scots engineer, the man they never knew.</l>
                  <l>An’ yet I like the wark for all we’ve dam’ few pickin’s here —</l>
                  <l>No pension, an’ the most we earn’s four hunder’ pound a year.</l>
                  <l>Better myself abroad? Maybe. <hi rend="italic">I’d</hi> sooner starve than sail</l>
                  <l>Wi’ such as call a snifter-rod <hi rend="italic">ross</hi>.... French for nightingale.</l>
                  <l>Commeesion on my stores? Some do; but I can not afford</l>
                  <l>To lie like stewards wi’ patty-pans. I’m older than the Board.</l>
                  <l>A bonus on the coal I save? Ou ay, the Scots are close,</l>
                  <l>But when I grudge the strength Ye gave I’ll grudge their food to <hi rend="italic">those</hi>.</l>
                  <l>(There’s bricks that I might recommend — an’ clink the fire-bars cruel.</l>
                  <l>No! Welsh — Wangarti at the worst — an’ damn all patent fuel!)</l>
                  <l>Inventions? Ye must stay in port to mak’ a patent pay.</l>
                  <l>My Deeferential Valve–Gear taught me how that business lay,</l>
                  <l>I blame no chaps wi’ clearer head for aught they make or sell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">I</hi> found that I could not invent an’ look to these — as well.</l>
                  <l>So, wrestled wi’ Apollyon — Nah!— fretted like a bairn —</l>
                  <l>But burned the workin’-plans last run wi’ all I hoped to earn.</l>
                  <l>Ye know how hard an Idol dies, an’ what that meant to me —</l>
                  <l>E’en tak’ it for a sacrifice acceptable to Thee....</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Below there! Oiler! What’s your wark? Ye find her runnin’ hard?<lb/>
Ye needn’t swill the cap wi’ oil — this isn’t the Cunard.<lb/>
Ye thought? Ye are not paid to think. Go, sweat that off again!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tck! Tck! It’s deeficult to sweer nor tak’ The Name in vain!</l>
                  <l>Men, ay an’ women, call me stern. Wi’ these to oversee</l>
                  <l>Ye’ll note I’ve little time to burn on social repartee.</l>
                  <l>The bairns see what their elders miss; they’ll hunt me to an’ fro,</l>
                  <l>Till for the sake of — well, a kiss — I tak’ ’em down below.</l>
                  <l>That minds me of our Viscount loon — Sir Kenneth’s kin — the chap</l>
                  <l>Wi’ russia leather tennis-shoon an’ spar-decked yachtin’-cap.</l>
                  <l>I showed him round last week, o’er all — an’ at the last says he:</l>
                  <l>“Mister McAndrews, don’t you think steam spoils romance at sea?”</l>
                  <l>Damned ijjit! I’d been doon that morn to see what ailed the throws,</l>
                  <l>Manholin’, on my back — the cranks three inches from my nose.</l>
                  <l>Romance! Those first-class passengers they like it very well,</l>
                  <l>Printed an’ bound in little books; but why don’t poets tell?</l>
                  <l>I’m sick of all their quirks an’ turns — the loves an’ doves they dream —</l>
                  <l>Lord, send a man like Robbie Burns to sing the Song o’ Steam!</l>
                  <l>To match wi’ Scotia’s noblest speech yon orchestra sublime</l>
                  <l>Whaurto — uplifted like the Just — the tail-rods mark the time.</l>
                  <l>The crank-throws give the double-bass; the feed-pump sobs an’ heaves:</l>
                  <l>An’ now the main eccentrics start their quarrel on the sheaves.</l>
                  <l>Her time, her own appointed time, the rocking link-head bides,</l>
                  <l>Till — hear that note?— the rod’s return whings glimmerin’ through the guides.</l>
                  <l>They’re all awa’! True beat, full power, the clangin’ chorus goes</l>
                  <l>Clear to the tunnel where they sit, my purrin’ dynamoes.</l>
                  <l>Interdependence absolute, foreseen, ordained, decreed,</l>
                  <l>To work, Ye’ll note, at any tilt an’ every rate o’ speed.</l>
                  <l>Fra’ skylight-lift to furnace-bars, backed, bolted, braced an’ stayed,</l>
                  <l>An’ singin’ like the Mornin’ Stars for joy that they are made;</l>
                  <l>While, out o’ touch o’ vanity, the sweatin’ thrust-block says:</l>
                  <l>“Not unto us the praise, or man — not unto us the praise!”</l>
                  <l>Now, a’ together, hear them lift their lesson — theirs an’ mine:</l>
                  <l>“Law, Orrder, Duty an’ Restraint, Obedience, Discipline!”</l>
                  <l>Mill, forge an’ try-pit taught them that when roarin’ they arose,</l>
                  <l>An’ whiles I wonder if a soul was gied them wi’ the blows.</l>
                  <l>Oh for a man to weld it then, in one trip-hammer strain,</l>
                  <l>Till even first-class passengers could tell the meanin’ plain!</l>
                  <l>But no one cares except mysel’ that serve an’ understand</l>
                  <l>My seven thousand horse-power here. Eh, Lord! They’re grand — they’re grand!</l>
                  <l>Uplift am I? When first in store the new-made beasties stood,</l>
                  <l>Were Ye cast down that breathed the Word declarin’ all things good?</l>
                  <l>Not so! O’ that warld-liftin’ joy no after-fall could vex,</l>
                  <l>Ye’ve left a glimmer still to cheer the Man — the Arrtifex!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">That</hi> holds, in spite o’ knock and scale, o’ friction, waste an’ slip,</l>
                  <l>An’ by that light — now, mark my word — we’ll build the Perfect Ship.</l>
                  <l>I’ll never last to judge her lines or take her curve — not I.</l>
                  <l>But I ha’ lived an’ I ha’ worked. All thanks to Thee, Most High!</l>
                  <l>An’ I ha’ done what I ha’ done — judge Thou if ill or well —</l>
                  <l>Always Thy Grace preventin’ me....</l>
                  <l>                                    Losh! Yon’s the “Stand by” bell.</l>
                  <l>Pilot so soon? His flare it is. The mornin’-watch is set.</l>
                  <l>Well, God be thanked, as I was sayin’, I’m no Pelagian yet.</l>
                  <l>Now I’ll tak’ on....</l>
                  <l>                      ’Morrn, Ferguson. Man, have ye ever thought</l>
                  <l>What your good leddy costs in coal?... I’ll burn ’em down to port.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section9">
               <head>The Miracles.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>I sent a message to my dear —</l>
                  <l>  A thousand leagues and more to her —</l>
                  <l>The dumb sea-levels thrilled to hear,</l>
                  <l>  And Lost Atlantis bore to her.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behind my message hard I came,</l>
                  <l>  And nigh had found a grave for me;</l>
                  <l>But that I launched of steel and flame</l>
                  <l>  Did war against the wave for me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Uprose the deep, by gale on gale,</l>
                  <l>  To bid me change my mind again —</l>
                  <l>He broke his teeth along my rail,</l>
                  <l>  And, roaring, swung behind again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I stayed the sun at noon to tell</l>
                  <l>  My way across the waste of it;</l>
                  <l>I read the storm before it fell</l>
                  <l>  And made the better haste of it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Afar, I hailed the land at night —</l>
                  <l>  The towers I built had heard of me —</l>
                  <l>And, ere my rocket reached its height,</l>
                  <l>  Had flashed my Love the word of me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Earth gave her chosen men of strength</l>
                  <l>  (They lived and strove and died for me)</l>
                  <l>To drive my road a nation’s length,</l>
                  <l>  And toss the miles aside for me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I snatched their toil to serve my needs —</l>
                  <l>  Too slow their fleetest flew for me —</l>
                  <l>I tired twenty smoking steeds,</l>
                  <l>  And bade them bait a new for me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I sent the lightnings forth to see</l>
                  <l>  Where hour by hour she waited me.</l>
                  <l>Among ten million one was she,</l>
                  <l>  And surely all men hated me!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dawn ran to meet us at my goal —</l>
                  <l>  Ah, day no tongue shall tell again!—</l>
                  <l>And little folk of little soul</l>
                  <l>  Rose up to buy and sell again!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section10">
               <head>The Native-Born.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>We’ve drunk to the Queen — God bless her!—</l>
                  <l>  We’ve drunk to our mothers’ land;</l>
                  <l>We’ve drunk to our English brother</l>
                  <l>  (But he does not understand);</l>
                  <l>We’ve drunk to the wide creation,</l>
                  <l>  And the Cross swings low to the morn,</l>
                  <l>Last toast, and of obligation,</l>
                  <l>  A health to the Native-born!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>They change their skies above them,</l>
                  <l>  But not their hearts that roam!</l>
                  <l>We learned from our wistful mothers</l>
                  <l>  To call old England “home”;</l>
                  <l>We read of the English sky-lark,</l>
                  <l>  Of the spring in the English lanes,</l>
                  <l>But we screamed with the painted lories</l>
                  <l>  As we rode on the dusty plains!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They passed with their old-world legends —</l>
                  <l>  Their tales of wrong and dearth —</l>
                  <l>Our fathers held by purchase,</l>
                  <l>  But we by the right of birth;</l>
                  <l>Our heart’s where they rocked our cradle,</l>
                  <l>  Our love where we spent our toil,</l>
                  <l>And our faith and our hope and our honour</l>
                  <l>  We pledge to our native soil!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I charge you charge your glasses —</l>
                  <l>  I charge you drink with me</l>
                  <l>To the men of the Four New Nations,</l>
                  <l>  And the Islands of the Sea —</l>
                  <l>To the last least lump of coral</l>
                  <l>  That none may stand outside,</l>
                  <l>And our own good pride shall teach us</l>
                  <l>  To praise our comrade’s pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To the hush of the breathless morning</l>
                  <l>  On the thin, tin, crackling roofs,</l>
                  <l>To the haze of the burned back-ranges</l>
                  <l>  And the dust of the shoeless hoofs —</l>
                  <l>To the risk of a death by drowning,</l>
                  <l>  To the risk of a death by drouth —</l>
                  <l>To the men of a million acres,</l>
                  <l>  To the Sons of the Golden South.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">To the Sons of the Golden South, (Stand up!)<lb/>
    And the life we live and know,<lb/>
  Let a fellow sing o’ the little things he cares about,<lb/>
  If a fellow fights for the little things he cares about<lb/>
    With the weight of a single blow!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>To the smoke of a hundred coasters,</l>
                  <l>  To the sheep on a thousand hills,</l>
                  <l>To the sun that never blisters,</l>
                  <l>  To the rain that never chills —</l>
                  <l>To the land of the waiting springtime,</l>
                  <l>  To our five-meal, meat-fed men,</l>
                  <l>To the tall deep-bosomed women,</l>
                  <l>  And the children nine and ten!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">And the children nine and ten, (Stand up!)<lb/>
    And the life we live and know,<lb/>
  Let a fellow sing o’ the little things he cares about,<lb/>
  If a fellow fights for the little things he cares about<lb/>
    With the weight of a two-fold blow!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>To the far-flung fenceless prairie</l>
                  <l>  Where the quick cloud-shadows trail,</l>
                  <l>To our neighbour’s barn in the offing</l>
                  <l>  And the line of the new-cut rail;</l>
                  <l>To the plough in her league-long furrow</l>
                  <l>  With the gray Lake gulls behind —</l>
                  <l>To the weight of a half-year’s winter</l>
                  <l>  And the warm wet western wind!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To the home of the floods and thunder,</l>
                  <l>  To her pale dry healing blue —</l>
                  <l>To the lift of the great Cape combers,</l>
                  <l>  And the smell of the baked Karroo.</l>
                  <l>To the growl of the sluicing stamp-head —</l>
                  <l>  To the reef and the water-gold,</l>
                  <l>To the last and the largest Empire,</l>
                  <l>  To the map that is half unrolled!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To our dear dark foster-mothers,</l>
                  <l>  To the heathen songs they sung —</l>
                  <l>To the heathen speech we babbled</l>
                  <l>  Ere we came to the white man’s tongue.</l>
                  <l>To the cool of our deep verandas —</l>
                  <l>  To the blaze of our jewelled main,</l>
                  <l>To the night, to the palms in the moonlight,</l>
                  <l>  And the fire-fly in the cane!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To the hearth of our people’s people —</l>
                  <l>  To her well-ploughed windy sea,</l>
                  <l>To the hush of our dread high-altars</l>
                  <l>  Where the Abbey makes us We;</l>
                  <l>To the grist of the slow-ground ages,</l>
                  <l>  To the gain that is yours and mine —</l>
                  <l>To the Bank of the Open Credit,</l>
                  <l>  To the Power-house of the Line!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’ve drunk to the Queen — God bless her!—</l>
                  <l>  We’ve drunk to our mothers’ land;</l>
                  <l>We’ve drunk to our English brother</l>
                  <l>  (And we hope he’ll understand).</l>
                  <l>We’ve drunk as much as we’re able,</l>
                  <l>  And the Cross swings low to the morn;</l>
                  <l>Last toast — and your foot on the table!—</l>
                  <l>  A health to the Native-born!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">A health to the Native-born, (Stand up!)<lb/>
    We’re six white men arow,<lb/>
  All bound to sing o’ the little things we care about,<lb/>
  All bound to fight for the little things we care about<lb/>
    With the weight of a six-fold blow!<lb/>
  By the might of our cable-tow, (Take hands!)<lb/>
  From the Orkneys to the Horn,<lb/>
    All round the world (and a little loop to pull it by),<lb/>
  All round the world (and a little strap to buckle it),<lb/>
    A health to the Native-born!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section11">
               <head>The King.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>“Farewell, Romance!” the Cave-men said;</l>
                  <l>  “With bone well carved he went away,</l>
                  <l>Flint arms the ignoble arrowhead,</l>
                  <l>  And jasper tips the spear today.</l>
                  <l>Changed are the Gods of Hunt and Dance,</l>
                  <l>And he with these. Farewell, Romance!”</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Farewell, Romance!” the Lake-folk sighed;</l>
                  <l>  “We lift the weight of flatling years;</l>
                  <l>The caverns of the mountain side</l>
                  <l>  Hold him who scorns our hutted piers.</l>
                  <l>Lost hills whereby we dare not dwell,</l>
                  <l>Guard ye his rest. Romance, farewell!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Farewell, Romance!” the Soldier spoke;</l>
                  <l>  “By sleight of sword we may not win,</l>
                  <l>But scuffle ‘mid uncleanly smoke</l>
                  <l>  Of arquebus and culverin.</l>
                  <l>Honour is lost, and none may tell</l>
                  <l>Who paid good blows. Romance, farewell!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Farewell, Romance!” the Traders cried;</l>
                  <l>  “Our keels ha’ lain with every sea;</l>
                  <l>The dull-returning wind and tide</l>
                  <l>  Heave up the wharf where we would be;</l>
                  <l>The known and noted breezes swell</l>
                  <l>Our trudging sail. Romance, farewell!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Good-bye, Romance!” the Skipper said;</l>
                  <l>  “He vanished with the coal we burn;</l>
                  <l>Our dial marks full steam ahead,</l>
                  <l>  Our speed is timed to half a turn.</l>
                  <l>Sure as the tidal trains we ply</l>
                  <l>‘Twixt port and port. Romance, good-bye!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Romance!” the Season-tickets mourn,</l>
                  <l>  “<hi rend="italic">He</hi> never ran to catch his train,</l>
                  <l>But passed with coach and guard and horn —</l>
                  <l>  And left the local — late again!</l>
                  <l>Confound Romance!”... And all unseen</l>
                  <l>Romance brought up the nine-fifteen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His hand was on the lever laid,</l>
                  <l>  His oil-can soothed the worrying cranks,</l>
                  <l>His whistle waked the snowbound grade,</l>
                  <l>  His fog-horn cut the reeking Banks;</l>
                  <l>In dock and deep and mine and mill</l>
                  <l>The Boy-god reckless laboured still.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Robed, crowned and throned, he wove his spell,</l>
                  <l>  Where heart-blood beat or hearth-smoke curled,</l>
                  <l>With unconsidered miracle,</l>
                  <l>  Hedged in a backward-gazing world;</l>
                  <l>Then taught his chosen bard to say:</l>
                  <l>“The King was with us — yesterday!”</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section12">
               <head>The Rhyme of the Three Sealers.</head>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Away by the lands of the Japanee,<lb/>
      When the paper lanterns glow<lb/>
  And the crews of all the shipping drink<lb/>
      In the house of Blood Street Joe,<lb/>
  At twilight, when the landward breeze<lb/>
      Brings up the harbour noise,<lb/>
  And ebb of Yokohama Bay<lb/>
      Swigs chattering through the buoys,<lb/>
  In Cisco’s Dewdrop Dining Rooms<lb/>
      They tell the tale anew<lb/>
  Of a hidden sea and a hidden fight,<lb/>
  When the Baltic ran from the Northern Light<lb/>
      And the Stralsund fought the two!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now this is the Law of the Muscovite, that he proves with shot and</l>
                  <l>          steel,</l>
                  <l>When ye come by his isles in the Smoky Sea ye must not take the seal,</l>
                  <l>Where the gray sea goes nakedly between the weed-hung shelves,</l>
                  <l>And the little blue fox he is bred for his skin and the seal they</l>
                  <l>          breed for themselves;</l>
                  <l>For when the <hi rend="italic">matkas</hi> seek the shore to drop their pups aland,</l>
                  <l>The great man-seal haul out of the sea, aroaring, band by band;</l>
                  <l>And when the first September gales have slaked their rutting-wrath,</l>
                  <l>The great man-seal haul back to the sea and no man knows their path.</l>
                  <l>Then dark they lie and stark they lie — rookery, dune, and floe,</l>
                  <l>And the Northern Lights come down o’ nights to dance with the</l>
                  <l>          houseless snow.</l>
                  <l>And God who clears the grounding berg and steers the grinding floe,</l>
                  <l>He hears the cry of the little kit-fox and the lemming on the snow.</l>
                  <l>But since our women must walk gay and money buys their gear,</l>
                  <l>The sealing-boats they filch that way at hazard year by year.</l>
                  <l>English they be and Japanee that hang on the Brown Bear’s flank,</l>
                  <l>And some be Scot, but the worst, God wot, and the boldest thieves,</l>
                  <l>          be Yank!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was the sealer Northern Light, to the Smoky Seas she bore.</l>
                  <l>With a stovepipe stuck from a starboard port and the Russian flag at</l>
                  <l>          her fore.</l>
                  <l>(Baltic, Stralsund, and Northern Light — oh! they were birds of a</l>
                  <l>          feather —</l>
                  <l>Slipping away to the Smoky Seas, three seal-thieves together!)</l>
                  <l>And at last she came to a sandy cove and the Baltic lay therein,</l>
                  <l>But her men were up with the herding seal to drive and club and skin.</l>
                  <l>There were fifteen hundred skins abeach, cool pelt and proper fur,</l>
                  <l>When the Northern Light drove into the bight and the sea-mist drove</l>
                  <l>          with her.</l>
                  <l>The Baltic called her men and weighed — she could not choose but run —</l>
                  <l>For a stovepipe seen through the closing mist, it shows like a</l>
                  <l>          four-inch gun</l>
                  <l>(And loss it is that is sad as death to lose both trip and ship</l>
                  <l>And lie for a rotting contraband on Vladivostock slip).</l>
                  <l>She turned and dived in the sea-smother as a rabbit dives in the whins,</l>
                  <l>And the Northern Light sent up her boats to steal the stolen skins.</l>
                  <l>They had not brought a load to side or slid their hatches clear,</l>
                  <l>When they were aware of a sloop-of-war, ghost-white and very near.</l>
                  <l>Her flag she showed, and her guns she showed — three of them, black,</l>
                  <l>          abeam,</l>
                  <l>And a funnel white with the crusted salt, but never a show of steam.</l>
                  <l>There was no time to man the brakes, they knocked the shackle free,</l>
                  <l>And the Northern Light stood out again, goose-winged to open sea.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>(For life it is that is worse than death, by force of Russian law</l>
                  <l>To work in the mines of mercury that loose the teeth in your jaw!)</l>
                  <l>They had not run a mile from shore — they heard no shots behind —</l>
                  <l>When the skipper smote his hand on his thigh and threw her up in the</l>
                  <l>          wind:</l>
                  <l>“Bluffed — raised out on a bluff,” said he, “for if my name’s Tom Hall,</l>
                  <l>You must set a thief to catch a thief — and a thief has caught us all!</l>
                  <l>By every butt in Oregon and every spar in Maine,</l>
                  <l>The hand that spilled the wind from her sail was the hand of Reuben</l>
                  <l>          Paine!</l>
                  <l>He has rigged and trigged her with paint and spar, and, faith, he</l>
                  <l>          has faked her well —</l>
                  <l>But I’d know the Stralsund’s deckhouse yet from here to the booms o’</l>
                  <l>          Hell.</l>
                  <l>Oh, once we ha’ met at Baltimore, and twice on Boston pier,</l>
                  <l>But the sickest day for you, Reuben Paine, was the day that you came</l>
                  <l>          here —</l>
                  <l>The day that you came here, my lad, to scare us from our seal</l>
                  <l>With your funnel made o’ your painted cloth, and your guns o’ rotten</l>
                  <l>          deal!</l>
                  <l>Ring and blow for the Baltic now, and head her back to the bay,</l>
                  <l>For we’ll come into the game again with a double deck to play!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They rang and blew the sealers’ call — the poaching cry o’ the sea —</l>
                  <l>And they raised the Baltic out of the mist, and an angry ship was she:</l>
                  <l>And blind they groped through the whirling white, and blind to the</l>
                  <l>          bay again,</l>
                  <l>Till they heard the creak of the Stralsund’s boom and the clank of</l>
                  <l>          her mooring-chain.</l>
                  <l>They laid them down by bitt and boat, their pistols in their belts,</l>
                  <l>And: “Will you fight for it, Reuben Paine, or will you share the</l>
                  <l>          pelts?”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A dog-toothed laugh laughed Reuben Paine, and bared his flenching</l>
                  <l>          knife.</l>
                  <l>“Yea, skin for skin, and all that he hath a man will give for his life;</l>
                  <l>But I’ve six thousand skins below, and Yeddo Port to see,</l>
                  <l>And there’s never a law of God or man runs north of Fifty–Three.</l>
                  <l>So go in peace to the naked seas with empty holds to fill,</l>
                  <l>And I’ll be good to your seal this catch, as many as I shall kill.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Answered the snap of a closing lock and the jar of a gun-butt slid,</l>
                  <l>But the tender fog shut fold on fold to hide the wrong they did.</l>
                  <l>The weeping fog rolled fold on fold the wrath of man to cloak,</l>
                  <l>And the flame-spurts pale ran down the rail as the sealing-rifles</l>
                  <l>          spoke.</l>
                  <l>The bullets bit on bend and butt, the splinter slivered free,</l>
                  <l>(Little they trust to sparrow-dust that stop the seal in his sea!)</l>
                  <l>The thick smoke hung and would not shift, leaden it lay and blue,</l>
                  <l>But three were down on the Baltic’s deck and two of the Stralsund’s</l>
                  <l>          crew.</l>
                  <l>An arm’s length out and overside the banked fog held them bound;</l>
                  <l>But, as they heard or groan or word, they fired at the sound.</l>
                  <l>For one cried out on the name of God, and one to have him cease;</l>
                  <l>And the questing volley found them both and bade them hold their peace.</l>
                  <l>And one called out on a heathen joss and one on the Virgin’s Name;</l>
                  <l>And the schooling bullet leaped across and showed them whence they</l>
                  <l>          came.</l>
                  <l>And in the waiting silences the rudder whined beneath,</l>
                  <l>And each man drew his watchful breath slow taken ‘tween the teeth —</l>
                  <l>Trigger and ear and eye acock, knit brow and hard-drawn lips —</l>
                  <l>Bracing his feet by chock and cleat for the rolling of the ships:</l>
                  <l>Till they heard the cough of a wounded man that fought in the fog for</l>
                  <l>          breath,</l>
                  <l>Till they heard the torment of Reuben Paine that wailed upon his death:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“The tides they’ll go through Fundy Race but I’ll go never more</l>
                  <l>And see the hogs from ebb-tide mark turn scampering back to shore.</l>
                  <l>No more I’ll see the trawlers drift below the Bass Rock ground,</l>
                  <l>Or watch the tall Fall steamer lights tear blazing up the Sound.</l>
                  <l>Sorrow is me, in a lonely sea and a sinful fight I fall,</l>
                  <l>But if there’s law o’ God or man you’ll swing for it yet, Tom Hall!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tom Hall stood up by the quarter-rail. “Your words in your teeth,”</l>
                  <l>          said he.</l>
                  <l>“There’s never a law of God or man runs north of Fifty Three.</l>
                  <l>So go in grace with Him to face, and an ill-spent life behind,</l>
                  <l>And I’ll take care o’ your widows, Rube, as many as I shall find.”</l>
                  <l>A Stralsund man shot blind and large, and a warlock Finn was he,</l>
                  <l>And he hit Tom Hall with a bursting ball a hand’s-breadth over the</l>
                  <l>          knee.</l>
                  <l>Tom Hall caught hold by the topping-lift, and sat him down with an</l>
                  <l>          oath,</l>
                  <l>“You’ll wait a little, Rube,” he said, “the Devil has called for both.</l>
                  <l>The Devil is driving both this tide, and the killing-grounds are close,</l>
                  <l>And we’ll go up to the Wrath of God as the holluschickie goes.</l>
                  <l>O men, put back your guns again and lay your rifles by,</l>
                  <l>We’ve fought our fight, and the best are down. Let up and let us die!</l>
                  <l>Quit firing, by the bow there — quit! Call off the Baltic’s crew!</l>
                  <l>You’re sure of Hell as me or Rube — but wait till we get through.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There went no word between the ships, but thick and quick and loud</l>
                  <l>The life-blood drummed on the dripping decks, with the fog-dew from</l>
                  <l>          the shroud,</l>
                  <l>The sea-pull drew them side by side, gunnel to gunnel laid,</l>
                  <l>And they felt the sheerstrakes pound and clear, but never a word was</l>
                  <l>          said.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then Reuben Paine cried out again before his spirit passed:</l>
                  <l>“Have I followed the sea for thirty years to die in the dark at last?</l>
                  <l>Curse on her work that has nipped me here with a shifty trick unkind —</l>
                  <l>I have gotten my death where I got my bread, but I dare not face it</l>
                  <l>          blind.</l>
                  <l>Curse on the fog! Is there never a wind of all the winds I knew</l>
                  <l>To clear the smother from off my chest, and let me look at the blue?”</l>
                  <l>The good fog heard — like a splitten sail, to left and right she tore,</l>
                  <l>And they saw the sun-dogs in the haze and the seal upon the shore.</l>
                  <l>Silver and gray ran spit and bay to meet the steel-backed tide,</l>
                  <l>And pinched and white in the clearing light the crews stared overside.</l>
                  <l>O rainbow-gay the red pools lay that swilled and spilled and spread,</l>
                  <l>And gold, raw gold, the spent shell rolled between the careless dead —</l>
                  <l>The dead that rocked so drunkenwise to weather and to lee,</l>
                  <l>And they saw the work their hands had done as God had bade them see!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And a little breeze blew over the rail that made the headsails lift,</l>
                  <l>But no man stood by wheel or sheet, and they let the schooners drift.</l>
                  <l>And the rattle rose in Reuben’s throat and he cast his soul with a cry,</l>
                  <l>And “Gone already?” Tom Hall he said. “Then it’s time for me to die.”</l>
                  <l>His eyes were heavy with great sleep and yearning for the land,</l>
                  <l>And he spoke as a man that talks in dreams, his wound beneath his hand.</l>
                  <l>“Oh, there comes no good in the westering wind that backs against the</l>
                  <l>          sun;</l>
                  <l>Wash down the decks — they’re all too red — and share the skins and run,</l>
                  <l>Baltic, Stralsund, and Northern Light,— clean share and share for all,</l>
                  <l>You’ll find the fleets off Tolstoi Mees, but you will not find Tom</l>
                  <l>          Hall.</l>
                  <l>Evil he did in shoal-water and blacker sin on the deep,</l>
                  <l>But now he’s sick of watch and trick, and now he’ll turn and sleep.</l>
                  <l>He’ll have no more of the crawling sea that made him suffer so,</l>
                  <l>But he’ll lie down on the killing-grounds where the holluschickie go.</l>
                  <l>And west you’ll turn and south again, beyond the sea-fog’s rim,</l>
                  <l>And tell the Yoshiwara girls to burn a stick for him.</l>
                  <l>And you’ll not weight him by the heels and dump him overside,</l>
                  <l>But carry him up to the sand-hollows to die as Bering died,</l>
                  <l>And make a place for Reuben Paine that knows the fight was fair,</l>
                  <l>And leave the two that did the wrong to talk it over there!”</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Half-steam ahead by guess and lead, for the sun is mostly veiled —<lb/>
Through fog to fog, by luck and log, sail ye as Bering sailed;<lb/>
And, if the light shall lift aright to give your landfall plain,<lb/>
North and by west, from Zapne Crest, ye raise the Crosses Twain.<lb/>
Fair marks are they to the inner bay, the reckless poacher knows,<lb/>
What time the scarred see-catchie lead their sleek seraglios.<lb/>
Ever they hear the floe-pack clear, and the blast of the old<lb/>
          bull-whale,<lb/>
And the deep seal-roar that beats off shore above the loudest gale.<lb/>
Ever they wait the winter’s hate as the thundering</hi> boorga <hi rend="italic">calls,<lb/>
Where northward look they to St. George, and westward to St. Paul’s.<lb/>
Ever they greet the hunted fleet — lone keels off headlands drear —<lb/>
When the sealing-schooners flit that way at hazard year by year.<lb/>
Ever in Yokohama Port men tell the tale anew<lb/>
  Of a hidden sea and a hidden fight,<lb/>
  When the Baltic ran from the Northern Light<lb/>
And the Stralsund fought the two!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section13">
               <head>The Derelict.</head>
               <quote>
                  <p>“And reports the derelict <hi rend="italic">Mary Pollock</hi> still at sea.”</p>
               </quote>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Shipping News.</hi>
               </p>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">I was the staunchest of our fleet<lb/>
    Till the Sea rose beneath our feet<lb/>
Unheralded, in hatred past all measure.<lb/>
    Into his pits he stamped my crew,<lb/>
    Buffeted, blinded, bound and threw;<lb/>
Bidding me eyeless wait upon his pleasure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    Man made me, and my will<lb/>
    Is to my maker still,<lb/>
Whom now the currents con, the rollers steer —<lb/>
    Lifting forlorn to spy<lb/>
    Trailed smoke along the sky,<lb/>
Falling afraid lest any keel come near.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    Wrenched as the lips of thirst,<lb/>
    Wried, dried, and split and burst,<lb/>
Bone-bleached my decks, wind-scoured to the graining;<lb/>
    And, jarred at every roll,<lb/>
    The gear that was my soul<lb/>
Answers the anguish of my beams’ complaining.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    For life that crammed me full,<lb/>
    Gangs of the prying gull<lb/>
That shriek and scrabble on the riven hatches.<lb/>
    For roar that dumbed the gale<lb/>
    My hawse-pipes guttering wail,<lb/>
Sobbing my heart out through the uncounted watches.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    Blind in the hot blue ring<lb/>
    Through all my points I swing —<lb/>
Swing and return to shift the sun anew.<lb/>
    Blind in my well-known sky<lb/>
    I hear the stars go by,<lb/>
Mocking the prow that can not hold one true!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    White on my wasted path<lb/>
    Wave after wave in wrath<lb/>
Frets ‘gainst his fellow, warring where to send me.<lb/>
    Flung forward, heaved aside,<lb/>
    Witless and dazed I bide<lb/>
The mercy of the comber that shall end me.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    North where the bergs careen,<lb/>
    The spray of seas unseen<lb/>
Smokes round my head and freezes in the falling;<lb/>
    South where the corals breed,<lb/>
    The footless, floating weed<lb/>
Folds me and fouls me, strake on strake upcrawling.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    I that was clean to run<lb/>
    My race against the sun —<lb/>
Strength on the deep, am bawd to all disaster —<lb/>
    Whipped forth by night to meet<lb/>
    My sister’s careless feet,<lb/>
And with a kiss betray her to my master!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>    Man made me, and my will<lb/>
    Is to my maker still —<lb/>
To him and his, our peoples at their pier:<lb/>
    Lifting in hope to spy<lb/>
    Trailed smoke along the sky;<lb/>
Falling afraid lest any keel come near!</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section14">
               <head>The Song of the Banjo.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>You couldn’t pack a Broadwood half a mile —</l>
                  <l>  You mustn’t leave a fiddle in the damp —</l>
                  <l>You couldn’t raft an organ up the Nile,</l>
                  <l>  And play it in an Equatorial swamp.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">I</hi> travel with the cooking-pots and pails —</l>
                  <l>                     
                     <hi rend="italic">I</hi>’m sandwiched ‘tween the coffee and the pork —</l>
                  <l>And when the dusty column checks and tails,</l>
                  <l>  You should hear me spur the rearguard to a walk!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Pilly-willy-winky-winky popp!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      [O it’s any tune that comes into my head!]</l>
                  <l>    So I keep ’em moving forward till they drop;</l>
                  <l>      So I play ’em up to water and to bed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In the silence of the camp before the fight,</l>
                  <l>  When it’s good to make your will and say your prayer,</l>
                  <l>You can hear my <hi rend="italic">strumpty-tumpty</hi> overnight</l>
                  <l>  Explaining ten to one was always fair.</l>
                  <l>I’m the prophet of the Utterly Absurd,</l>
                  <l>  Of the Patently Impossible and Vain —</l>
                  <l>And when the Thing that Couldn’t has occurred,</l>
                  <l>  Give me time to change my leg and go again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Tumpa-tumpa-tumpa-tum-pa tump!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      In the desert where the dung-fed camp-smoke curled</l>
                  <l>    There was never voice before us till I led our lonely chorus,</l>
                  <l>      I— the war-drum of the White Man round the world!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By the bitter road the Younger Son must tread,</l>
                  <l>  Ere he win to hearth and saddle of his own,—</l>
                  <l>‘Mid the riot of the shearers at the shed,</l>
                  <l>  In the silence of the herder’s hut alone —</l>
                  <l>In the twilight, on a bucket upside down,</l>
                  <l>  Hear me babble what the weakest won’t confess —</l>
                  <l>I am Memory and Torment — I am Town!</l>
                  <l>  I am all that ever went with evening dress!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Tunk-a tunka-tunka-tunka-tunk!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      [So the lights — the London lights — grow near and plain!]</l>
                  <l>    So I rowel ’em afresh towards the Devil and the Flesh,</l>
                  <l>      Till I bring my broken rankers home again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In desire of many marvels over sea,</l>
                  <l>  Where the new-raised tropic city sweats and roars,</l>
                  <l>I have sailed with Young Ulysses from the quay</l>
                  <l>  Till the anchor rumbled down on stranger shores.</l>
                  <l>He is blooded to the open and the sky,</l>
                  <l>  He is taken in a snare that shall not fail,</l>
                  <l>He shall hear me singing strongly, till he die,</l>
                  <l>  Like the shouting of a backstay in a gale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Hya! Heeya! Heeya! Hullah! Haul!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      [O the green that thunders aft along the deck!]</l>
                  <l>    Are you sick o’ towns and men? You must sign and sail again,</l>
                  <l>      For it’s “Johnny Bowlegs, pack your kit and trek!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Through the gorge that gives the stars at noon-day clear —</l>
                  <l>  Up the pass that packs the scud beneath our wheel —</l>
                  <l>Round the bluff that sinks her thousand fathom sheer —</l>
                  <l>  Down the valley with our guttering brakes asqueal:</l>
                  <l>Where the trestle groans and quivers in the snow,</l>
                  <l>  Where the many-shedded levels loop and twine,</l>
                  <l>So I lead my reckless children from below</l>
                  <l>  Till we sing the Song of Roland to the pine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Tinka-tinka-tinka-tinka-tink!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      [And the axe has cleared the mountain, croup and crest!]</l>
                  <l>    So we ride the iron stallions down to drink,</l>
                  <l>      Through the cañons to the waters of the West!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And the tunes that mean so much to you alone —</l>
                  <l>  Common tunes that make you choke and blow your nose,</l>
                  <l>Vulgar tunes that bring the laugh that brings the groan —</l>
                  <l>  I can rip your very heartstrings out with those;</l>
                  <l>With the feasting, and the folly, and the fun —</l>
                  <l>  And the lying, and the lusting, and the drink,</l>
                  <l>And the merry play that drops you, when you’re done,</l>
                  <l>  To the thoughts that burn like irons if you think.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Plunka-lunka-lunka-lunka-lunk!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      Here’s a trifle on account of pleasure past,</l>
                  <l>    Ere the wit that made you win gives you eyes to see your sin</l>
                  <l>      And the heavier repentance at the last.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let the organ moan her sorrow to the roof —</l>
                  <l>  I have told the naked stars the grief of man.</l>
                  <l>Let the trumpets snare the foeman to the proof —</l>
                  <l>  I have known Defeat, and mocked it as we ran.</l>
                  <l>My bray ye may not alter nor mistake</l>
                  <l>  When I stand to jeer the fatted Soul of Things,</l>
                  <l>But the Song of Lost Endeavour that I make,</l>
                  <l>  Is it hidden in the twanging of the strings?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Ta-ra-rara-rara-ra-ra-rrrp!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      [Is it naught to you that hear and pass me by?]</l>
                  <l>    But the word — the word is mine, when the order moves the line</l>
                  <l>      And the lean, locked ranks go roaring down to die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The grandam of my grandam was the Lyre —</l>
                  <l>  [O the blue below the little fisher-huts!]</l>
                  <l>That the Stealer stooping beach ward filled with fire,</l>
                  <l>  Till she bore my iron head and ringing guts!</l>
                  <l>By the wisdom of the centuries I speak —</l>
                  <l>  To the tune of yestermorn I set the truth —</l>
                  <l>I, the joy of life unquestioned — I, the Greek —</l>
                  <l>  I, the everlasting Wonder Song of Youth!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    With my “<hi rend="italic">Tinka-tinka-tinka-tinka-tink!</hi>”</l>
                  <l>      [What d’ye lack, my noble masters? What d’ye lack?]</l>
                  <l>    So I draw the world together link by link:</l>
                  <l>      Yea, from Delos up to Limerick and back!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section15">
               <head>“The Liner She’s a Lady.”</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The Liner she’s a lady, an’ she never looks nor ’eeds —</l>
                  <l>The Man-o’-War’s ’er ’usband, an’ ’e gives ’er all she needs;</l>
                  <l>But, oh, the little cargo-boats, that sail the wet seas roun’,</l>
                  <l>They’re just the same as you an’ me a-plyin’ up an’ down!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Plyin’ up an’ down, Jenny, ’angin’ round the Yard,<lb/>
  All the way by Fratton tram down to Portsmouth ’Ard;<lb/>
  Anythin’ for business, an’ we’re growin’ old —<lb/>
  Plyin’ up an’ down, Jenny, waitin’ in the cold!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Liner she’s a lady by the paint upon ’er face,</l>
                  <l>An’ if she meets an accident they call it sore disgrace:</l>
                  <l>The Man-o’-War’s ’er ’usband, and ’e’s always ’andy by,</l>
                  <l>But, oh, the little cargo-boats! they’ve got to load or die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Liner she’s a lady, and ’er route is cut an’ dried;</l>
                  <l>The Man-o’-War’s ’er ’usband, an’ ’e always keeps beside;</l>
                  <l>But, oh, the little cargo-boats that ’aven’t any man!</l>
                  <l>They’ve got to do their business first, and make the most they can.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Liner she’s a lady, and if a war should come,</l>
                  <l>The Man-o’-War’s ’er ’usband, and ’e’d bid ’er stay at home;</l>
                  <l>But, oh, the little cargo-boats that fill with every tide!</l>
                  <l>’E’d ’ave to up an’ fight for them, for they are England’s pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Liner she’s a lady, but if she wasn’t made,</l>
                  <l>There still would be the cargo-boats for ’ome an’ foreign trade.</l>
                  <l>The Man-o’-War’s ’er ’usband, but if we wasn’t ’ere,</l>
                  <l>’E wouldn’t have to fight at all for ’ome an’ friends so dear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  ’Ome an’ friends so dear, Jenny, ’angin’ round the Yard,</l>
                  <l>  All the way by Fratton tram down to Portsmouth ’Ard;</l>
                  <l>  Anythin’ for business, an’ we’re growin’ old —</l>
                  <l>  ’Ome an’ friends so dear, Jenny, waitin’ in the cold!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section16">
               <head>Mulholland’s Contract.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The fear was on the cattle, for the gale was on the sea,</l>
                  <l>An’ the pens broke up on the lower deck an’ let the creatures free —</l>
                  <l>An’ the lights went out on the lower deck, an’ no one down but me.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>I had been singin’ to them to keep ’em quiet there,</l>
                  <l>For the lower deck is the dangerousest, requirin’ constant care,</l>
                  <l>An’ give to me as the strongest man, though used to drink and swear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I see my chance was certain of bein’ horned or trod,</l>
                  <l>For the lower deck was packed with steers thicker ‘n peas in a pod,</l>
                  <l>An’ more pens broke at every roll — so I made a Contract with God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ by the terms of the Contract, as I have read the same,</l>
                  <l>If He got me to port alive I would exalt His name,</l>
                  <l>An’ praise His Holy Majesty till further orders came.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He saved me from the cattle an’ He saved me from the sea,</l>
                  <l>For they found me ‘tween two drownded ones where the roll had landed</l>
                  <l>          me —</l>
                  <l>An’ a four-inch crack on top of my head, as crazy as could be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But that were done by a stanchion, an’ not by a bullock at all,</l>
                  <l>An’ I lay still for seven weeks convalessing of the fall,</l>
                  <l>An’ readin’ the shiny Scripture texts in the Seamen’s Hospital.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ I spoke to God of our Contract, an’ He says to my prayer:</l>
                  <l>“I never puts on My ministers no more than they can bear.</l>
                  <l>So back you go to the cattle-boats an’ preach My Gospel there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“For human life is chancy at any kind of trade,</l>
                  <l>But most of all, as well you know, when the steers are mad-afraid;</l>
                  <l>So you go back to the cattle-boats an’ preach ’em as I’ve said.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“They must quit drinkin’ an’ swearin’, they mustn’t knife on a blow,</l>
                  <l>They must quit gamblin’ their wages, and you must preach it so;</l>
                  <l>For now those boats are more like Hell than anything else I know.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I didn’t want to do it, for I knew what I should get,</l>
                  <l>An’ I wanted to preach Religion, handsome an’ out of the wet,</l>
                  <l>But the Word of the Lord were lain on me, an’ I done what I was set.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I have been smit an’ bruisèd, as warned would be the case,</l>
                  <l>An’ turned my cheek to the smiter exactly as Scripture says;</l>
                  <l>But following that, I knocked him down an’ led him up to Grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ we have preaching on Sundays whenever the sea is calm,</l>
                  <l>An’ I use no knife nor pistol an’ I never take no harm,</l>
                  <l>For the Lord abideth back of me to guide my fighting arm.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ I sign for four pound ten a month and save the money clear,</l>
                  <l>An’ I am in charge of the lower deck, an’ I never lose a steer;</l>
                  <l>An’ I believe in Almighty God an’ I preach His Gospel here.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The skippers say I’m crazy, but I can prove ’em wrong,</l>
                  <l>For I am in charge of the lower deck with all that doth belong —</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Which they would not give to a lunatic, and the competition so<lb/>
          strong!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section17">
               <head>Anchor Song.</head>
               <p>(<hi rend="italic">From Many Inventions</hi>).</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Heh! Walk her round. Heave, ah heave her short again!<lb/>
  Over, snatch her over, there, and hold her on the pawl.<lb/>
Loose all sail, and brace your yards aback and full —<lb/>
  Ready jib to pay her off and heave short all!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  Well, ah fare you well; we can stay no more with you, my love —<lb/>
    Down, set down your liquor and your girl from off your knee;<lb/>
        For the wind has come to say:<lb/>
        “You must take me while you may,<lb/>
      If you’d go to Mother Carey,<lb/>
      (Walk her down to Mother Carey!)<lb/>
    Oh, we’re bound to Mother Carey where she feeds her chicks at sea!”</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Heh! Walk her round. Break, ah break it out o’ that!<lb/>
  Break our starboard bower out, apeak, awash, and clear.<lb/>
Port — port she casts, with the harbour-roil beneath her foot,<lb/>
  And that’s the last o’ bottom we shall see this year!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  Well, ah fare you well, for we’ve got to take her out again —<lb/>
    Take her out in ballast, riding light and cargo-free.<lb/>
        And it’s time to clear and quit<lb/>
        When the hawser grips the bitt,<lb/>
    So we’ll pay you with the foresheet and a promise from the sea!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Heh! Tally on! Aft and walk away with her!<lb/>
  Handsome to the cathead, now; O tally on the fall!<lb/>
Stop, seize and fish, and easy on the davit-guy.<lb/>
  Up, well up the fluke of her, and inboard haul!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  Well, ah fare you well, for the Channel wind’s took hold of us,<lb/>
    Choking down our voices as we snatch the gaskets free.<lb/>
        And it’s blowing up for night,<lb/>
        And she’s dropping Light on Light,<lb/>
    And she’s snorting under bonnets for a breath of open sea.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Wheel, full and by; but she’ll smell her road alone to-night.<lb/>
  Sick she is and harbour-sick — O sick to clear the land!<lb/>
Roll down to Brest with the old Red Ensign over us —<lb/>
  Carry on and thrash her out with all she’ll stand!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  Well, ah fare you well, and it’s Ushant gives the door to us,<lb/>
    Whirling like a windmill on the dirty scud to lee:<lb/>
        Till the last, last flicker goes<lb/>
        From the tumbling water-rows,<lb/>
      And we’re off to Mother Carey<lb/>
      (Walk her down to Mother Carey!)<lb/>
    Oh, we’re bound for Mother Carey where she feeds her chicks at sea!</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section18">
               <head>The Sea-Wife.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>There dwells a wife by the Northern Gate,</l>
                  <l>  And a wealthy wife is she;</l>
                  <l>She breeds a breed o’ rovin’ men</l>
                  <l>  And casts them over sea,</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>And some are drowned in deep water,</l>
                  <l>  And some in sight o’ shore.</l>
                  <l>And word goes back to the weary wife,</l>
                  <l>  And ever she sends more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For since that wife had gate and gear,</l>
                  <l>  And hearth and garth and bield,</l>
                  <l>She willed her sons to the white harvest,</l>
                  <l>  And that is a bitter yield.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She wills her sons to the wet ploughing,</l>
                  <l>  To ride the horse of tree;</l>
                  <l>And syne her sons come home again</l>
                  <l>  Far-spent from out the sea.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The good wife’s sons come home again</l>
                  <l>  With little into their hands,</l>
                  <l>But the lore of men that ha’ dealt with men</l>
                  <l>  In the new and naked lands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But the faith of men that ha’ brothered men</l>
                  <l>  By more than the easy breath,</l>
                  <l>And the eyes o’ men that ha’ read wi’ men</l>
                  <l>  In the open books of death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rich are they, rich in wonders seen,</l>
                  <l>  But poor in the goods o’ men,</l>
                  <l>So what they ha’ got by the skin o’ their teeth</l>
                  <l>  They sell for their teeth again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For whether they lose to the naked skin,</l>
                  <l>  Or win to their hearts’ desire,</l>
                  <l>They tell it all to the weary wife</l>
                  <l>  That nods beside the fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her hearth is wide to every wind</l>
                  <l>  That makes the white ash spin;</l>
                  <l>And tide and tide and ‘tween the tides</l>
                  <l>  Her sons go out and in;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>(Out with great mirth that do desire</l>
                  <l>  Hazard of trackless ways,</l>
                  <l>In with content to wait their watch</l>
                  <l>  And warm before the blaze);</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And some return by failing light,</l>
                  <l>  And some in waking dream,</l>
                  <l>For she hears the heels of the dripping ghosts</l>
                  <l>  That ride the rough roof-beam.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Home, they come home from all the ports,</l>
                  <l>  The living and the dead;</l>
                  <l>The good wife’s sons come home again</l>
                  <l>  For her blessing on their head!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section19">
               <head>Hymn Before Action.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The earth is full of anger,</l>
                  <l>  The seas are dark with wrath;</l>
                  <l>The Nations in their harness</l>
                  <l>  Go up against our path!</l>
                  <l>Ere yet we loose the legions —</l>
                  <l>  Ere yet we draw the blade,</l>
                  <l>Jehovah of the Thunders,</l>
                  <l>  Lord God of Battles, aid!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>High lust and froward bearing,</l>
                  <l>  Proud heart, rebellious brow —</l>
                  <l>Deaf ear and soul uncaring,</l>
                  <l>  We seek Thy mercy now:</l>
                  <l>The sinner that forswore Thee,</l>
                  <l>  The fool that passed Thee by,</l>
                  <l>Our times are known before Thee —</l>
                  <l>  Lord, grant us strength to die!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For those who kneel beside us</l>
                  <l>  At altars not Thine own,</l>
                  <l>Who lack the lights that guide us,</l>
                  <l>  Lord, let their faith atone;</l>
                  <l>If wrong we did to call them,</l>
                  <l>  By honour bound they came;</l>
                  <l>Let not Thy wrath befall them,</l>
                  <l>  But deal to us the blame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From panic, pride, and terror,</l>
                  <l>  Revenge that knows no rein —</l>
                  <l>Light haste and lawless error,</l>
                  <l>  Protect us yet again.</l>
                  <l>Cloak Thou our undeserving,</l>
                  <l>  Make firm the shuddering breath,</l>
                  <l>In silence and unswerving</l>
                  <l>  To taste thy lesser death!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, Mary pierced with sorrow,</l>
                  <l>  Remember, reach and save</l>
                  <l>The soul that comes tomorrow</l>
                  <l>  Before the God that gave!</l>
                  <l>Since each was born of woman,</l>
                  <l>  For each at utter need —</l>
                  <l>True comrade and true foeman,</l>
                  <l>  Madonna, intercede!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>E’en now their vanguard gathers,</l>
                  <l>  E’en now we face the fray —</l>
                  <l>As Thou didst help our fathers,</l>
                  <l>  Help Thou our host today!</l>
                  <l>Fulfilled of signs and wonders,</l>
                  <l>  In life, in death made clear —</l>
                  <l>Jehovah of the Thunders,</l>
                  <l>  Lord God of Battles, hear!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section20">
               <head>To the True Romance.</head>
               <p>(<hi rend="italic">From Many Inventions</hi>).</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thy face is far from this our war,<lb/>
  Our call and counter-cry,<lb/>
I shall not find Thee quick and kind,<lb/>
  Nor know Thee till I die:<lb/>
Enough for me in dreams to see<lb/>
  And touch Thy garments’ hem:<lb/>
Thy feet have trod so near to God<lb/>
  I may not follow them.</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Through wantonness if men profess<lb/>
  They weary of Thy parts,<lb/>
E’en let them die at blasphemy<lb/>
  And perish with their arts;<lb/>
But we that love, but we that prove<lb/>
  Thine excellence august,<lb/>
While we adore discover more<lb/>
  Thee perfect, wise, and just.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Since spoken word Man’s Spirit stirred<lb/>
  Beyond his belly-need,<lb/>
What is is Thine of fair design<lb/>
  In thought and craft and deed;<lb/>
Each stroke aright of toil and fight,<lb/>
  That was and that shall be,<lb/>
And hope too high, wherefore we die,<lb/>
  Has birth and worth in Thee.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Who holds by Thee hath Heaven in fee<lb/>
  To gild his dross thereby,<lb/>
And knowledge sure that he endure<lb/>
  A child until he die —<lb/>
For to make plain that man’s disdain<lb/>
  Is but new Beauty’s birth —<lb/>
For to possess, in loneliness,<lb/>
  The joy of all the earth.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>As Thou didst teach all lovers speech,<lb/>
  And Life all mystery,<lb/>
So shalt Thou rule by every school<lb/>
  Till love and longing die,<lb/>
Who wast or yet the lights were set,<lb/>
  A whisper in the Void,<lb/>
Who shalt be sung through planets young<lb/>
  When this is clean destroyed.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Beyond the bounds our staring rounds,<lb/>
  Across the pressing dark,<lb/>
The children wise of outer skies<lb/>
  Look hitherward and mark<lb/>
A light that shifts, a glare that drifts,<lb/>
  Rekindling thus and thus,<lb/>
Not all forlorn, for Thou hast borne<lb/>
  Strange tales to them of us.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Time hath no tide but must abide<lb/>
  The servant of Thy will;<lb/>
Tide hath no time, for to Thy rhyme<lb/>
  The ranging stars stand still —<lb/>
Regent of spheres that lock our fears<lb/>
  Our hopes invisible,<lb/>
Oh ’twas certes at Thy decrees<lb/>
  We fashioned Heaven and Hell!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Pure Wisdom hath no certain path<lb/>
  That lacks thy morning-eyne,<lb/>
And captains bold by Thee controlled<lb/>
  Most like to Gods design;<lb/>
Thou art the Voice to kingly boys<lb/>
  To lift them through the fight,<lb/>
And Comfortress of Unsuccess,<lb/>
  To give the dead good-night —</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>A veil to draw ‘twixt God His Law<lb/>
  And Man’s infirmity,<lb/>
A shadow kind to dumb and blind<lb/>
  The shambles where we die;<lb/>
A sum to trick th’ arithmetic<lb/>
  Too base of leaguing odds,<lb/>
The spur of trust, the curb of lust,<lb/>
  Thou handmaid of the Gods!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Oh Charity, all patiently<lb/>
  Abiding wrack and scaith!<lb/>
Oh Faith, that meets ten thousand cheats<lb/>
  Yet drops no jot of faith!<lb/>
Devil and brute Thou dost transmute<lb/>
  To higher, lordlier show,<lb/>
Who art in sooth that lovely Truth<lb/>
  The careless angels know!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thy face is far from this our war,<lb/>
  Our call and counter-cry,<lb/>
I may not find Thee quick and kind,<lb/>
  Nor meet Thee till I die.</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Yet may I look with heart unshook<lb/>
  On blow brought home or missed —<lb/>
Yet may I hear with equal ear<lb/>
  The clarions down the list;<lb/>
Yet set my lance above mischance<lb/>
  And ride the barriere —<lb/>
Oh, hit or miss, how little ’tis,<lb/>
  My Lady is not there!</hi>
                     <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section21">
               <head>The Flowers.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>“To our private taste, there is always something a little exotic,</l>
                  <l>almost artificial, in songs which, under an English aspect and</l>
                  <l>dress, are yet so manifestly the product of other skies. They affect</l>
                  <l>us like translations; the very fauna and flora are alien, remote;</l>
                  <l>the dog’s-tooth violet is but an ill substitute for the rathe</l>
                  <l>primrose, nor can we ever believe that the wood-robin sings as</l>
                  <l>sweetly in April as the English thrush.”— <hi rend="italic">The Athenæum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>      
                     <hi rend="italic">Buy my English posies —<lb/>
        Kent and Surrey may,<lb/>
      Violets of the Undercliff<lb/>
        Wet with Channel spray;<lb/>
      Cowslips from a Devon combe<lb/>
        Midland furze afire —<lb/>
      Buy my English posies,<lb/>
        And I’ll sell your hearts’ desire!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>      Buy my English posies!—</l>
                  <l>        You that scorn the may</l>
                  <l>      Won’t you greet a friend from home</l>
                  <l>        Half the world away?</l>
                  <l>      Green against the draggled drift,</l>
                  <l>        Faint and frail and first —</l>
                  <l>      Buy my Northern blood-root</l>
                  <l>        And I’ll know where you were nursed!</l>
                  <l>Robin down the logging-road whistles, “Come to me,”</l>
                  <l>Spring has found the maple-grove, the sap is running free;</l>
                  <l>All the winds o’ Canada call the ploughing-rain.</l>
                  <l>Take the flower and turn the hour, and kiss your love again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>      Buy my English posies!—</l>
                  <l>        Here’s to match your need.</l>
                  <l>      Buy a tuft of royal heath,</l>
                  <l>        Buy a bunch of weed</l>
                  <l>      White as sand of Muysenberg</l>
                  <l>        Spun before the gale —</l>
                  <l>      Buy my heath and lilies</l>
                  <l>        And I’ll tell you whence you hail!</l>
                  <l>Under hot Constantia broad the vineyards lie —</l>
                  <l>Throned and thorned the aching berg props the speckless sky —</l>
                  <l>Slow below the Wynberg firs trails the tilted wain —</l>
                  <l>Take the flower and turn the hour, and kiss your love again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>      Buy my English posies!—</l>
                  <l>        You that will not turn,</l>
                  <l>      Buy my hot-wood clematis,</l>
                  <l>        Buy a frond o’ fern</l>
                  <l>      Gathered where the Erskine leaps</l>
                  <l>        Down the road to Lorne —</l>
                  <l>      Buy my Christmas creeper</l>
                  <l>        And I’ll say where you were born!</l>
                  <l>West away from Melbourne dust holidays begin —</l>
                  <l>They that mock at Paradise woo at Cora Lynn —</l>
                  <l>Through the great South Otway gums sings the great South Main —</l>
                  <l>Take the flower and turn the hour, and kiss your love again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>      Buy my English posies!—</l>
                  <l>        Here’s your choice unsold!</l>
                  <l>      Buy a blood-red myrtle-bloom,</l>
                  <l>        Buy the kowhai’s gold</l>
                  <l>      Flung for gift on Taupo’s face</l>
                  <l>        Sign that spring is come —</l>
                  <l>      Buy my clinging myrtle</l>
                  <l>        And I’ll give you back your home!</l>
                  <l>Broom behind the windy town; pollen o’ the pine —</l>
                  <l>Bell-bird in the leafy deep where the <hi rend="italic">ratas</hi> twine —</l>
                  <l>Fern above the saddle-bow, flax upon the plain —</l>
                  <l>Take the flower and turn the hour, and kiss your love again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>      Buy my English posies!</l>
                  <l>        Ye that have your own</l>
                  <l>      Buy them for a brother’s sake</l>
                  <l>        Overseas, alone.</l>
                  <l>      Weed ye trample underfoot</l>
                  <l>        Floods his heart abrim —</l>
                  <l>      Bird ye never heeded,</l>
                  <l>        Oh, she calls his dead to him!</l>
                  <l>Far and far our homes are set round the Seven Seas.</l>
                  <l>Woe for us if we forget, we that hold by these!</l>
                  <l>Unto each his mother-beach, bloom and bird and land —</l>
                  <l>Masters of the Seven Seas, oh, love and understand!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section22">
               <head>The Last Rhyme of True Thomas.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The King has called for priest and cup,</l>
                  <l>  The King has taken spur and blade</l>
                  <l>To dub True Thomas a belted knight,</l>
                  <l>  And all for the sake o’ the songs he made.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>They have sought him high, they have sought him low,</l>
                  <l>  They have sought him over down and lea;</l>
                  <l>They have found him by the milk-white thorn</l>
                  <l>  That guards the gates o’ Faerie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’Twas bent beneath and blue above,</l>
                  <l>  Their eyes were held that they might not see</l>
                  <l>The kine that grazed between the knowes,</l>
                  <l>  Oh, they were the Queens o’ Faerie!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Now cease your song,” the King he said,</l>
                  <l>  “Oh, cease your song and get you dight</l>
                  <l>To vow your vow and watch your arms,</l>
                  <l>  For I will dub you a belted knight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“For I will give you a horse o’ pride,</l>
                  <l>  Wi’ blazon and spur and page and squire;</l>
                  <l>Wi’ keep and tail and seizin and law,</l>
                  <l>  And land to hold at your desire.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>True Thomas smiled above his harp,</l>
                  <l>  And turned his face to the naked sky,</l>
                  <l>Where, blown before the wastrel wind,</l>
                  <l>  The thistle-down she floated by.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“I ha’ vowed my vow in another place,</l>
                  <l>  And bitter oath it was on me,</l>
                  <l>I ha’ watched my arms the lee-long night,</l>
                  <l>  Where five-score fighting-men would flee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“My lance is tipped o’ the hammered flame,</l>
                  <l>  My shield is beat o’ the moonlight cold;</l>
                  <l>And I won my spurs in the Middle World,</l>
                  <l>  A thousand fathoms beneath the mould.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“And what should I make wi’ a horse o’ pride,</l>
                  <l>  And what should I make wi’ a sword so brown,</l>
                  <l>But spill the rings o’ the Gentle Folk</l>
                  <l>  And flyte my kin in the Fairy Town?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“And what should I make wi’ blazon and belt,</l>
                  <l>  Wi’ keep and tail and seizin and fee,</l>
                  <l>And what should I do wi’ page and squire</l>
                  <l>  That am a king in my own countrie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“For I send east and I send west,</l>
                  <l>  And I send far as my will may flee,</l>
                  <l>By dawn and dusk and the drinking rain,</l>
                  <l>  And syne my Sendings return to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“They come wi’ news of the groanin’ earth,</l>
                  <l>  They come wi’ news o’ the roarin’ sea,</l>
                  <l>Wi’ word of Spirit and Ghost and Flesh,</l>
                  <l>  And man that’s mazed among the three.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The King he bit his nether lip,</l>
                  <l>  And smote his hand upon his knee:</l>
                  <l>“By the faith o’ my soul, True Thomas,” he said,</l>
                  <l>  “Ye waste no wit in courtesie!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“As I desire, unto my pride,</l>
                  <l>  Can I make Earls by three and three,</l>
                  <l>To run before and ride behind</l>
                  <l>  And serve the sons o’ my body.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“And what care I for your row-foot earls,</l>
                  <l>  Or all the sons o’ your body?</l>
                  <l>Before they win to the Pride o’ Name,</l>
                  <l>  I trow they all ask leave o’ me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“For I make Honour wi’ muckle mouth,</l>
                  <l>  As I make Shame wi’ mincin’ feet,</l>
                  <l>To sing wi’ the priests at the market-cross,</l>
                  <l>  Or run wi’ the dogs in the naked street.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“And some they give me the good red gold,</l>
                  <l>  And some they give me the white money,</l>
                  <l>And some they give me a clout o’ meal,</l>
                  <l>  For they be people o’ low degree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“And the song I sing for the counted gold</l>
                  <l>  The same I sing for the white money,</l>
                  <l>But best I sing for the clout o’ meal</l>
                  <l>  That simple people given me.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The King cast down a silver groat,</l>
                  <l>  A silver groat o’ Scots money,</l>
                  <l>“If I come with a poor man’s dole,” he said,</l>
                  <l>  “True Thomas, will ye harp to me?”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Whenas I harp to the children small,</l>
                  <l>  They press me close on either hand:</l>
                  <l>And who are you,” True Thomas said,</l>
                  <l>  “That you should ride while they must stand?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Light down, light down from your horse o’ pride,</l>
                  <l>  I trow ye talk too loud and hie,</l>
                  <l>And I will make you a triple word,</l>
                  <l>  And syne, if ye dare, ye shall ‘noble me.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He has lighted down from his horse o’ pride,</l>
                  <l>  And set his back against the stone.</l>
                  <l>“Now guard you well,” True Thomas said,</l>
                  <l>  “Ere I rax your heart from your breast-bone!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>True Thomas played upon his harp,</l>
                  <l>  The fairy harp that couldna’ lee,</l>
                  <l>And the first least word the proud King heard,</l>
                  <l>  It harpit the salt tear out o’ his ee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Oh, I see the love that I lost long syne,</l>
                  <l>  I touch the hope that I may not see,</l>
                  <l>And all that I did o’ hidden shame,</l>
                  <l>  Like little snakes they hiss at me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“The sun is lost at noon — at noon!</l>
                  <l>  The dread o’ doom has grippit me.</l>
                  <l>True Thomas, hide me under your cloak,</l>
                  <l>  God wot, I’m little fit to dee!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’Twas bent beneath and blue above —</l>
                  <l>  ’Twas open field and running flood —</l>
                  <l>Where, hot on heath and dyke and wall,</l>
                  <l>  The high sun warmed the adder’s brood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Lie down, lie down,” True Thomas said.</l>
                  <l>  “The God shall judge when all is done;</l>
                  <l>But I will bring you a better word</l>
                  <l>  And lift the cloud that I laid on.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>True Thomas played upon his harp,</l>
                  <l>  That birled and brattled to his hand,</l>
                  <l>And the next least word True Thomas made,</l>
                  <l>  It garred the King take horse and brand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Oh, I hear the tread o’ the fighting-men,</l>
                  <l>  I see the sun on splent and spear!</l>
                  <l>I mark the arrow outen the fern!</l>
                  <l>  That flies so low and sings so clear!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Advance my standards to that war,</l>
                  <l>  And bid my good knights prick and ride;</l>
                  <l>The gled shall watch as fierce a fight</l>
                  <l>  As e’er was fought on the Border side!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’Twas bent beneath and blue above,</l>
                  <l>  ’Twas nodding grass and naked sky,</l>
                  <l>Where ringing up the wastrel wind</l>
                  <l>  The eyass stooped upon the pye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>True Thomas sighed above his harp,</l>
                  <l>  And turned the song on the midmost string;</l>
                  <l>And the last least word True Thomas made</l>
                  <l>  He harpit his dead youth back to the King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Now I am prince, and I do well</l>
                  <l>  To love my love withouten fear;</l>
                  <l>To walk wi’ man in fellowship,</l>
                  <l>  And breathe my horse behind the deer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“My hounds they bay unto the death,</l>
                  <l>  The buck has couched beyond the burn,</l>
                  <l>My love she waits at her window</l>
                  <l>  To wash my hands when I return.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“For that I live am I content</l>
                  <l>  (Oh! I have seen my true love’s eyes!)</l>
                  <l>To stand wi’ Adam in Eden-glade,</l>
                  <l>  And run in the woods o’ Paradise!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’Twas nodding grass and naked sky,</l>
                  <l>  ’Twas blue above and bent below,</l>
                  <l>Where, checked against the wastrel wind,</l>
                  <l>  The red deer belled to call the doe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>True Thomas laid his harp away,</l>
                  <l>  And louted low at the saddle-side;</l>
                  <l>He has taken stirrup and hauden rein,</l>
                  <l>  And set the King on his horse o’ pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Sleep ye or wake,” True Thomas said,</l>
                  <l>  “That sit so still, that muse so long;</l>
                  <l>Sleep ye or wake?— till the latter sleep</l>
                  <l>  I trow ye’ll not forget my song.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“I ha’ harpit a shadow out o’ the sun</l>
                  <l>  To stand before your face and cry;</l>
                  <l>I ha’ armed the earth beneath your heel,</l>
                  <l>  And over your head I ha’ dusked the sky!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“I ha’ harpit ye up to the Throne o’ God,</l>
                  <l>  I ha’ harpit your secret soul in three;</l>
                  <l>I ha’ harpit ye down to the Hinges o’ Hell,</l>
                  <l>  And — ye — would — make — a Knight o’ me!”</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section23">
               <head>The Story of Ung.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>Once, on a glittering ice-field, ages and ages ago,</l>
                  <l>Ung, a maker of pictures, fashioned an image of snow.</l>
                  <l>Fashioned the form of a tribesman — gaily he whistled and sung,</l>
                  <l>Working the snow with his fingers. <hi rend="italic">Read ye the Story of Ung!</hi>
                  </l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pleased was his tribe with that image — came in their hundreds to scan —</l>
                  <l>Handled it, smelt it, and grunted: “Verily, this is a man!</l>
                  <l>Thus do we carry our lances — thus is a war-belt slung.</l>
                  <l>Ay, it is even as we are. Glory and honour to Ung!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Later he pictured an aurochs — later he pictured a bear —</l>
                  <l>Pictured the sabre-tooth tiger dragging a man to his lair —</l>
                  <l>Pictured the mountainous mammoth, hairy, abhorrent, alone —</l>
                  <l>Out of the love that he bore them, scribing them clearly on bone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Swift came the tribe to behold them, peering and pushing and still —</l>
                  <l>Men of the berg-battered beaches, men of the boulder-hatched hill,</l>
                  <l>Hunters and fishers and trappers — presently whispering low;</l>
                  <l>“Yea, they are like — and it may be.... But how does the Picture-man</l>
                  <l>          know?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Ung — hath he slept with the Aurochs — watched where the Mastodon roam?</l>
                  <l>Spoke on the ice with the Bow-head — followed the Sabre-tooth home?</l>
                  <l>Nay! These are toys of his fancy! If he have cheated us so,</l>
                  <l>How is there truth in his image — the man that he fashioned of snow?”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wroth was that maker of pictures — hotly he answered the call:</l>
                  <l>“Hunters and fishers and trappers, children and fools are ye all!</l>
                  <l>Look at the beasts when ye hunt them!” Swift from the tumult he broke,</l>
                  <l>Ran to the cave of his father and told him the shame that they spoke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And the father of Ung gave answer, that was old and wise in the craft,</l>
                  <l>Maker of pictures aforetime, he leaned on his lance and laughed:</l>
                  <l>“If they could see as thou seest they would do what thou hast done,</l>
                  <l>And each man would make him a picture, and — what would become of my</l>
                  <l>          son?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“There would be no pelts of the reindeer, flung down at thy cave for a</l>
                  <l>          gift,</l>
                  <l>Nor dole of the oily timber that strands with the Baltic drift;</l>
                  <l>No store of well-drilled needles, nor ouches of amber pale;</l>
                  <l>No new-cut tongues of the bison, nor meat of the stranded whale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“<hi rend="italic">Thou</hi> hast not toiled at the fishing when the sodden trammels freeze,</l>
                  <l>Nor worked the war-boats outward, through the rush of the rock-staked</l>
                  <l>          seas,</l>
                  <l>Yet they bring thee fish and plunder — full meal and an easy bed —</l>
                  <l>And all for the sake of thy pictures.” And Ung held down his head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“<hi rend="italic">Thou</hi> hast not stood to the aurochs when the red snow reeks of the</l>
                  <l>          fight;</l>
                  <l>Men have no time at the houghing to count his curls aright:</l>
                  <l>And the heart of the hairy mammoth thou sayest they do not see,</l>
                  <l>Yet they save it whole from the beaches and broil the best for thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>“And now do they press to thy pictures, with open mouth and eye,</l>
                  <l>And a little gift in the doorway, and the praise no gift can buy:</l>
                  <l>But — sure they have doubted thy pictures, and that is a grievous</l>
                  <l>          stain —</l>
                  <l>Son that can see so clearly, return them their gifts again.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And Ung looked down at his deerskins — their broad shell-tasselled</l>
                  <l>          bands —</l>
                  <l>And Ung drew downward his mitten and looked at his naked hands;</l>
                  <l>And he gloved himself and departed, and he heard his father, behind:</l>
                  <l>“Son that can see so clearly, rejoice that thy tribe is blind!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Straight on that glittering ice-field, by the caves of the lost</l>
                  <l>          Dordogne,</l>
                  <l>Ung, a maker of pictures, fell to his scribing on bone —</l>
                  <l>Even to mammoth editions. Gaily he whistled and sung,</l>
                  <l>Blessing his tribe for their blindness. <hi rend="italic">Heed ye the Story of Ung!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section24">
               <head>The Three-Decker.</head>
               <p>“The three-volume novel is extinct.”</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>Full thirty foot she towered from waterline to rail.<lb/>
It cost a watch to steer her, and a week to shorten sail;<lb/>
But, spite all modern notions, I found her first and best —<lb/>
The only certain packet for the Islands of the Blest.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Fair held our breeze behind us —’twas warm with lovers’ prayers:<lb/>
We’d stolen wills for ballast and a crew of missing heirs;<lb/>
They shipped as Able Bastards till the Wicked Nurse confessed,<lb/>
And they worked the old three-decker to the Islands of the Blest.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Carambas</hi> and <hi rend="italic">serapés</hi> we waved to every wind,<lb/>
We smoked good Corpo Bacco when our sweethearts proved unkind;<lb/>
With maids of matchless beauty and parentage unguessed<lb/>
We also took our manners to the Islands of the Blest.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>We asked no social questions — we pumped no hidden shame —<lb/>
We never talked obstetrics when the little stranger came:<lb/>
We left the Lord in Heaven, we left the fiends in Hell.<lb/>
We weren’t exactly Yussufs, but — Zuleika didn’t tell!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>No moral doubt assailed us, so when the port we neared,<lb/>
The villain got his flogging at the gangway, and we cheered.<lb/>
’Twas fiddles in the foc’sle —’twas garlands on the mast,<lb/>
For every one got married, and I went ashore at last.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>I left ’em all in couples akissing on the decks.<lb/>
I left the lovers loving and the parents signing checks.<lb/>
In endless English comfort by county-folk caressed,<lb/>
I left the old three-decker at the Islands of the Blest!</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>That route is barred to steamers: you’ll never lift again<lb/>
Our purple-painted headlands or the lordly keeps of Spain.<lb/>
They’re just beyond the skyline, howe’er so far you cruise<lb/>
In a ram-you-damn-you liner with a brace of bucking screws.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Swing round your aching search-light —’twill show no haven’s peace!<lb/>
Ay, blow your shrieking sirens to the deaf, gray-bearded seas!<lb/>
Boom out the dripping oil-bags to skin the deep’s unrest —<lb/>
But you aren’t a knot the nearer to the Islands of the Blest.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>And when you’re threshing, crippled, with broken bridge and rail,<lb/>
On a drogue of dead convictions to hold you head to gale,<lb/>
Calm as the Flying Dutchman, from truck to taffrail dressed,<lb/>
You’ll see the old three-decker for the Islands of the Blest.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>You’ll see her tiering canvas in sheeted silver spread;<lb/>
You’ll hear the long-drawn thunder ‘neath her leaping figure-head;<lb/>
While far, so far above you, her tall poop-lanterns shine<lb/>
Unvexed by wind or weather like the candles round a shrine.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Hull down — hull down and under — she dwindles to a speck,<lb/>
With noise of pleasant music and dancing on her deck.<lb/>
All’s well — all’s well aboard her — she’s dropped you far behind,<lb/>
With a scent of old-world roses through the fog that ties you blind.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Her crew are babes or madmen? Her port is all to make?<lb/>
You’re manned by Truth and Science, and you steam for steaming’s sake?<lb/>
Well, tinker up your engines — you know your business best —<lb/>
                     <hi rend="italic">She’s</hi> taking tired people to the Islands of the Blest!</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section25">
               <head>An American.</head>
               <p>The American Spirit speaks:</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>If the Led Striker call it a strike,<lb/>
  Or the papers call it a war,<lb/>
They know not much what I am like,<lb/>
  Nor what he is, my Avatar.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Through many roads, by me possessed,<lb/>
  He shambles forth in cosmic guise;<lb/>
He is the Jester and the Jest,<lb/>
  And he the Text himself applies.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>The Celt is in his heart and hand,<lb/>
  The Gaul is in his brain and nerve;<lb/>
Where, cosmopolitanly planned,<lb/>
  He guards the Redskin’s dry reserve.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>His easy unswept hearth he lends<lb/>
  From Labrador to Guadeloupe;<lb/>
Till, elbowed out by sloven friends,<lb/>
  He camps, at sufferance, on the stoop.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Calm-eyed he scoffs at sword and crown,<lb/>
  Or panic-blinded stabs and slays:<lb/>
Blatant he bids the world bow down,<lb/>
  Or cringing begs a crumb of praise;</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Or, sombre-drunk, at mine and mart,<lb/>
  He dubs his dreary brethren Kings.<lb/>
His hands are black with blood: his heart<lb/>
  Leaps, as a babe’s, at little things.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>But, through the shift of mood and mood,<lb/>
  Mine ancient humour saves him whole —<lb/>
The cynic devil in his blood<lb/>
  That bids him mock his hurrying soul;</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>That bids him flout the Law he makes,<lb/>
  That bids him make the Law he flouts,<lb/>
Till, dazed by many doubts, he wakes<lb/>
  The drumming guns that — have no doubts;</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>That checks him foolish hot and fond,<lb/>
  That chuckles through his deepest ire,<lb/>
That gilds the slough of his despond<lb/>
  But dims the goal of his desire;</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Inopportune, shrill-accented,<lb/>
  The acrid Asiatic mirth<lb/>
That leaves him careless ‘mid his dead,<lb/>
  The scandal of the elder earth.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>How shall he clear himself, how reach<lb/>
  Our bar or weighed defence prefer —<lb/>
A brother hedged with alien speech<lb/>
  And lacking all interpreter?</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Which knowledge vexes him a space;<lb/>
  But while reproof around him rings,<lb/>
He turns a keen untroubled face<lb/>
  Home, to the instant need of things.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Enslaved, illogical, elate,<lb/>
  He greets th’ embarrassed Gods, nor fears<lb/>
To shake the iron hand of Fate<lb/>
  Or match with Destiny for beers.</p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>Lo! imperturbable he rules,<lb/>
  Unkempt, disreputable, vast —<lb/>
And, in the teeth of all the schools<lb/>
  I— I shall save him at the last!</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section26">
               <head>The Mary Gloster.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>I’ve paid for your sickest fancies; I’ve humoured your crackedest</l>
                  <l>          whim —</l>
                  <l>Dick, it’s your daddy — dying: you’ve got to listen to him!</l>
                  <l>Good for a fortnight, am I? The doctor told you? He lied.</l>
                  <l>I shall go under by morning, and —— Put that nurse outside.</l>
                  <l>Never seen death yet, Dickie? Well, now is your time to learn,</l>
                  <l>And you’ll wish you held my record before it comes to your turn.</l>
                  <l>Not counting the Line and the Foundry, the yards and the village, too,</l>
                  <l>I’ve made myself and a million; but I’m damned if I made you.</l>
                  <l>Master at two-and-twenty, and married at twenty three —</l>
                  <l>Ten thousand men on the pay-roll, and forty freighters at sea!</l>
                  <l>Fifty years between ’em, and every year of it fight,</l>
                  <l>And now I’m Sir Anthony Gloster, dying, a baronite:</l>
                  <l>For I lunched with His Royal ’Ighness — what was it the papers a-had?</l>
                  <l>“Not least of our merchant-princes.” Dickie, that’s me, your dad!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">I</hi> didn’t begin with askings. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> took my job and I stuck;</l>
                  <l>And I took the chances they wouldn’t, an’ now they’re calling it luck.</l>
                  <l>Lord, what boats I’ve handled — rotten and leaky and old!</l>
                  <l>Ran ’em, or — opened the bilge-cock, precisely as I was told.</l>
                  <l>Grub that ’ud bind you crazy, and crews that ’ud turn you gray,</l>
                  <l>And a big fat lump of insurance to cover the risk on the way.</l>
                  <l>The others they duresn’t do it; they said they valued their life</l>
                  <l>(They’ve served me since as skippers). <hi rend="italic">I</hi> went, and I took my wife.</l>
                  <l>Over the world I drove ’em, married at twenty-three,</l>
                  <l>And your mother saving the money and making a man of me.</l>
                  <l>I was content to be master, but she said there was better behind;</l>
                  <l>She took the chances I wouldn’t, and I followed your mother blind.</l>
                  <l>She egged me to borrow the money, an’ she helped me clear the loan,</l>
                  <l>When we bought half shares in a cheap ’un and hoisted a flag of our</l>
                  <l>          own.</l>
                  <l>Patching and coaling on credit, and living the Lord knew how,</l>
                  <l>We started the Red Ox freighters — we’ve eight-and-thirty now.</l>
                  <l>And those were the days of clippers, and the freights were</l>
                  <l>          clipper-freights,</l>
                  <l>And we knew we were making our fortune, but she died in Macassar</l>
                  <l>          Straits —</l>
                  <l>By the Little Paternosters, as you come to the Union Bank —</l>
                  <l>And we dropped her in fourteen fathom; I pricked it off where she sank.</l>
                  <l>Owners we were, full owners, and the boat was christened for her,</l>
                  <l>And she died out there in childbed. My heart, how young we were!</l>
                  <l>So I went on a spree round Java and well-nigh ran her ashore,</l>
                  <l>But your mother came and warned me and I wouldn’t liquor no more.</l>
                  <l>Strict I stuck to my business, afraid to stop or I’d think,</l>
                  <l>Saving the money (she warned me), and letting the other men drink.</l>
                  <l>And I met McCullough in London (I’d saved five ’undred then),</l>
                  <l>And ‘tween us we started the Foundry — three forges and twenty men:</l>
                  <l>Cheap repairs for the cheap ’uns. It paid, and the business grew,</l>
                  <l>For I bought me a steam-lathe patent, and that was a gold mine too.</l>
                  <l>“Cheaper to build ’em than buy ’em,” <hi rend="italic">I</hi> said, but McCullough he shied,</l>
                  <l>And we wasted a year in talking before we moved to the Clyde.</l>
                  <l>And the Lines were all beginning, and we all of us started fair,</l>
                  <l>Building our engines like houses and staying the boilers square.</l>
                  <l>But McCullough ’e wanted cabins with marble and maple and all,</l>
                  <l>And Brussels and Utrecht velvet, and baths and a Social Hall,</l>
                  <l>And pipes for closets all over, and cutting the frames too light.</l>
                  <l>But McCullough he died in the Sixties, and —— Well, I’m dying</l>
                  <l>          to-night....</l>
                  <l>I knew — <hi rend="italic">I</hi> knew what was coming, when we bid on the <hi rend="italic">Byfleet’s</hi> keel.</l>
                  <l>They piddled and piffled with iron: I’d given my orders for steel.</l>
                  <l>Steel and the first expansions. It paid, I tell you, it paid,</l>
                  <l>When we came with our nine-knot freighters and collared the long-run</l>
                  <l>          trade.</l>
                  <l>And they asked me how I did it, and I gave ’em the Scripture text,</l>
                  <l>“You keep your light so shining a little in front o’ the next!”</l>
                  <l>They copied all they could follow, but they couldn’t copy my mind,</l>
                  <l>And I left ’em sweating and stealing a year and a half behind.</l>
                  <l>Then came the armour-contracts, but that was McCullough’s side;</l>
                  <l>He was always best in the Foundry, but better, perhaps, he died.</l>
                  <l>I went through his private papers; the notes was plainer than print;</l>
                  <l>And I’m no fool to finish if a man’ll give me a hint.</l>
                  <l>(I remember his widow was angry.) So I saw what the drawings meant,</l>
                  <l>And I started the six-inch rollers, and it paid me sixty per cent.</l>
                  <l>Sixty per cent <hi rend="italic">with</hi> failures, and more than twice we could do,</l>
                  <l>And a quarter-million to credit, and I saved it all for you.</l>
                  <l>I thought — it doesn’t matter — you seemed to favour your ma,</l>
                  <l>But you’re nearer forty than thirty, and I know the kind you are.</l>
                  <l>Harrer an’ Trinity College! I ought to ha’ sent you to sea —</l>
                  <l>But I stood you an education, an’ what have you done for me?</l>
                  <l>The things I knew was proper you wouldn’t thank me to give,</l>
                  <l>And the things I knew was rotten you said was the way to live;</l>
                  <l>For you muddled with books and pictures, an’ china an’ etchin’s an’</l>
                  <l>          fans,</l>
                  <l>And your rooms at college was beastly — more like a whore’s than a</l>
                  <l>          man’s —</l>
                  <l>Till you married that thin-flanked woman, as white and as stale as a</l>
                  <l>          bone,</l>
                  <l>And she gave you your social nonsense; but where’s that kid o’ your</l>
                  <l>          own?</l>
                  <l>I’ve seen your carriages blocking the half of the Cromwell Road,</l>
                  <l>But never the doctor’s brougham to help the missus unload.</l>
                  <l>(So there isn’t even a grandchild, an’ the Gloster family’s done.)</l>
                  <l>Not like your mother, she isn’t. <hi rend="italic">She</hi> carried her freight each run.</l>
                  <l>But they died, the pore little beggars! At sea she had ’em — they died.</l>
                  <l>Only you, an’ you stood it; you haven’t stood much beside —</l>
                  <l>Weak, a liar, and idle, and mean as a collier’s whelp</l>
                  <l>Nosing for scraps in the galley. No help — my son was no help!</l>
                  <l>So he gets three ’undred thousand, in trust and the interest paid.</l>
                  <l>I wouldn’t give it you, Dickie — you see, I made it in trade.</l>
                  <l>You’re saved from soiling your fingers, and if you have no child,</l>
                  <l>It all comes back to the business. Gad, won’t your wife be wild!</l>
                  <l>Calls and calls in her carriage, her ’andkerchief up to ’er eye:</l>
                  <l>“Daddy! dear daddy’s dyin’!” and doing her best to cry.</l>
                  <l>Grateful? Oh, yes, I’m grateful, but keep ’er away from here.</l>
                  <l>Your mother ’ud never ha’ stood ’er, and, anyhow, women are queer....</l>
                  <l>There’s women will say I’ve married a second time. Not quite!</l>
                  <l>But give pore Aggie a hundred, and tell her your lawyers’ll fight.</l>
                  <l>She was the best o’ the boiling — you’ll meet her before it ends;</l>
                  <l>I’m in for a row with the mother — I’ll leave you settle my friends:</l>
                  <l>For a man he must go with a woman, which women don’t understand —</l>
                  <l>Or the sort that say they can see it they aren’t the marrying brand.</l>
                  <l>But I wanted to speak o’ your mother that’s Lady Gloster still.</l>
                  <l>I’m going to up and see her, without it’s hurting the will.</l>
                  <l>Here! Take your hand off the bell-pull. Five thousand’s waiting for</l>
                  <l>          you,</l>
                  <l>If you’ll only listen a minute, and do as I bid you do.</l>
                  <l>They’ll try to prove me a loony, and, if you bungle, they can;</l>
                  <l>And I’ve only you to trust to! (O God, why ain’t he a man?)</l>
                  <l>There’s some waste money on marbles, the same as McCullough tried —</l>
                  <l>Marbles and mausoleums — but I call that sinful pride.</l>
                  <l>There’s some ship bodies for burial — we’ve carried ’em, soldered and</l>
                  <l>          packed;</l>
                  <l>Down in their wills they wrote it, and nobody called <hi rend="italic">them</hi> cracked.</l>
                  <l>But me — I’ve too much money, and people might.... All my fault:</l>
                  <l>It come o’ hoping for grandsons and buying that Wokin’ vault.</l>
                  <l>I’m sick o’ the ’ole dam’ business; I’m going back where I came.</l>
                  <l>Dick, you’re the son o’ my body, and you’ll take charge o’ the same!</l>
                  <l>I’m going to lie by your mother, ten thousand mile away,</l>
                  <l>And they’ll want to send me to Woking; and that’s where you’ll earn</l>
                  <l>          your pay.</l>
                  <l>I’ve thought it out on the quiet, the same as it ought to be done —</l>
                  <l>Quiet, and decent, and proper — an’ here’s your orders, my son.</l>
                  <l>You know the Line? You don’t, though. You write to the Board, and tell</l>
                  <l>Your father’s death has upset you an’ you’re goin’ to cruise for a</l>
                  <l>          spell,</l>
                  <l>An’ you’d like the Mary Gloster — I’ve held her ready for this —</l>
                  <l>They’ll put her in working order an’ you’ll take her out as she is.</l>
                  <l>Yes, it was money idle when I patched her and put her aside</l>
                  <l>(Thank God, I can pay for my fancies!)— the boat where your mother</l>
                  <l>          died,</l>
                  <l>By the Little Paternosters, as you come to the Union Bank,</l>
                  <l>We dropped her — I think I told you — and I pricked it off where she</l>
                  <l>          sank.</l>
                  <l>[Tiny she looked on the grating — that oily, treacly sea —]</l>
                  <l>Hundred and eighteen East, remember, and South just three.</l>
                  <l>Easy bearings to carry — three South — three to the dot;</l>
                  <l>But I gave McAndrews a copy in case of dying — or not.</l>
                  <l>And so you’ll write to McAndrews, he’s Chief of the Maori Line;</l>
                  <l>They’ll give him leave, if you ask ’em and say it’s business o’ mine.</l>
                  <l>I built three boats for the Maoris, an’ very well pleased they were,</l>
                  <l>An’ I’ve known Mac since the Fifties, and Mac knew me — and her.</l>
                  <l>After the first stroke warned me I sent him the money to keep</l>
                  <l>Against the time you’d claim it, committin’ your dad to the deep;</l>
                  <l>For you are the son o’ my body, and Mac was my oldest friend,</l>
                  <l>I’ve never asked ’im to dinner, but he’ll see it out to the end.</l>
                  <l>Stiff-necked Glasgow beggar, I’ve heard he’s prayed for my soul,</l>
                  <l>But he couldn’t lie if you paid him, and he’d starve before he stole.</l>
                  <l>He’ll take the Mary in ballast — you’ll find her a lively ship;</l>
                  <l>And you’ll take Sir Anthony Gloster, that goes on his wedding-trip,</l>
                  <l>Lashed in our old deck-cabin with all three port-holes wide,</l>
                  <l>The kick o’ the screw beneath him and the round blue seas outside!</l>
                  <l>Sir Anthony Gloster’s carriage — our ’ouse-flag flyin’ free —</l>
                  <l>Ten thousand men on the pay-roll and forty freighters at sea!</l>
                  <l>He made himself and a million, but this world is a fleetin’ show,</l>
                  <l>And he’ll go to the wife of ’is bosom the same as he ought to go.</l>
                  <l>By the heel of the Paternosters — there isn’t a chance to mistake —</l>
                  <l>And Mac’ll pay you the money as soon as the bubbles break!</l>
                  <l>Five thousand for six weeks’ cruising, the stanchest freighter afloat,</l>
                  <l>And Mac he’ll give you your bonus the minute I’m out o’ the boat!</l>
                  <l>He’ll take you round to Macassar, and you’ll come back alone;</l>
                  <l>He knows what I want o’ the Mary.... I’ll do what I please with my own.</l>
                  <l>Your mother ’ud call it wasteful, but I’ve seven-and-thirty more;</l>
                  <l>I’ll come in my private carriage and bid it wait at the door....</l>
                  <l>For my son ’e was never a credit: ’e muddled with books and art,</l>
                  <l>And ’e lived on Sir Anthony’s money and ’e broke Sir Anthony’s heart.</l>
                  <l>There isn’t even a grandchild, and the Gloster family’s done —</l>
                  <l>The only one you left me, O mother, the only one!</l>
                  <l>Harrer an’ Trinity College! Me slavin’ early an’ late,</l>
                  <l>An’ he thinks I’m dyin’ crazy, and you’re in Macassar Strait!</l>
                  <l>Flesh o’ my flesh, my dearie, for ever an’ ever amen,</l>
                  <l>That first stroke come for a warning; I ought to ha’ gone to you then,</l>
                  <l>But — cheap repairs for a cheap ’un-the doctors said I’d do:</l>
                  <l>Mary, why didn’t <hi rend="italic">you</hi> warn me? I’ve allus heeded to you,</l>
                  <l>Excep’— I know — about women; but you are a spirit now;</l>
                  <l>An’, wife, they was only women, and I was a man. That’s how.</l>
                  <l>An’ a man ’e must go with a woman, as you could not understand;</l>
                  <l>But I never talked ’em secrets. I paid ’em out o’ hand.</l>
                  <l>Thank Gawd, I can pay for my fancies! Now what’s five thousand to me,</l>
                  <l>For a berth off the Paternosters in the haven where I would be?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">I</hi> believe in the Resurrection, if I read my Bible plain,</l>
                  <l>But I wouldn’t trust ’em at Wokin’; we’re safer at sea again.</l>
                  <l>For the heart it shall go with the treasure — go down to the sea in</l>
                  <l>          ships.</l>
                  <l>I’m sick of the hired women — I’ll kiss my girl on her lips!</l>
                  <l>I’ll be content with my fountain, I’ll drink from my own well,</l>
                  <l>And the wife of my youth shall charm me — an’ the rest can go to Hell!</l>
                  <l>(Dickie, <hi rend="italic">he</hi> will, that’s certain.) I’ll lie in our standin’-bed,</l>
                  <l>An’ Mac’ll take her in ballast — and she trims best by the head....</l>
                  <l>Down by the head an’ sinkin’. Her fires are drawn and cold,</l>
                  <l>And the water’s splashin’ hollow on the skin of the empty hold —</l>
                  <l>Churning an’ choking and chuckling, quiet and scummy and dark —</l>
                  <l>Full to her lower hatches and risin’ steady. Hark!</l>
                  <l>That was the after-bulkhead ... she’s flooded from stem to stern....</l>
                  <l>Never seen death yet, Dickie?... Well, now is your time to learn!</l>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section27">
               <head>Sestina of the Tramp-Royal.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>Speakin’ in general, I ’ave tried ’em all,</l>
                  <l>The ’appy roads that take you o’er the world.</l>
                  <l>Speakin’ in general, I ’ave found them good</l>
                  <l>For such as cannot use one bed too long,</l>
                  <l>But must get ’ence, the same as I ’ave done,</l>
                  <l>An’ go observin’ matters till they die.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>What do it matter where or ’ow we die,</l>
                  <l>So long as we’ve our ’ealth to watch it all —</l>
                  <l>The different ways that different things are done,</l>
                  <l>An’ men an’ women lovin’ in this world —</l>
                  <l>Takin’ our chances as they come along,</l>
                  <l>An’ when they ain’t, pretendin’ they are good?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In cash or credit — no, it ain’t no good;</l>
                  <l>You ’ave to ’ave the ’abit or you’d die,</l>
                  <l>Unless you lived your life but one day long,</l>
                  <l>Nor didn’t prophesy nor fret at all,</l>
                  <l>But drew your tucker some’ow from the world,</l>
                  <l>An’ never bothered what you might ha’ done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, Gawd, what things are they I ’aven’t done?</l>
                  <l>I’ve turned my ’and to most, an’ turned it good,</l>
                  <l>In various situations round the world —</l>
                  <l>For ’im that doth not work must surely die;</l>
                  <l>But that’s no reason man should labour all</l>
                  <l>’Is life on one same shift; life’s none so long.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therfore, from job to job I’ve moved along.</l>
                  <l>Pay couldn’t ’old me when my time was done,</l>
                  <l>For something in my ’ead upset me all,</l>
                  <l>Till I ’ad dropped whatever ’twas for good,</l>
                  <l>An’, out at sea, be’eld the dock-lights die,</l>
                  <l>An’ met my mate — the wind that tramps the world.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It’s like a book, I think, this bloomin’ world,</l>
                  <l>Which you can read and care for just so long,</l>
                  <l>But presently you feel that you will die</l>
                  <l>Unless you get the page you’re readin’ done,</l>
                  <l>An’ turn another — likely not so good;</l>
                  <l>But what you’re after is to turn ’em all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gawd bless this world! Whatever she ’ath done —</l>
                  <l>Excep’ when awful long — I’ve found it good.</l>
                  <l>So write, before I die, “’E liked it all!”</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Barrack-Room Ballads.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">When ’Omer smote ’is bloomin’ lyre,<lb/>
  He’d ’eard men sing by land an’ sea;<lb/>
An’ what he thought ’e might require,<lb/>
  ’E went an’ took — the same as me!</hi>
               </l>
               <l/>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">The market-girls an’ fishermen,<lb/>
  The shepherds an’ the sailors, too,<lb/>
They ’eard old songs turn up again,<lb/>
  But kep’ it quiet — same as you!</hi>
               </l>
               <l/>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">They knew ’e stole; ’e knew they knowed.<lb/>
  They didn’t tell, nor make a fuss,<lb/>
But winked at ’Omer down the road,<lb/>
  An’ ’e winked back — the same as us!</hi>
               </l>
               <l/>
            </lg>
            <div xml:id="section29">
               <head>“Back to the Army Again.”</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>I’m ’ere in a ticky ulster an’ a broken billycock ’at,</l>
                  <l>A-layin’ on to the sergeant I don’t know a gun from a bat;</l>
                  <l>My shirt’s doin’ duty for jacket, my sock’s stickin’ out o’ my boots,</l>
                  <l>An’ I’m learnin’ the damned old goose-step along o’ the new recruits!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again.</l>
                  <l>  Don’t look so ’ard, for I ’aven’t no card,</l>
                  <l>    I’m back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I done my six years’ service. ’Er Majesty sez: “Good day —</l>
                  <l>You’ll please to come when you’re rung for, an’ ’ere’s your ’ole back</l>
                  <l>          pay;</l>
                  <l>An’ fourpence a day for baccy — an’ bloomin’ gen’rous, too;</l>
                  <l>An’ now you can make your fortune — the same as your orf’cers do.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again;</l>
                  <l>  ’Ow did I learn to do right-about turn?</l>
                  <l>    I’m back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A man o’ four-an’-twenty that ’asn’t learned of a trade —</l>
                  <l>Beside “Reserve” agin’ him —’e’d better be never made.</l>
                  <l>I tried my luck for a quarter, an’ that was enough for me,</l>
                  <l>An’ I thought of ’Er Majesty’s barricks, an’ I thought I’d go an’ see.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again;</l>
                  <l>  ‘Tisn’t my fault if I dress when I ’alt —</l>
                  <l>    I’m back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The sergeant arst no questions, but ’e winked the other eye,</l>
                  <l>E’ sez to me, “‘Shun!” an’ I shunted, the same as in days gone by;</l>
                  <l>For ’e saw the set o’ my shoulders, an’ I couldn’t ’elp ’oldin’</l>
                  <l>          straight</l>
                  <l>When me an’ the other rookies come under the barrick gate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again;</l>
                  <l>  ’Oo would ha’ thought I could carry an’ port?</l>
                  <l>    I’m back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I took my bath, an’ I wallered — for, Gawd, I needed it so!</l>
                  <l>I smelt the smell o’ the barricks, I ’eard the bugles go.</l>
                  <l>I ’eard the feet on the gravel — the feet o’ the men what drill —</l>
                  <l>An’ I sez to my flutterin’ ’eartstrings, I sez to ’em, “Peace, be</l>
                  <l>          still!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again;</l>
                  <l>  ’Oo said I knew when the Jumner was due?</l>
                  <l>    I’m back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I carried my slops to the tailor; I sez to ’im, “None o’ your lip!</l>
                  <l>You tight ’em over the shoulders, an’ loose ’em over the ’ip,</l>
                  <l>For the set o’ the tunic’s ’orrid.” An’ ’e sez to me, “Strike me dead,</l>
                  <l>But I thought you was used to the business!” an’ so ’e done what I</l>
                  <l>          said.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again.</l>
                  <l>  Rather too free with my fancies? Wot — me?</l>
                  <l>    I’m back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Next week I’ll ’ave ’em fitted; I’ll buy me a walkin’ cane;</l>
                  <l>They’ll let me free o’ the barricks to walk on the Hoe again</l>
                  <l>In the name o’ William Parsons, that used to be Edward Clay,</l>
                  <l>An’— any pore beggar that wants it can draw my fourpence a day!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  Back to the Army again, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Back to the Army again:</l>
                  <l>  Out o’ the cold an’ the rain, sergeant,</l>
                  <l>    Out o’ the cold an’ the rain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>                        ’Oo’s there?</l>
                  <l>  A man that’s too good to be lost you,</l>
                  <l>    A man that is ’andled an’ made —</l>
                  <l>  A man that will pay what ’e cost you</l>
                  <l>    In learnin’ the others their trade — parade!</l>
                  <l>  You’re droppin’ the pick o’ the Army</l>
                  <l>    Because you don’t ’elp ’em remain,</l>
                  <l>  But drives ’em to cheat to get out o’ the street</l>
                  <l>    An’ back to the Army again!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section30">
               <head>“Birds of Prey” March.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>March! The mud is cakin’ good about our trousies.</l>
                  <l>  Front!— eyes front, an’ watch the Colour-casin’s drip.</l>
                  <l>Front! The faces of the women in the ’ouses</l>
                  <l>  Ain’t the kind o’ things to take aboard the ship.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Cheer! An’ we’ll never march to victory.<lb/>
Cheer! An’ we’ll never live to ’ear the cannon roar!<lb/>
        The Large Birds o’ Prey<lb/>
        They will carry us away,<lb/>
An’ you’ll never see your soldiers any more!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wheel! Oh, keep your touch; we’re goin’ round a corner.</l>
                  <l>  Time!— mark time, an’ let the men be’ind us close.</l>
                  <l>Lord! the transport’s full, an’ ’alf our lot not on ’er —</l>
                  <l>  Cheer, O cheer! We’re going off where no one knows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>March! The Devil’s none so black as ’e is painted!</l>
                  <l>  Cheer! We’ll ’ave some fun before we’re put away.</l>
                  <l>’Alt, an’ ’and ’er out — a woman’s gone and fainted!</l>
                  <l>  Cheer! Get on — Gawd ’elp the married men today!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hoi! Come up, you ’ungry beggars, to yer sorrow.</l>
                  <l>  (’Ear them say they want their tea, an’ want it quick!)</l>
                  <l>You won’t have no mind for slingers, not tomorrow —</l>
                  <l>  No; you’ll put the ‘tween-decks stove out, bein’ sick!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’Alt! The married kit ’as all to go before us!</l>
                  <l>  ‘Course it’s blocked the bloomin’ gangway up again!</l>
                  <l>Cheer, O cheer the ’Orse Guards watchin’ tender o’er us,</l>
                  <l>  Keepin’ us since eight this mornin’ in the rain!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stuck in ’eavy marchin’-order, sopped and wringin’—</l>
                  <l>  Sick, before our time to watch ’er ’eave an’ fall,</l>
                  <l>’Ere’s your ’appy ’ome at last, an’ stop your singin’.</l>
                  <l>  ’Alt! Fall in along the troop-deck! Silence all!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Cheer! For we’ll never live to see no bloomin’ victory!<lb/>
  Cheer! An’ we’ll never live to ’ear the cannon roar! (One cheer<lb/>
          more!)<lb/>
        The jackal an’ the kite<lb/>
        ’Ave an ’ealthy appetite,<lb/>
An’ you’ll never see your soldiers any more! (’Ip! Urroar!)<lb/>
        The eagle an’ the crow<lb/>
        They are waitin’ ever so,<lb/>
An’ you’ll never see your soldiers any more! (’Ip! Urroar!)<lb/>
        Yes, the Large Birds o’ Prey<lb/>
        They will carry us away,<lb/>
An’ you’ll never see your soldiers any more!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section31">
               <head>“Soldier an’ Sailor Too.”</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>As I was spittin’ into the Ditch aboard o’ the Crocodile,</l>
                  <l>I seed a man on a man-o’-war got up in the Reg’lars’ style.</l>
                  <l>’E was scrapin’ the paint from off of ’er plates, an’ I sez to ’im,</l>
                  <l>          “’Oo are you?”</l>
                  <l>Sez ’e, “I’m a Jolly —’Er Majesty’s Jolly — soldier an’ sailor too!”</l>
                  <l>Now ’is work begins at Gawd knows when, and ’is work is never through;</l>
                  <l>’E isn’t one o’ the reg’lar Line, nor ’e isn’t one of the crew.</l>
                  <l>’E’s a kind of a giddy harumfrodite — soldier an’ sailor too!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ after I met ’im all over the world, a-doin’ all kinds of things,</l>
                  <l>Like landin’ ’isself with a Gatlin’ gun to talk to them ’eathen kings;</l>
                  <l>’E sleeps in an ’ammick instead of a cot, an’ ’e drills with the deck</l>
                  <l>          on a slew,</l>
                  <l>An’ ’e sweats like a Jolly —’Er Majesty’s Jolly — soldier an’ sailor</l>
                  <l>          too!</l>
                  <l>For there isn’t a job on the top o’ the earth the beggar don’t know,</l>
                  <l>          nor do.</l>
                  <l>You can leave ’im at night on a bald man’s ’ead, to paddle ’is own</l>
                  <l>          canoe;</l>
                  <l>’E’s a sort of a bloomin’ cosmopolouse — soldier an’ sailor too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’ve fought ’em on trooper, we’ve fought ’em in dock, an’ drunk with</l>
                  <l>          ’em in betweens,</l>
                  <l>When they called us the seasick scull’ry maids, an’ we called ’em the</l>
                  <l>          Ass Marines;</l>
                  <l>But, when we was down for a double fatigue, from Woolwich to</l>
                  <l>          Bernardmyo,</l>
                  <l>We sent for the Jollies —’Er Majesty’s Jollies — soldier an’ sailor too!</l>
                  <l>They think for ’emselves, an’ they steal for ’emselves, and they never</l>
                  <l>          ask what’s to do,</l>
                  <l>But they’re camped an’ fed an’ they’re up an’ fed before our bugle’s</l>
                  <l>          blew.</l>
                  <l>Ho! they ain’t no limpin’ procrastitutes — soldier an’ sailor too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You may say we are fond of an ’arness-cut, or ’ootin’ in barrick-yards,</l>
                  <l>Or startin’ a Board School mutiny along o’ the Onion Guards;</l>
                  <l>But once in a while we can finish in style for the ends of the earth</l>
                  <l>          to view,</l>
                  <l>The same as the Jollies —’er Majesty’s Jollies — soldier an’ sailor too!</l>
                  <l>They come of our lot, they was brothers to us; they was beggars we’d</l>
                  <l>          met an’ knew;</l>
                  <l>Yes, barrin’ an inch in the chest an’ the arms, they was doubles o’ me</l>
                  <l>          an’ you;</l>
                  <l>For they weren’t no special chrysanthemums — soldier an’ sailor too!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To take your chance in the thick of a rush, with firing all about,</l>
                  <l>Is nothing so bad when you’ve cover to ’and, an’ leave an’ likin’ to</l>
                  <l>          shout;</l>
                  <l>But to stand an’ be still to the <hi rend="italic">Birken’ead</hi> drill is a damn tough</l>
                  <l>          bullet to chew,</l>
                  <l>An’ they done it, the Jollies —’Er Majesty’s Jollies — soldier an’</l>
                  <l>          sailor too!</l>
                  <l>Their work was done when it ’adn’t begun; they was younger nor me an’</l>
                  <l>          you;</l>
                  <l>Their choice it was plain between drownin’ in ’eaps an’ bein’ mashed</l>
                  <l>          by the screw,</l>
                  <l>So they stood an’ was still to the <hi rend="italic">Birken’ead</hi> drill, soldier an’</l>
                  <l>          sailor too!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’re most of us liars, we’re ’arf of us thieves, an’ the rest are as</l>
                  <l>          rank as can be,</l>
                  <l>But once in a while we can finish in style (which I ’ope it won’t</l>
                  <l>          ’appen to me).</l>
                  <l>But it makes you think better o’ you an’ your friends, an’ the work</l>
                  <l>          you may ’ave to do,</l>
                  <l>When you think o’ the sinkin’ <hi rend="italic">Victorier’s</hi> Jollies — soldier an’</l>
                  <l>          sailor too!</l>
                  <l>Now there isn’t no room for to say ye don’t know — they ’ave proved it</l>
                  <l>          plain and true —</l>
                  <l>That whether it’s Widow, or whether it’s ship, Victorier’s work is to</l>
                  <l>          do,</l>
                  <l>An’ they done it, the Jollies —’Er Majesty’s Jollies — soldier an’</l>
                  <l>          sailor too!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section32">
               <head>Sappers.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>When the Waters were dried an’ the Earth did appear</l>
                  <l>    (“It’s all one,” says the Sapper),</l>
                  <l>The Lord He created the Engineer,</l>
                  <l>    Her Majesty’s Royal Engineer,</l>
                  <l>    With the rank and pay of a Sapper!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>When the Flood come along for an extra monsoon,</l>
                  <l>’Twas Noah constructed the first pontoon</l>
                  <l>    To the plans of Her Majesty’s, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But after “fatigue” in the wet an’ the sun,</l>
                  <l>Old Noah got drunk, which he wouldn’t ha’ done</l>
                  <l>    If he’d trained with, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When the Tower o’ Babel had mixed up men’s <hi rend="italic">bat</hi>,</l>
                  <l>Some clever civilian was managing that,</l>
                  <l>    An’ none of, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When the Jews had a fight at the foot of an ’ill,</l>
                  <l>Young Joshua ordered the sun to stand still,</l>
                  <l>    For he was a Captain of Engineers, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When the Children of Israel made bricks without straw,</l>
                  <l>They were learnin’ the regular work of our Corps,</l>
                  <l>    The work of, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For ever since then, if a war they would wage,</l>
                  <l>Behold us a-shinin’ on history’s page —</l>
                  <l>    First page for, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We lay down their sidings an’ help ’em entrain,</l>
                  <l>An’ we sweep up their mess through the bloomin’ campaign,</l>
                  <l>    In the style of, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They send us in front with a fuse an’ a mine</l>
                  <l>To blow up the gates that are rushed by the Line,</l>
                  <l>    But bent by, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They send us behind with a pick an’ a spade,</l>
                  <l>To dig for the guns of a bullock-brigade</l>
                  <l>    Which has asked for, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We work under escort in trousies an’ shirt,</l>
                  <l>An’ the heathen they plug us tail-up in the dirt,</l>
                  <l>    Annoying, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We blast out the rock an’ we shovel the mud,</l>
                  <l>We make ’em good roads an’— they roll down the <hi rend="italic">khud</hi>,</l>
                  <l>    Reporting, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We make ’em their bridges, their wells, an’ their huts,</l>
                  <l>An’ the telegraph-wire the enemy cuts,</l>
                  <l>    An’ it’s blamed on, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ when we return an’ from war we would cease,</l>
                  <l>They grudge us adornin’ the billets of peace,</l>
                  <l>    Which are kept for, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We build ’em nice barricks — they swear they are bad,</l>
                  <l>That our Colonels are Methodist, married or mad,</l>
                  <l>    Insultin’, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They haven’t no manners nor gratitude too,</l>
                  <l>For the more that we help ’em the less will they do,</l>
                  <l>    But mock at, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now the Line’s but a man with a gun in his hand,</l>
                  <l>An’ Cavalry’s only what horses can stand,</l>
                  <l>    When helped by, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Artillery moves by the leave o’ the ground,</l>
                  <l>But <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are the men that do something all round,</l>
                  <l>    For <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are, etc.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I have stated it plain, an’ my argument’s thus,</l>
                  <l>    (“It’s all one,” says the Sapper),</l>
                  <l>There’s only one Corps which is perfect — that’s us;</l>
                  <l>    An’ they call us Her Majesty’s Engineers,</l>
                  <l>    Her Majesty’s Royal Engineers,</l>
                  <l>    With the rank and pay of a Sapper!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section33">
               <head>That Day.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>It got beyond all orders an’ it got beyond all ’ope;</l>
                  <l>  It got to shammin’ wounded an’ retirin’ from the ’alt.</l>
                  <l>’Ole companies was lookin’ for the nearest road to slope;</l>
                  <l>  It were just a bloomin’ knock-out — an’ our fault!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Now there ain’t no chorus ’ere to give,<lb/>
    Nor there ain’t no band to play;<lb/>
  An’ I wish I was dead ‘fore I done what I did<lb/>
    Or seen what I seed that day!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>We was sick o’ bein’ punished, an’ we let ’em know it, too;</l>
                  <l>  An’ a company-commander up an’ ’it us with a sword,</l>
                  <l>An’ some one shouted “’Ook it!” an’ it come to <hi rend="italic">sove-ki-poo</hi>,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we chucked our rifles from us — oh, my Gawd!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There was thirty dead an’ wounded on the ground we wouldn’t keep —</l>
                  <l>  No, there wasn’t more than twenty when the front begun to go;</l>
                  <l>But, Christ! along the line o’ flight they cut us up like sheep,</l>
                  <l>  An’ that was all we gained by doin’ so.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ’eard the knives be’ind me, but I dursn’t face my man,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I don’t know where I went to, ‘cause I didn’t ’alt to see,</l>
                  <l>Till I ’eard a beggar squealin’ out for quarter as ’e ran,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I thought I knew the voice an’— it was me!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We was ’idin’ under bedsteads more than ’arf a march away;</l>
                  <l>  We was lyin’ up like rabbits all about the country side;</l>
                  <l>An’ the major cursed ’is Maker ‘cause ’e lived to see that day,</l>
                  <l>  An’ the colonel broke ’is sword acrost, an’ cried.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We was rotten ‘fore we started — we was never disciplined;</l>
                  <l>  We made it out a favour if an order was obeyed;</l>
                  <l>Yes, every little drummer ’ad ’is rights an’ wrongs to mind,</l>
                  <l>  So we had to pay for teachin’— an’ we paid!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The papers ’id it ’andsome, but you know the Army knows;</l>
                  <l>  We was put to groomin’ camels till the regiments withdrew,</l>
                  <l>An’ they give us each a medal for subduin’ England’s foes,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I ’ope you like my song — because it’s true!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">An’ there ain’t no chorus ’ere to give,<lb/>
    Nor there ain’t no band to play;<lb/>
  But I wish I was dead ‘fore I done what I did<lb/>
    Or seen what I seed that day!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section34">
               <head>“The Men That Fought at Minden.”</head>
               <byline>A SONG OF INSTRUCTION.</byline>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they was rookies in their time —</l>
                  <l>  So was them that fought at Waterloo!</l>
                  <l>All the ’ole command, yuss, from Minden to Maiwand,</l>
                  <l>  They was once dam’ sweeps like you!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Then do not be discouraged, ’Eaven is your ’elper,<lb/>
    We’ll learn you not to forget;<lb/>
  An’ you mustn’t swear an’ curse, or you’ll only catch it worse,<lb/>
    For we’ll make you soldiers yet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they ’ad stocks beneath their chins,</l>
                  <l>  Six inch ’igh an’ more;</l>
                  <l>But fatigue it was their pride, and they <hi rend="italic">would</hi> not be denied</l>
                  <l>  To clean the cook-’ouse floor.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they ’ad anarchistic bombs</l>
                  <l>  Served to ’em by name of ’and-grenades;</l>
                  <l>But they got it in the eye (same as you will by an’ by)</l>
                  <l>  When they clubbed their field-parades.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they ’ad buttons up an’ down,</l>
                  <l>  Two-an’-twenty dozen of ’em told;</l>
                  <l>But they didn’t grouse an’ shirk at an hour’s extry work,</l>
                  <l>  They kept ’em bright as gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they was armed with musketoons,</l>
                  <l>  Also, they was drilled by ’alberdiers;</l>
                  <l>I don’t know what they were, but the sergeants took good care</l>
                  <l>  They washed be’ind their ears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they ’ad ever cash in ’and</l>
                  <l>  Which they did not bank nor save,</l>
                  <l>But spent it gay an’ free on their betters — such as me —</l>
                  <l>  For the good advice I gave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they was civil — yuss, they was —</l>
                  <l>  Never didn’t talk o’ rights an’ wrongs,</l>
                  <l>But they got it with the toe (same as you will get it — so!)—</l>
                  <l>  For interrupting songs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The men that fought at Minden, they was several other things</l>
                  <l>  Which I don’t remember clear;</l>
                  <l>But <hi rend="italic">that’s</hi> the reason why, now the six-year men are dry,</l>
                  <l>  The rooks will stand the beer!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Then do not be discouraged, ’Eaven is your ’elper,<lb/>
    We’ll learn you not to forget;<lb/>
  An’ you mustn’t swear an’ curse, or you’ll only catch it worse,<lb/>
    And we’ll make you soldiers yet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Soldiers yet, if you’ve got it in you —<lb/>
    All for the sake o’ the Core;<lb/>
  Soldiers yet, if we ’ave to skin you —<lb/>
    Run an’ get the beer, Johnny Raw — Johnny Raw!<lb/>
    Ho! run an’ get the beer, Johnny Raw!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section35">
               <head>Cholera Camp.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>We’ve got the cholerer in camp — it’s worse than forty fights;</l>
                  <l>We’re dyin’ in the wilderness the same as Isrulites!</l>
                  <l>It’s before us, an’ be’ind us, an’ we cannot get away,</l>
                  <l>An’ the doctor’s just reported we’ve ten more today!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Oh, strike your camp an’ go, the bugle’s callin’,<lb/>
    The Rains are fallin’—<lb/>
  The dead are bushed an’ stoned to keep ’em safe below;<lb/>
  The Band’s a-doin’ all she knows to cheer us;<lb/>
  The chaplain’s gone and prayed to Gawd to ’ear us —<lb/>
    To ’ear us —<lb/>
  O Lord, for it’s a-killing of us so!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since August, when it started, it’s been sticking to our tail,</l>
                  <l>Tho’ they’ve ’ad us out by marches an’ they’ve ’ad us back by rail;</l>
                  <l>But it runs as fast as troop-trains, an’ we can not get away;</l>
                  <l>An’ the sick-list to the Colonel makes ten more today.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There ain’t no fun in women nor there ain’t no bite to drink;</l>
                  <l>It’s much too wet for shootin’, we can only march and think;</l>
                  <l>An’ at evenin’, down the <hi rend="italic">nullahs</hi>, we can ’ear the jackals say,</l>
                  <l>“Get up, you rotten beggars, you’ve ten more today!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Twould make a monkey cough to see our way o’ doin’ things —</l>
                  <l>Lieutenants takin’ companies an’ captains takin’ wings,</l>
                  <l>An’ Lances actin’ Sergeants — eight file to obey —</l>
                  <l>For we’ve lots o’ quick promotion on ten deaths a day!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Colonel’s white an’ twitterly —’e gets no sleep nor food,</l>
                  <l>But mucks about in ’orspital where nothing does no good.</l>
                  <l>’E sends us ’eaps o’ comforts, all bought from ’is pay —</l>
                  <l>But there aren’t much comfort ’andy on ten deaths a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Chaplain’s got a banjo, an’ a skinny mule ’e rides,</l>
                  <l>An’ the stuff ’e says an’ sings us, Lord, it makes us split our sides!</l>
                  <l>With ’is black coat-tails a-bobbin’ to <hi rend="italic">Ta-ra-ra Boom-der-ay!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>’E’s the proper kind o’ <hi rend="italic">padre</hi> for ten deaths a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ Father Victor ’elps ’im with our Roman Catholicks —</l>
                  <l>He knows an ’eap of Irish songs an’ rummy conjurin’ tricks;</l>
                  <l>An’ the two they works together when it comes to play or pray;</l>
                  <l>So we keep the ball a-rollin’ on ten deaths a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’ve got the cholerer in camp — we’ve got it ’ot an’ sweet;</l>
                  <l>It ain’t no Christmas dinner, but it’s ’elped an’ we must eat.</l>
                  <l>We’ve gone beyond the funkin’, ‘cause we’ve found it doesn’t pay,</l>
                  <l>An’ we’re rockin’ round the Districk on ten deaths a day!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Then strike your camp an’ go, the Rains are fallin’,<lb/>
    The bugle’s callin’!<lb/>
  The dead are bushed an’ stoned to keep ’em safe below!<lb/>
  An’ them that do not like it they can lump it,<lb/>
  An’ them that can not stand it they can jump it;<lb/>
  We’ve got to die somewhere — some way — some’ow —<lb/>
  We might as well begin to do it now!<lb/>
  Then, Number One, let down the tent-pole slow,<lb/>
  Knock out the pegs an’ ’old the corners — so!<lb/>
  Fold in the flies, furl up the ropes, an’ stow!<lb/>
  Oh, strike — oh, strike your camp an’ go!<lb/>
    (Gawd ’elp us!)</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section36">
               <head>The Ladies.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>I’ve taken my fun where I’ve found it;</l>
                  <l>  I’ve rogued an’ I’ve ranged in my time;</l>
                  <l>I’ve ’ad my pickin’ o’ sweet’earts,</l>
                  <l>  An’ four o’ the lot was prime.</l>
                  <l>One was an ’arf-caste widow,</l>
                  <l>  One was a woman at Prome,</l>
                  <l>One was the wife of a <hi rend="italic">jemadar-sais</hi>,<ref target="#fn1">
                        <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </l>
                  <l>  An’ one is a girl at ’ome.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Now I aren’t no ’and with the ladies,<lb/>
  For, takin’ ’em all along,<lb/>
You never can say till you’ve tried ’em,<lb/>
  An’ then you are like to be wrong.<lb/>
There’s times when you’ll think that you mightn’t,<lb/>
  There’s times when you’ll know that you might;<lb/>
But the things you will learn from the Yellow an’ Brown,<lb/>
  They’ll ’elp you an ’eap with the White!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I was a young un at ’Oogli,</l>
                  <l>  Shy as a girl to begin;</l>
                  <l>Aggie de Castrer she made me,</l>
                  <l>  An’ Aggie was clever as sin;</l>
                  <l>Older than me, but my first un-</l>
                  <l>  More like a mother she were —</l>
                  <l>Showed me the way to promotion an’ pay,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I learned about women from ’er.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then I was ordered to Burma,</l>
                  <l>  Actin’ in charge o’ Bazar,</l>
                  <l>An’ I got me a tiddy live ’eathen</l>
                  <l>  Through buyin’ supplies off ’er pa.</l>
                  <l>Funny an’ yellow an’ faithful —</l>
                  <l>  Doll in a teacup she were,</l>
                  <l>But we lived on the square, like a true-married pair,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I learned about women from ’er.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then we was shifted to Neemuch</l>
                  <l>  (Or I might ha’ been keepin’ ’er now),</l>
                  <l>An’ I took with a shiny she-devil,</l>
                  <l>  The wife of a nigger at Mhow;</l>
                  <l>Taught me the gipsy-folks’ <hi rend="italic">bolee</hi>;<ref target="#fn2">
                        <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </l>
                  <l>  Kind o’ volcano she were,</l>
                  <l>For she knifed me one night ‘cause I wished she was white,</l>
                  <l>  And I learned about women from ’er.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then I come ’ome in the trooper,</l>
                  <l>  ‘Long of a kid o’ sixteen —</l>
                  <l>Girl from a convent at Meerut,</l>
                  <l>  The straightest I ever ’ave seen.</l>
                  <l>Love at first sight was ’er trouble,</l>
                  <l>                     
                     <hi rend="italic">She</hi> didn’t know what it were;</l>
                  <l>An’ I wouldn’t do such, ‘cause I liked ’er too much,</l>
                  <l>  But — I learned about women from ’er!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I’ve taken my fun where I’ve found it,</l>
                  <l>  An’ now I must pay for my fun,</l>
                  <l>For the more you ’ave known o’ the others</l>
                  <l>  The less will you settle to one;</l>
                  <l>An’ the end of it’s sittin’ and thinkin’,</l>
                  <l>  An’ dreamin’ Hell-fires to see;</l>
                  <l>So be warned by my lot (which I know you will not),</l>
                  <l>  An’ learn about women from me!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">What did the colonel’s lady think?<lb/>
  Nobody never knew.<lb/>
Somebody asked the sergeant’s wife,<lb/>
  An’ she told ’em true.<lb/>
When you get to a man in the case,<lb/>
  They’re like as a row of pins —<lb/>
For the colonel’s lady an’ Judy O’Grady<lb/>
  Are sisters under their skins!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <note xml:id="fn1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Head-groom.</note>
               <note xml:id="fn2">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Slang.</note>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section37">
               <head>Bill ’Awkins.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>  “’As anybody seen Bill ’Awkins?”</l>
                  <l>    “Now ’ow in the devil would I know?”</l>
                  <l>“’E’s taken my girl out walkin’,</l>
                  <l>    An’ I’ve got to tell ’im so —</l>
                  <l>          Gawd — bless —’im!</l>
                  <l>    I’ve got to tell ’im so.”</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>  “D’yer know what ’e’s like, Bill ’Awkins?”</l>
                  <l>    “Now what in the devil would I care?”</l>
                  <l>“’E’s the livin’, breathin’ image of an organ-grinder’s monkey,</l>
                  <l>    With a pound of grease in ’is ’air —</l>
                  <l>          Gawd — bless —’im!</l>
                  <l>    An’ a pound o’ grease in ’is ’air.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  “An’ s’pose you met Bill ’Awkins,</l>
                  <l>    Now what in the devil ’ud ye do?”</l>
                  <l>“I’d open ’is cheek to ’is chin-strap buckle,</l>
                  <l>    An’ bung up ’is both eyes, too —</l>
                  <l>          Gawd — bless —’im!</l>
                  <l>    An’ bung up ’is both eyes, too!”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>  “Look ’ere, where ’e comes, Bill ’Awkins!</l>
                  <l>    Now what in the devil will you say?”</l>
                  <l>“It isn’t fit an’ proper to be fightin’ on a Sunday,</l>
                  <l>    So I’ll pass ’im the time o’ day —</l>
                  <l>          Gawd — bless —’im!</l>
                  <l>    I’ll pass ’im the time o’ day!”</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section38">
               <head>The Mother-Lodge.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>There was Rundle, Station Master,</l>
                  <l>  An’ Beazeley of the Rail,</l>
                  <l>An’ ’Ackman, Commissariat,</l>
                  <l>  An’ Donkin o’ the Jail;</l>
                  <l>An’ Blake, Conductor–Sargent,</l>
                  <l>  Our Master twice was ’e,</l>
                  <l>With ’im that kept the Europe shop,</l>
                  <l>  Old Framjee Eduljee.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Outside —“Sergeant! Sir! Salute! Salaam!”<lb/>
Inside —“Brother,” an’ it doesn’t do no ’arm.<lb/>
We met upon the Level an’ we parted on the Square,<lb/>
An’ I was Junior Deacon in my Mother Lodge out there!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We’d Bola Nath, Accountant,</l>
                  <l>  An’ Saul the Aden Jew,</l>
                  <l>An’ Din Mohammed, draughtsman</l>
                  <l>  Of the Survey Office too;</l>
                  <l>There was Babu Chuckerbutty,</l>
                  <l>  An’ Amir Singh the Sikh,</l>
                  <l>An’ Castro from the fittin’-sheds,</l>
                  <l>  The Roman Catholick!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We ’adn’t good regalia,</l>
                  <l>  An’ our Lodge was old an’ bare,</l>
                  <l>But we knew the Ancient Landmarks,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we kep’ ’em to a hair;</l>
                  <l>An’ lookin’ on it backwards</l>
                  <l>  It often strikes me thus,</l>
                  <l>There ain’t such things as infidels,</l>
                  <l>  Excep’, per’aps, it’s us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For monthly, after Labour,</l>
                  <l>  We’d all sit down and smoke</l>
                  <l>(We dursn’t give no banquits,</l>
                  <l>  Lest a Brother’s caste were broke),</l>
                  <l>An’ man on man got talkin’</l>
                  <l>  Religion an’ the rest,</l>
                  <l>An’ every man comparin’</l>
                  <l>  Of the God ’e knew the best.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So man on man got talkin’,</l>
                  <l>  An’ not a Brother stirred</l>
                  <l>Till mornin’ waked the parrots</l>
                  <l>  An’ that dam’ brain-fever-bird;</l>
                  <l>We’d say ’twas ’ighly curious,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we’d all ride ’ome to bed,</l>
                  <l>With Mo’ammed, God, an’ Shiva</l>
                  <l>  Changin’ pickets in our ’ead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Full oft on Guv’ment service</l>
                  <l>  This rovin’ foot ’ath pressed,</l>
                  <l>An’ bore fraternal greetin’s</l>
                  <l>  To the Lodges east an’ west,</l>
                  <l>Accordin’ as commanded</l>
                  <l>  From Kohat to Singapore,</l>
                  <l>But I wish that I might see them</l>
                  <l>  In my Mother Lodge once more!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I wish that I might see them,</l>
                  <l>  My Brethren black an’ brown,</l>
                  <l>With the trichies smellin’ pleasant</l>
                  <l>  An’ the <hi rend="italic">hog-darn</hi>
                     <ref target="#fn3">
                        <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                     </ref> passin’ down;</l>
                  <l>An’ the old khansamah<ref target="#fn4">
                        <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                     </ref> snorin’</l>
                  <l>  On the bottle-khana<ref target="#fn5">
                        <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                     </ref> floor,</l>
                  <l>Like a Master in good standing</l>
                  <l>  With my Mother Lodge once more!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Outside —“Sergeant! Sir! Salute! Salaam!”<lb/>
Inside —“Brother,” an’ it doesn’t do no ’arm.<lb/>
We met upon the Level an’ we parted on the Square,<lb/>
An’ I was Junior Deacon in my Mother Lodge out there!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <note xml:id="fn3">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Cigar-lighter.</note>
               <note xml:id="fn4">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Butler.</note>
               <note xml:id="fn5">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Pantry.</note>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section39">
               <head>“Follow Me ’Ome.”</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>    There was no one like ’im, ’Orse or Foot,</l>
                  <l>      Nor any o’ the Guns I knew;</l>
                  <l>An’ because it was so, why, o’ course ’e went an’ died,</l>
                  <l>      Which is just what the best men do.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">So it’s knock out your pipes an’ follow me!<lb/>
  An’ it’s finish up your swipes an’ follow me!<lb/>
    Oh, ’ark to the big drum callin’,<lb/>
      Follow me — follow me ’ome!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>    ’Is mare she neighs the ’ole day long,</l>
                  <l>      She paws the ’ole night through,</l>
                  <l>An’ she won’t take ’er feed ‘cause o’ waitin’ for ’is step,</l>
                  <l>      Which is just what a beast would do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    ’Is girl she goes with a bombardier</l>
                  <l>      Before ’er month is through;</l>
                  <l>An’ the banns are up in church, for she’s got the beggar hooked,</l>
                  <l>      Which is just what a girl would do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    We fought ‘bout a dog — last week it were —</l>
                  <l>      No more than a round or two;</l>
                  <l>But I strook ’im cruel ’ard, an’ I wish I ’adn’t now,</l>
                  <l>      Which is just what a man can’t do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>    ’E was all that I ’ad in the way of a friend,</l>
                  <l>      An’ I’ve ’ad to find one new;</l>
                  <l>But I’d give my pay an’ stripe for to get the beggar back,</l>
                  <l>      Which it’s just too late to do.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">So it’s knock out your pipes an’ follow me!<lb/>
  An’ it’s finish off your swipes an’ follow me!<lb/>
    Oh, ’ark to the fifes a-crawlin’!<lb/>
      Follow me — follow me ’ome!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>      
                     <hi rend="italic">Take ’im away! ’E’s gone where the best men go.<lb/>
      Take ’im away! An’ the gun-wheels turnin’ slow.<lb/>
      Take ’im away! There’s more from the place ’e come.<lb/>
      Take ’im away, with the limber an’ the drum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">For it’s “Three rounds blank” an’ follow me,<lb/>
  An’ it’s “Thirteen rank” an’ follow me;<lb/>
    Oh, passin’ the love o’ women,<lb/>
      Follow me — follow me ’ome!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section40">
               <head>The Sergeant’s Weddin’.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>’E was warned agin’ ’er —</l>
                  <l>  That’s what made ’im look;</l>
                  <l>She was warned agin’ ’im-</l>
                  <l>  That is why she took.</l>
                  <l>Wouldn’t ’ear no reason,</l>
                  <l>  Went an’ done it blind;</l>
                  <l>We know all about ’em,</l>
                  <l>  They’ve got all to find!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Cheer for the Sergeant’s weddin’—<lb/>
    Give ’em one cheer more!<lb/>
  Gray gun-’orses in the lando,<lb/>
    An’ a rogue is married to, etc.</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>What’s the use o’ tellin’</l>
                  <l>  ’Arf the lot she’s been?</l>
                  <l>’E’s a bloomin’ robber,</l>
                  <l>                     
                     <hi rend="italic">An’</hi> ’e keeps canteen.</l>
                  <l>’Ow did ’e get ’is buggy?</l>
                  <l>  Gawd, you needn’t ask!</l>
                  <l>Made ’is forty gallon</l>
                  <l>  Out of every cask!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Watch ’im, with ’is ’air cut,</l>
                  <l>  Count us filin’ by —</l>
                  <l>Won’t the Colonel praise ’is</l>
                  <l>  Pop — u — lar — i — ty!</l>
                  <l>We ’ave scores to settle —</l>
                  <l>  Scores for more than beer;</l>
                  <l>She’s the girl to pay ’em —</l>
                  <l>  That is why we’re ’ere!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See the chaplain thinkin’?</l>
                  <l>  See the women smile?</l>
                  <l>Twig the married winkin’</l>
                  <l>  As they take the aisle?</l>
                  <l>Keep your side-arms quiet,</l>
                  <l>  Dressin’ by the Band.</l>
                  <l>Ho! You ’oly beggars,</l>
                  <l>  Cough be’ind your ’and!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now it’s done an’ over,</l>
                  <l>  ’Ear the organ squeak,</l>
                  <l>“<hi rend="italic">Voice that breathed o’er Eden</hi>”—</l>
                  <l>  Ain’t she got the cheek!</l>
                  <l>White an’ laylock ribbons,</l>
                  <l>  Think yourself so fine!</l>
                  <l>I’d pray Gawd to take yer</l>
                  <l>  ‘Fore I made yer mine!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Escort to the kerridge,</l>
                  <l>  Wish ’im luck, the brute!</l>
                  <l>Chuck the slippers after —</l>
                  <l>  [Pity ‘taint a boot!]</l>
                  <l>Bowin’ like a lady,</l>
                  <l>  Blushin’ like a lad —</l>
                  <l>’Oo would say to see ’em —</l>
                  <l>  Both are rotten bad!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Cheer for the Sergeant’s weddin’—<lb/>
    Give ’em one cheer more!<lb/>
  Gray gun-’orses in the lando,<lb/>
    An’ a rogue is married to, etc.</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section41">
               <head>The Jacket.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>Through the Plagues of Egyp’ we was chasin’ Arabi,</l>
                  <l>  Gettin’ down an’ shovin’ in the sun;</l>
                  <l>An’ you might ’ave called us dirty, an’ you might ha’ called us dry,</l>
                  <l>  An’ you might ’ave ’eard us talkin’ at the gun.</l>
                  <l>But the Captain ’ad ’is jacket, an’ the jacket it was new —</l>
                  <l>  (’Orse–Gunners, listen to my song!)</l>
                  <l>An’ the wettin’ of the jacket is the proper thing to do,</l>
                  <l>  Nor we didn’t keep ’im waiting very long!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>One day they give us orders for to shell a sand redoubt,</l>
                  <l>  Loadin’ down the axle-arms with case;</l>
                  <l>But the Captain knew ’is dooty, an’ he took the crackers out,</l>
                  <l>  An’ he put some proper liquor in its place.</l>
                  <l>An’ the Captain saw the shrapnel (which is six-an’-thirty clear).</l>
                  <l>  (’Orse–Gunners, listen to my song!)</l>
                  <l>“Will you draw the weight,” sez ’e, “or will you draw the beer?”</l>
                  <l>  An’ we didn’t keep ’im waitin’ very long.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">For the Captain</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then we trotted gentle, not to break the bloomin’ glass,</l>
                  <l>  Though the Arabites ’ad all their ranges marked;</l>
                  <l>But we dursn’t ’ardly gallop, for the most was bottled Bass,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we’d dreamed of it since we was disembarked.</l>
                  <l>So we fired economic with the shells we ’ad in ’and,</l>
                  <l>  (’Orse–Gunners, listen to my song!)</l>
                  <l>But the beggars under cover ’ad the impidence to stand,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we couldn’t keep ’em waitin’ very long.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">And the Captain</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>So we finished ’arf the liquor (an’ the Captain took champagne),</l>
                  <l>  An’ the Arabites was shootin’ all the while;</l>
                  <l>An’ we left our wounded ’appy with the empties on the plain,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we used the bloomin’ guns for pro-jec-tile!</l>
                  <l>We limbered up an’ galloped — there were nothin’ else to do —</l>
                  <l>  (’Orse–Gunners, listen to my song!)</l>
                  <l>An’ the Battery come a-boundin’ like a boundin’ kangaroo,</l>
                  <l>  But they didn’t watch us comin’ very long.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">As the Captain</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>We was goin’ most extended — we was drivin’ very fine,</l>
                  <l>  An’ the Arabites were loosin’ ’igh an’ wide,</l>
                  <l>Till the Captain took the glassy with a rattlin’ right incline,</l>
                  <l>  An’ we dropped upon their ’eads the other side.</l>
                  <l>Then we give ’em quarter — such as ’adn’t up and cut,</l>
                  <l>  (’Orse–Gunners, listen to my song!)</l>
                  <l>An’ the Captain stood a limberful of fizzy — somethin’ Brutt,</l>
                  <l>  But we didn’t leave it fizzing very long.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">For the Captain</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>We might ha’ been court-martialled, but it all come out all right</l>
                  <l>  When they signalled us to join the main command.</l>
                  <l>There was every round expended, there was every gunner tight,</l>
                  <l>  An’ the Captain waved a corkscrew in ’is ’and!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">But the Captain had ’is jacket</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section42">
               <head>The ’Eathen.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The ’eathen in ’is blindness bows down to wood an’ stone;</l>
                  <l>’E don’t obey no orders unless they is ’is own;</l>
                  <l>’E keeps ’is side-arms awful: ’e leaves ’em all about,</l>
                  <l>An’ then comes up the regiment an’ pokes the ’eathen out.</l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">All along o’ dirtiness, all along o’ mess,<lb/>
  All along o’ doin’ things rather-more-or-less,<lb/>
  All along of abby-nay,<ref target="#fn6">
                           <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
                        </ref> kul,<ref target="#fn7">
                           <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                        </ref> and hazar-ho,<ref target="#fn8">
                           <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <lb/>
  Mind you keep your rifle an’ yourself jus’ so!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>The young recruit is ’aughty —’e draf’s from Gawd knows where;</l>
                  <l>They bid ’im show ’is stockin’s an’ lay ’is mattress square;</l>
                  <l>’E calls it bloomin’ nonsense —’e doesn’t know, no more —</l>
                  <l>An’ then up comes ’is company an’ kicks ’em round the floor!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The young recruit is ’ammered —’e takes it very ’ard;</l>
                  <l>’E ’angs ’is ’ead an’ mutters —’e sulks about the yard;</l>
                  <l>’E talks o’ “cruel tyrants” ’e’ll swing for by-an’-bye,</l>
                  <l>An’ the others ’ears an’ mocks ’im, an’ the boy goes orf to cry.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The young recruit is silly —’e thinks o’ suicide;</l>
                  <l>’E’s lost ’is gutter-devil; ’e ’asn’t got ’is pride;</l>
                  <l>But day by day they kicks ’im, which ’elps ’im on a bit,</l>
                  <l>Till ’e finds ’isself one mornin’ with a full an’ proper kit.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Gettin’ clear o’ dirtiness, gettin’ done with mess,<lb/>
  Gettin’ shut o’ doin’ things rather-more-or-less;<lb/>
  Not so fond of abby-nay, kul, nor hazar-ho,<lb/>
  Learns to keep ’is rifle an’ ’isself jus’ so!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>The young recruit is ’appy —’e throws a chest to suit;</l>
                  <l>You see ’im grow mustaches; you ’ear ’im slap ’is boot;</l>
                  <l>’E learns to drop the “bloodies” from every word he slings,</l>
                  <l>An’ ’e shows an ’ealthy brisket when ’e strips for bars an’ rings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The cruel tyrant sergeants they watch ’im ’arf a year;</l>
                  <l>They watch ’im with ’is comrades, they watch ’im with ’is beer;</l>
                  <l>They watch ’im with the women, at the regimental dance,</l>
                  <l>And the cruel tyrant sergeants send ’is name along for “Lance.”</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ now ’e’s ’arf o’ nothin’, an’ all a private yet,</l>
                  <l>’Is room they up an’ rags ’im to see what they will get;</l>
                  <l>They rags ’im low an’ cunnin’, each dirty trick they can,</l>
                  <l>But ’e learns to sweat ’is temper an’ ’e learns to know ’is man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’, last, a Colour–Sergeant, as such to be obeyed,</l>
                  <l>’E leads ’is men at cricket, ’e leads ’em on parade;</l>
                  <l>They sees ’em quick an’ ’andy, uncommon set an’ smart,</l>
                  <l>An’ so ’e talks to orficers which ’ave the Core at ’eart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’E learns to do ’is watchin’ without it showin’ plain;</l>
                  <l>’E learns to save a dummy, an’ shove ’im straight again;</l>
                  <l>’E learns to check a ranker that’s buyin’ leave to shirk;</l>
                  <l>An’ ’e learns to make men like ’im so they’ll learn to like their work.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ when it comes to marchin’ he’ll see their socks are right,</l>
                  <l>An’ when it comes to action ’e shows ’em ’ow to sight;</l>
                  <l>’E knows their ways of thinkin’ and just what’s in their mind;</l>
                  <l>’E feels when they are comin’ on an’ when they’ve fell be’ind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’E knows each talkin’ corpril that leads a squad astray;</l>
                  <l>’E feels ’is innards ’eavin’, ’is bowels givin’ way;</l>
                  <l>’E sees the blue-white faces all tryin’ ’ard to grin,</l>
                  <l>An’ ’e stands an’ waits an’ suffers till it’s time to cap ’em in.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ now the hugly bullets come peckin’ through the dust,</l>
                  <l>An’ no one wants to face ’em, but every beggar must;</l>
                  <l>So, like a man in irons which isn’t glad to go,</l>
                  <l>They moves ’em off by companies uncommon stiff an’ slow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of all ’is five years’ schoolin’ they don’t remember much</l>
                  <l>Excep’ the not retreatin’, the step an’ keepin’ touch.</l>
                  <l>It looks like teachin’ wasted when they duck an’ spread an’ ’op,</l>
                  <l>But if ’e ’adn’t learned ’em they’d be all about the shop!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An’ now it’s “’Oo goes backward?” an’ now it’s “’Oo comes on?”</l>
                  <l>An’ now it’s “Get the doolies,” an’ now the captain’s gone;</l>
                  <l>An’ now it’s bloody murder, but all the while they ’ear</l>
                  <l>’Is voice, the same as barrick drill, a-shepherdin’ the rear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>’E’s just as sick as they are, ’is ’eart is like to split,</l>
                  <l>But ’e works ’em, works ’em, works ’em till ’e feels ’em take the bit;</l>
                  <l>The rest is ’oldin’ steady till the watchful bugles play,</l>
                  <l>An’ ’e lifts ’em, lifts ’em, lifts ’em through the charge that wins</l>
                  <l>          the day!</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">The ’eathen in ’is blindness bows down to wood an’ stone;<lb/>
  ’E don’t obey no orders unless they is ’is own;<lb/>
  The ’eathen in ’is blindness must end where ’e began,<lb/>
  But the backbone of the Army is the noncommissioned man!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <quote>
                  <p>  
                     <hi rend="italic">Keep away from dirtiness — keep away from mess.<lb/>
  Don’t get into doin’ things rather-more-or-less!<lb/>
  Let’s ha’ done with abby-nay, kul, an’ hazar-ho;<lb/>
  Mind you keep your rifle an’ yourself jus’ so!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <note xml:id="fn6">
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Not now.</note>
               <note xml:id="fn7">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi> To-morrow.</note>
               <note xml:id="fn8">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi> Wait a bit.</note>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section43">
               <head>The Shut-Eye Sentry.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>Sez the Junior Orderly Sergeant</l>
                  <l>  To the Senior Orderly Man:</l>
                  <l>“Our Orderly Orf’cer’s <hi rend="italic">hokee-mut</hi>,</l>
                  <l>  You ’elp ’im all you can.</l>
                  <l>For the wine was old and the night is cold,</l>
                  <l>  An’ the best we may go wrong,</l>
                  <l>So, ‘fore ’e gits to the sentry-box,</l>
                  <l>  You pass the word along.”</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Then it was “Rounds! What rounds?” at two of a frosty night,<lb/>
  ’E’s ’oldin’ on by the sergeant’s sash, but, sentry, shut your eye.<lb/>
An’ it’s “Pass! All’s well!” Oh, ain’t ’e rockin’ tight!<lb/>
  ’E’ll need an affidavit pretty badly by-an’-bye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The moon was white on the barricks,</l>
                  <l>  The road was white an’ wide,</l>
                  <l>An’ the Orderly Orf’cer took it all,</l>
                  <l>  An’ the ten-foot ditch beside.</l>
                  <l>An’ the corporal pulled an’ the sergeant pushed,</l>
                  <l>  An’ the three they wagged along,</l>
                  <l>But I’d shut my eyes in the sentry-box,</l>
                  <l>  So I didn’t see nothin’ wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Though it was “Rounds! What rounds?” O corporal, ’old ’im up!<lb/>
  ’E’s usin’ ’is cap as it shouldn’t be used, but, sentry, shut your<lb/>
          eye.<lb/>
An’ it’s “Pass! All’s well!” Ho, shun the foamin’ cup!<lb/>
  ’E’ll need</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>’Twas after four in the mornin’;</l>
                  <l>  We ’ad to stop the fun,</l>
                  <l>An’ we sent ’im ’ome on a bullock-cart,</l>
                  <l>  With ’is belt an’ stock undone;</l>
                  <l>But we sluiced ’im down an’ we washed ’im out,</l>
                  <l>  An’ a first-class job we made,</l>
                  <l>When we saved ’im smart as a bombardier</l>
                  <l>  For six o’clock parade.</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">It ’ad been “Rounds! What rounds?” Oh, shove ’im straight again!<lb/>
  ’E’s usin’ ’is sword for a bicycle, but, sentry, shut your eye.<lb/>
An’ it was “Pass! All’s well!” ’E’s called me “darlin’ Jane”!<lb/>
  ’E’ll need</hi>, etc.</p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>The drill was ’ard an’ ’eavy,</l>
                  <l>  The sky was ’ot an’ blue,</l>
                  <l>An’ ’is eye was wild an’ ’is ’air was wet,</l>
                  <l>  But ’is sergeant pulled ’im through.</l>
                  <l>Our men was good old trusties —</l>
                  <l>  They’d done it on their ’ead;</l>
                  <l>But you ought to ’ave ’eard ’em markin’ time</l>
                  <l>  To ’ide the things ’e said!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">For it was “Right flank — wheel!” for “’Alt, an’ stand at ease!”<lb/>
  An’ “Left extend!” for “Centre close!” O marker, shut your eye!<lb/>
An’ it was, “’Ere, sir, ’ere! before the colonel sees!”<lb/>
  So he needed affidavits pretty badly by-an’-bye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There was two-an’-thirty sergeants,</l>
                  <l>  There was corp’rals forty-one,</l>
                  <l>There was just nine ’undred rank an’ file</l>
                  <l>  To swear to a touch o’ sun.</l>
                  <l>There was me ’e’d kissed in the sentry-box</l>
                  <l>  (As I ’ave not told in my song),</l>
                  <l>But I took my oath, which were Bible truth,</l>
                  <l>  I ’adn’t seen nothin’ wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There’s them that’s ’ot an’ ’aughty,</l>
                  <l>  There’s them that’s cold an’ ’ard,</l>
                  <l>But there comes a night when the best gets tight,</l>
                  <l>  An’ then turns out the Guard.</l>
                  <l>I’ve seen them ’ide their liquor</l>
                  <l>  In every kind o’ way,</l>
                  <l>But most depends on makin’ friends</l>
                  <l>  With Privit Thomas A.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">When it is “Rounds! What rounds?” ’E’s breathin’ through ’is nose.<lb/>
  ’E’s reelin’, rollin’, roarin’ ripe, but, sentry, shut your eye.<lb/>
An’ it’s “Pass! All’s well!” An’ that’s the way it goes.<lb/>
  We’ll ’elp ’im for ’is mother, an’ ’e’ll ’elp us by-an’-bye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section44">
               <head>“Mary, Pity Women!”</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>You call yourself a man,</l>
                  <l>  For all you used to swear,</l>
                  <l>An’ leave me, as you can,</l>
                  <l>  My certain shame to bear?</l>
                  <l>  I ’ear! You do not care —</l>
                  <l>  You done the worst you know.</l>
                  <l>I ’ate you, grinnin’ there....</l>
                  <l>  Ah, Gawd, I love you so!</l>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Nice while it lasted, an’ now it is over —<lb/>
Tear out your ’eart an’ good-bye to your lover!<lb/>
What’s the use o’ grievin’, when the mother that bore you<lb/>
(Mary, pity women!) knew it all before you?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It aren’t no false alarm,</l>
                  <l>  The finish to your fun;</l>
                  <l>You — you ’ave brung the ’arm,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I’m the ruined one;</l>
                  <l>  An’ now you’ll off an’ run</l>
                  <l>  With some new fool in tow.</l>
                  <l>Your ’eart? You ’aven’t none....</l>
                  <l>  Ah, Gawd, I love you so!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">When a man is tired there is naught will bind ’im;<lb/>
All ’e solemn promised ’e will shove be’ind ’im.<lb/>
What’s the good o’ prayin’ for The Wrath to strike ’im,<lb/>
(Mary, pity women!) when the rest are like ’im?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ’ope for me or — it?</l>
                  <l>  What’s left for us to do?</l>
                  <l>I’ve walked with men a bit,</l>
                  <l>  But this — but this is you!</l>
                  <l>  So ’elp me Christ, it’s true!</l>
                  <l>  Where can I ’ide or go?</l>
                  <l>You coward through an’ through!...</l>
                  <l>  Ah, Gawd, I love you so!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">All the more you give ’em the less are they for givin’!<lb/>
Love lies dead, an’ you can not kiss ’im livin’.<lb/>
Down the road ’e led you there is no returnin’,<lb/>
(Mary, pity women!) but you’re late in learnin’.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You’d like to treat me fair?</l>
                  <l>  You can’t, because we’re pore?</l>
                  <l>We’d starve? What do I care!</l>
                  <l>  We might, but <hi rend="italic">this</hi> is shore:</l>
                  <l>  I want the name — no more —</l>
                  <l>  The name, an’ lines to show,</l>
                  <l>An’ not to be an ’ore....</l>
                  <l>  Ah, Gawd, I love you so!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">What’s the good o’ pleadin’, when the mother that bore you<lb/>
(Mary, pity women!) knew it all before you?<lb/>
Sleep on ’is promises an’ wake to your sorrow,<lb/>
(Mary, pity women!) for we sail tomorrow!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section45">
               <head>For to Admire.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <l>The Injian Ocean sets an’ smiles</l>
                  <l>  So sof’, so bright, so bloomin’ blue;</l>
                  <l>There aren’t a wave for miles an’ miles</l>
                  <l>  Excep’ the jiggle from the screw.</l>
                  <l>The ship is swep’, the day is done,</l>
                  <l>  The bugle’s gone for smoke an’ play;</l>
                  <l>An’ black agin’ the settin’ sun</l>
                  <l>  The Lascar sings, “<hi rend="italic">Hum deckty hai!</hi>”<ref target="#fn9">
                        <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </l>
               </epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">For to admire an’ for to see,<lb/>
      For to be’old this world so wide —<lb/>
    It never done no good to me,<lb/>
      But I can’t drop it if I tried!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <lg>
                  <l>I see the sergeants pitchin’ quoits,</l>
                  <l>  I ’ear the women laugh an’ talk,</l>
                  <l>I spy upon the quarter-deck</l>
                  <l>  The orficers an’ lydies walk.</l>
                  <l>I thinks about the things that was,</l>
                  <l>  An’ leans an’ looks acrost the sea,</l>
                  <l>Till, spite of all the crowded ship,</l>
                  <l>  There’s no one lef’ alive but me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The things that was which I ’ave seen,</l>
                  <l>  In barrick, camp, an’ action too,</l>
                  <l>I tells them over by myself,</l>
                  <l>  An’ sometimes wonders if they’re true;</l>
                  <l>For they was odd — most awful odd —</l>
                  <l>  But all the same now they are o’er,</l>
                  <l>There must be ’eaps o’ plenty such,</l>
                  <l>  An’ if I wait I’ll see some more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh, I ’ave come upon the books,</l>
                  <l>  An’ often broke a barrick rule,</l>
                  <l>An’ stood beside an’ watched myself</l>
                  <l>  Be’avin’ like a bloomin’ fool.</l>
                  <l>I paid my price for findin’ out,</l>
                  <l>  Nor never grutched the price I paid,</l>
                  <l>But sat in Clink without my boots,</l>
                  <l>  Admirin’ ’ow the world was made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be’old a cloud upon the beam,</l>
                  <l>  An’ ’umped above the sea appears</l>
                  <l>Old Aden, like a barrick-stove</l>
                  <l>  That no one’s lit for years an’ years!</l>
                  <l>I passed by that when I began,</l>
                  <l>  An’ I go ’ome the road I came,</l>
                  <l>A time-expired soldier-man</l>
                  <l>  With six years’ service to ’is name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My girl she said, “Oh, stay with me!”</l>
                  <l>  My mother ’eld me to ’er breast.</l>
                  <l>They’ve never written none, an’ so</l>
                  <l>  They must ’ave gone with all the rest —</l>
                  <l>With all the rest which I ’ave seen</l>
                  <l>  An’ found an’ known an’ met along.</l>
                  <l>I cannot say the things I feel,</l>
                  <l>  But still I sing my evenin’ song:</l>
               </lg>
               <quote>
                  <p>    
                     <hi rend="italic">For to admire an’ for to see,<lb/>
      For to be’old this world so wide —<lb/>
    It never done no good to me,<lb/>
      But I can’t drop it if I tried!</hi>
                  </p>
               </quote>
               <note xml:id="fn9">
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi> “I’m looking out.”</note>
            </div>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://www.ota.ox.ac.uk/Graphics/3297/003.png"
                        width="291px"
                        height="113px"/>
            </figure>
            <div>
               <head>L'Envoi</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Earth’s last picture is painted, and the tubes are twisted and</l>
                  <l>          dried,</l>
                  <l>When the oldest colours have faded, and the youngest critic has died,</l>
                  <l>We shall rest, and, faith, we shall need it — lie down for an æon or</l>
                  <l>          two,</l>
                  <l>Till the Master of All Good Workmen shall set us to work anew!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And those that were good shall be happy: they shall sit in a golden</l>
                  <l>          chair;</l>
                  <l>They shall splash at a ten-league canvas with brushes of comets’ hair;</l>
                  <l>They shall find real saints to draw from — Magdalene, Peter, and Paul;</l>
                  <l>They shall work for an age at a sitting and never be tired at all!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And only the Master shall praise us, and only the Master shall blame;</l>
                  <l>And no one shall work for money, and no one shall work for fame;</l>
                  <l>But each for the joy of the working, and each, in his separate star,</l>
                  <l>Shall draw the Thing as he sees It for the God of Things as They Are!</l>
               </lg>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="http://www.ota.ox.ac.uk/Graphics/3297/004.png"
                           width="359px"
                           height="206px"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

