<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to Mrs. Wallup: now in the train of Her Royal Highness, the Princess of Wales. As it was sent to her to the Hague. Written by Mrs. Susanna Centlivre.</title>
            <author>Centlivre, Susanna, 1667?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/3318</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106003179</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106003171</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K000663.000</idno>
            <idno type="BIBNO">CW3324703547</idno>
            <idno type="ECGR">0101502500</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	  Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
	</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to Mrs. Wallup: now in the train of Her Royal Highness, the Princess of Wales. As it was sent to her to the Hague. Written by Mrs. Susanna Centlivre.</title>
                  <author>Centlivre, Susanna, 1667?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8p. ; 2⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and sold by R. Burleigh, and A. Boulter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1715.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse.</note>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the Harvard University Houghton Library.</note>
                  <note>Foxon, C92</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCN1081.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:0101502500:1"/>
AN EPISTLE TO Mrs. WALLUP, Now in the TRAIN of Her Royal Highneſs, The Princeſs of <hi>WALES.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:0101502500:2"/>
AN EPISTLE TO Mrs. WALLUP, Now in the TRAIN of Her Royal Highneſs, The Princeſs of <hi>WALES. As it was ſent to her to the</hi> HAGUE. <hi>Written by Mrs.</hi> SUSANNA CENTLIVRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and Sold by <hi>R. Burleigh</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> and <hi>A. Boulter</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1715. (Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>)</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:0101502500:3"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</hi> What <hi>Muſe</hi> can ſpeak, what <hi>Pen</hi> diſplay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Pomp upon that happy <hi>Day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When Royal <hi>George</hi> our <hi>City</hi> dain'd to Grace,</l>
               <l>And from impending Slav'ry <hi>freed</hi> her <hi>Race?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His grateful Subjects round his Chariot hung,</l>
               <l>Long live the <hi>King</hi> was heard from ev'ry Tongue:</l>
               <l>Tranſporting Raptures all their Senſe employ,</l>
               <l>And Babes unborn, by Inſtinct leap'd for Joy;</l>
               <l>Ev'n thoſe whom Death ſtood ready to releaſe,</l>
               <l>Bleſt <hi>the Deliverer,</hi> and dy'd in Peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As <hi>Roman</hi> Sages charg'd their Sons to tell</l>
               <l>That at their Deaths they left <hi>Auguſtus</hi> well:</l>
               <l>So ſhall thoſe <hi>Patriots</hi> who with Care and Toil,</l>
               <l>Reſcu'd the <hi>Charters</hi> of our <hi>Britiſh Iſle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:0101502500:4"/>
At Fate's firſt Summons willingly obey,</l>
               <l>And to their weeping Wives and Children ſay,</l>
               <l>Ceaſe, ceaſe your Tears, no more of Grief be ſhown,</l>
               <l>We leave you <hi>Free,</hi> and <hi>George</hi> upon the Throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This <hi>Madam,</hi> we may write, but who can tell</l>
               <l>What mighty Tranſports in your Boſom dwell,</l>
               <l>To ſee the <hi>Scepter</hi> by that <hi>Hero</hi> ſway'd,</l>
               <l>To whom long ſince your ardent Vows were paid.</l>
               <l>When your unweary'd Zeal thrice croſt the Sea,</l>
               <l>Nor fear'd what Dangers might obſtruct your Way:</l>
               <l>Not led by Int'reſt, or Intrigues of State,</l>
               <l>(Avarice and Pride! Faults of the meanly great:)</l>
               <l>No private <hi>End</hi> by you was underſtood,</l>
               <l>But all your Wiſhes were the <hi>Publick Good.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh may the <hi>Princeſs</hi> you ſo oft have prais'd,</l>
               <l>And great Ideas of her Vertues rais'd,</l>
               <l>Give you that Preference due to your Deſert,</l>
               <l>And place you foremoſt in her Royal Heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Princeſs,</hi> ſaid I? Oh that charming Name,</l>
               <l>She comes! Who can th' exulting Joy ſuſtain?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Heroes</hi> did ſuch mighty Tranſports give,</l>
               <l>We ſcarce can view the <hi>Heroine,</hi> and Live.</l>
               <l>Oh Happy <hi>Britain!</hi> Oh propitious Day!</l>
               <l>That ſhall this <hi>Lady</hi> to thy <hi>Iſle</hi> convey:</l>
               <l>From <hi>her</hi> may ſuch a Race of <hi>Princes</hi> flow,</l>
               <l>'Till Heralds barren of new Titles grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:0101502500:5"/>
               <l>Come Royal <hi>Dame,</hi> and bleſs our longing Eyes,</l>
               <l>Fulfil our Hopes, conſummate all our Joys.</l>
               <l>Your Glorious <hi>Offspring</hi> let <hi>Britannia</hi> ſee,</l>
               <l>And make <hi>her</hi> happy, as you made <hi>her</hi> free.</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Babes</hi> are for our <hi>Church</hi>'s Safety given,</l>
               <l>The Darling Hoſtages 'twixt <hi>her</hi> and <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi>'s Court ſhall in full Luſtre ſhine,</l>
               <l>As heretofore in Bright <hi>Maria</hi>'s time:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maria</hi>'s Name ſtill ſounds in <hi>Britiſh</hi> Ears,</l>
               <l>Like Muſick tun'd from the Celeſtial Spheres.</l>
               <l>With thouſand Beauties was <hi>Maria</hi> grac'd,</l>
               <l>A thouſand Vertues in her Soul were plac'd;</l>
               <l>Such was her <hi>Form,</hi> and ſuch her mighty Mind,</l>
               <l>That ſcarcely Angels cou'd be more refin'd:</l>
               <l>She wanted only Immortality,</l>
               <l>To make the Angel with the Saint agree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sun which ſet in fair <hi>Maria</hi>'s Eyes,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Carolina</hi>'s does triumphant riſe,</l>
               <l>In <hi>her</hi> you'll find <hi>Maria</hi>'s Loſs retriev'd,</l>
               <l>That Charming <hi>Queen</hi> for whom ſo much we griev'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As when ſome happy Nuptial Knot's unty'd,</l>
               <l>And Death uncourteous does the Pair divide,</l>
               <l>The poor Wife, o'erpower'd by the Stroke of Fate,</l>
               <l>Mourns like a Turtle her departed Mate,</l>
               <l>Stretch'd on the Breathleſs Trunk her Tears ſhe vents,</l>
               <l>And utters to the Lifeleſs Clay Complaints:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:0101502500:6"/>
To draw her thence all Arguments are try'd,</l>
               <l>Nothing can raiſe her from her Husband's Side,</l>
               <l>Till ſome one Friend more lucky than the reſt,</l>
               <l>Lays the ſurviving Infant on her Breaſt:</l>
               <l>She views each Feature, dwells on ev'ry Grace,</l>
               <l>And in the Child ſurveys the Father's Face;</l>
               <l>Then the dear Relick ſnatches to her Arms,</l>
               <l>And all the Mother inſtantly returns.</l>
               <l>So, when the beautious, fair <hi>Maria</hi> dy'd,</l>
               <l>Sorrow o'erwhelm'd us like a riſing Tyde,</l>
               <l>Till Godlike <hi>WILLIAM</hi> ſtudying our Repoſe,</l>
               <l>Fix'd the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and reliev'd our Woes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whate'er th' <hi>Almighty</hi> gives to bleſs Mankind,</l>
               <l>We, or in Spring, or in the <hi>Autumn</hi> find,</l>
               <l>The Spring revives what Winter has decay'd,</l>
               <l>And in New Livery all the Earth's array'd.</l>
               <l>But tho' the Spring a Thouſand Sweets diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Indian</hi> Jeſſamine, and <hi>Syrian</hi> Roſe;</l>
               <l>The various Product of each fertile Soil,</l>
               <l>'Tis the Rich Autumn Crowns the Peaſant's Toil.</l>
               <l>So, tho' we ſee a New-Created Spring,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry Joy reviving in the KING;</l>
               <l>YOU in the PRINCESS will our Harveſt bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

