<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons humbly offered by the Company exercising the trade and mystery of upholders: against part of the bill for the better viewing, searching, and examining drugs, medicines, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Arbuthnot, John, 1667-1735.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/4148</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106011473</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106011473</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K043780.000</idno>
            <idno type="BIBNO">CW3307998902</idno>
            <idno type="ECMS">0135202200</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	  Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
	</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons humbly offered by the Company exercising the trade and mystery of upholders: against part of the bill for the better viewing, searching, and examining drugs, medicines, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Arbuthnot, John, 1667-1735.</author>
                  <author>Company of Upholders (London, England)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4],7,[1]p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed in the year,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1724.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Arbuthnot.</note>
                  <note>Half-title: 'Reasons humbly offer'd ..'.</note>
                  <note>A satirical petition to the House of Commons, charging that the prosperity of undertakers and clergy would be reduced if the bill were passed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT46417.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:0135202200:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS
Humbly Offer'd
By the Company Exerciſing the Trade
and Myſtery of UPHOLDERS, Againſt Part of the BILL, <hi>For the better
Viewing, Searching, and Examining
DRUGS, MEDICINES, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:0135202200:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS
Humbly Offered by the
COMPANY
Exerciſing the Trade and Myſtery of
<hi>UPHOLDERS,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt Part of the BILL
<hi>For the better Viewing, Searching, and
Examining DRUGS, MEDICINES, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed in the YEAR 1724.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:0135202200:3"/>
            <head>REASONS
Humbly Offer'd
By the Company exerciſing the
Trade and Miſtery of UPHOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS,
againſt Part of the
BILL, <hi>For the better Viewing,
Searching and Examining Drugs,
Medicines, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEING call'd upon by ſeveral Retailers
and Diſpenſers of Drugs and Medicines
about Town, to uſe our Endeavours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Bill now depending, <hi>for Viewing,</hi> &amp;c.
In Regard of our common Intereſt and in Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
to the ſaid Retailers and Diſpenſers of
Medicines (which we have always found to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:0135202200:4"/>
very effectual) we preſume to lay the following
Reaſons before the Publick, againſt the ſaid Bill.</p>
            <p>That the Company of Upholders <hi>are far
from being averſe to the giving of Drugs and
Medicines in general,</hi> provided they may be of
ſuch Qualities as we require, and adminiſter'd
by ſuch Perſons in whom our Company juſtly
repoſe the greateſt Confidence: And provided
they tend to the Encouragement of Trade, and
the Conſumption of the Woolen Manufacture
of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>We beg Leave to obſerve, that <hi>there hath
been no Complaint from any of the Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
and Citizens whom we have attended.</hi> Our
Practice, which conſiſts chiefly in outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications,
having been always ſo effectual, that
none of our Patients have been oblig'd to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo
a ſecond Operation. Excepting one Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman;
who, after her firſt Burial, having,
burthen'd her Husband with a new Brood of
poſthumous Children, her ſecond Funeral was
by us perform'd without any further Charges to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:0135202200:5"/>
the ſaid Husband of the deceas'd. And we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
hope, that one ſingle Inſtance of this Kind
(a Misfortune owing meerly to the Avarice of
a Sexton in cutting off a Ring) will not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted,
to any Want of Skill, or Care in our
Company.</p>
            <p>We humbly conceive, that this <hi>Power, by
this Bill lodged in the Cenſors of the College of
Phyſicians,</hi> to reſtrain any of His Majeſty's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
from diſpenſing, and well-diſpoſed Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
from taking what Medicines they pleaſe, <hi>is
a manifeſt Encroachment on the Liberty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
of the Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Company exerciſing the Trade and
Miſtery of Upholders, have an undiſputed Right
in and upon the Bodies of all and every the
Subjects of the Kingdom; we conceive the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
of this Bill, though not abſolutely depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
them of their ſaid Right, might keep them
out of Poſſeſſion by unreaſonable Delays, to the
great Detriment of our Company and their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous
Families.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:0135202200:6"/>
We hope it will be conſider'd that there are
Multitudes of neceſſitous Heirs and penurious
Parents, Perſons in pinching Circumſtances,
with numerous Families of Children, Wives that
have lived long, many robuſt aged Women
with great Jointures, elder Brothers with bad
Underſtandings, ſingle Heirs of great Eſtates,
whereby the Collateral Line are for ever exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
Reverſionary Patents, and Reverſionary
Promiſes of Preferments, Leaſes upon Single
Lives, and Play-debts upon joint Lives, and
that the Perſons ſo agrieved have no Hope of
being ſpeedily relieved any other Way, than by
the diſpenſing of Drugs and Medicines in the
Manner they now are; Burying alive being
judg'd repugnant to the know Laws of this
Kingdom.</p>
            <p>That there are many of the Deceaſed, who
by certain mechanical Motions and Powers are
carried about Town, who would have been put
into our Hands long before this Time by any
other well-ordered Government; by want of a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:0135202200:7"/>
due Police in this Particular, our Company
have been great Sufferers.</p>
            <p>That frequent Funerals contribute to preſerve
the Genealogies of Families, and the Honours
conferred by the Crown, (which are no where
ſo well illuſtrated as on this ſolemn Occaſion;)
to maintain neceſſitous Clergy, to enable the
Clerks to appear in decent Habits to officiate
on <hi>Sundays,</hi> to feed the great Retinue of ſober
and melancholy Men who appear at the ſaid
Funerals, and who muſt ſtarve without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
and regular Employment. Moreover we
deſire it may be remember'd, that by the paſſing
of this Bill the Nobility and Gentry will have
their old Coaches lie upon their Hands, which
are now employed by our Company.</p>
            <p>And we further hope that frequent Funerals
will not be diſcouraged (as is by this Bill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed)
it being the only Method left of <hi>carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
ſome People to Church.</p>
            <p>We are afraid that by the Hardſhips of this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:0135202200:8"/>
Bill our Company will be reduced to leave
their Buſineſs here, and <hi>practiſe at</hi> York <hi>and</hi>
Briſtol, <hi>where the free Uſe of bad Medicines
will be ſtill allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is therefore hoped that no ſpecious Pretence
whatſoever will be thought ſufficient to introduce
an Arbitrary and unlimited Power for People to
live</hi> (in Defiance of Art) as long as they can
by the Courſe of Nature, to the Prejudice of
our Company, and the Decay of Trade.</p>
            <p>That as our Company are like to ſuffer in
ſome meaſure by the Power given to Phyſicians
to diſſect the Bodies of Malefactors, we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
hope that the Manufacture of Caſes for
Skeletons will be reſerved ſolely to the Coffin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers.</p>
            <p>We likewiſe humbly preſume that the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts
of the ſeveral Trades and Profeſſions which
depend upon ours, may be regarded; ſuch as
that of the Makers of Hearſes, Coaches, Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins,
Epitaphs, and Bell-ropes; Stone-cutters,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:0135202200:9"/>
Feather-men and Bell-ringers; and eſpecially
the Manufacturers of Crapes; and the Makers
of Snuff, who uſe great Quantities of old-Coffins,
and who, conſidered in the Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of their Drugs, employ by far the greateſt
Number of Hands of any Manufacture of the
Kingdom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

